<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The new politicks of the court of France Under the reign of Levvis XIV. Wherein are to be seen all his intreagues, and his present manner of acting, in respect of all the potentates of Europe, to satisfie his ambition and grandeur. Made English from the original printed at Cologne, 1694.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1695</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 241 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 73 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A52961</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing N715A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R224183</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99834532</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99834532</idno>
            <idno type="VID">39033</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A52961)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 39033)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1817:15)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The new politicks of the court of France Under the reign of Levvis XIV. Wherein are to be seen all his intreagues, and his present manner of acting, in respect of all the potentates of Europe, to satisfie his ambition and grandeur. Made English from the original printed at Cologne, 1694.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 142 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed for Henry Rhodes, at the Star the corner of Bride-lane, in Fleet-street; and John Harris at the Harrow in the Poultry,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1695.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the University of Illinois (Urbana-Champaign Campus). Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Louis --  XIV, --  King of France, 1638-1715 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>France --  History --  Louis XIV, 1643-1715 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>France --  Politics and government --  1643-1715 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-02</date>
            <label>Kate Allen</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-02</date>
            <label>Kate Allen</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:39033:1"/>
            <p>THE <hi>New Politicks</hi> OF THE COURT OF FRANCE.</p>
            <p>Under the Reign of LEWIS XIV.</p>
            <p>WHEREIN Are to be ſeen all his Intreagues, and his preſent Manner of Acting, in reſpect of all the Potentates of <hi>Europe,</hi> to ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie his Ambition and Grandeur.</p>
            <p>Made <hi>Engliſh</hi> from the Original Printed at <hi>Cologne,</hi> 1694.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Henry Rhodes,</hi> at the <hi>Star</hi> the corner of <hi>Bride-lane,</hi> in <hi>Fleet-ſtreet;</hi> And <hi>John Harris</hi> at the <hi>Harrow</hi> in the <hi>Poultry.</hi> 1695.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div n="1-75" type="pages">
            <pb facs="tcp:39033:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:39033:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>THE <hi>Secret Intrigues</hi> OF THE COURT of <hi>FRANCE.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>THat which we call the Policy of a State, very nearly reſembles the Oeconomy of a Private Family: the Miniſters and Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſury-Officers of the One, are like the Steward and Caterer in the Other. And therefore it was, that an Ancient Author made no difficulty to ſay, <hi>That a Politick Court ſupported the State,</hi> in like manner as Oeconomy kept up the Grandeur and good Diſcipline of a ſingle Houſe. And as there are two ſorts of Oeconomy; the one Honeſt, and Praiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy, the other Mechanick and Sordid, which a Lunatick Perſon makes uſe of to pile up Riches any manner of way, thereby rendring himſelf odious to all Men of worth, 'tis very near the ſame thing with Policy, which may be alſo diſtinguiſh'd into two Claſſes, the one Lawful, the other Illegitimate. Which latter having only uſurp'd the Name of Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licy as Uſurpation has done, conceals it ſelf under the Appellation of Conqueſt, On the other ſide, True Policy is not only beneficial but commendable,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:39033:3"/> and permitted by the Laws of God and Man. She is the Daughter of Prudence, and the Prince that makes uſe of her Profitably and Sincerely, wins to himſelf by that means, the Admiration of Foreigners, as well as the Love and Reſpect of his own Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects; and frequently merits the Epithetes and Sir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>names of Great, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>iſe. O<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he other <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>de, Falſe Policy is meerly <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ly<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> cunning, wil<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ly Craft, or in a word downright Knavery and Cheat, always covetous of other Mens Goods, leaving no Stone un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn'd to aggrandize it ſelf at any rate whatever, come what will come of it, and tacking, according to the Proverb, <hi>The Foxes to the Lyons Skin.</hi> And theſe two different ſorts of Politicks, are as two Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſite Mirrours, that openly diſplay the Inſide of Princes, and ſhew their vertuous or wicked Incli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations. Nor can I forbear divulging to the World that the Court of <hi>France,</hi> ever ſince the Death of <hi>Hen.</hi> IV. has very much ſtudied the Practice of this ſame falſe Policy, on purpoſe to endeavour the Aggrandizing of her ſelf by Cheat and Uſurpation. And it may be ſaid to have had extraordinary Succeſs in this laſt Reign of <hi>Lewis</hi> XIV. under a falſe Idea of Conqueſt, having thereby augmented his Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nues to above two Thirds, and his Dominions above a Third Part; as might be eaſily prov'd, were it not viſible to all his Neighbours, or if his Neighbours were not ſenſible of it by woful Experience. And I do farther averr, that it was almoſt impoſſible for <hi>France</hi> to aggrandize her ſelf, and every way to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>large her Dominions as now we ſee her Limits ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended, or for her Monarch to raiſe himſelf to the preſent Pinacle of Grandeur, had ſhe not made a ſmart uſe of Violence, Uſurpation &amp; Breach of Faith.
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:39033:3"/> To which I may moreover add, the Hypocriſie and Deceit which the King of <hi>France</hi> has us'd in theſe latter times of Religion, on purpoſe to trample un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der foot and appropriate to himſelf the Eſtates of his Subjects; and the Treacherous Leagues he has made with Foreign Princes the more eaſily to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive 'em, and lay hold upon favourable Oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunities to invade their Territories, when leaſt they dream'd of any ſuch thing, but lay repoſing under the Security of a Peace; and all this to make him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf Maſter of their Dominions, when it was not in the Power of their Allies to aſſiſt 'em. Formerly indeed the <hi>Romans,</hi> who were Pagans, made uſe of the ſame Maxims and the ſame Stratagems to grow great upon their Neighbours, and to make them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves univerſal Maſters of the World. And now <hi>Lewis</hi> XIV. believes he cannot fail of obtaining the ſame Succeſs in his vaſt Expectations by treading the ſame laudable and worthy Steps.</p>
            <p>We have ſeen, that ſince the Church-Men, for moſt part greedy Heapers of Wealth, have intru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded into the Miniſtry of the Court of <hi>France,</hi> they have inſtill'd into the Government Sentiments like their own; that is to ſay, Sentiments of Uſurpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and Covetouſneſs, and a Liberty to do what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever they pleaſe: and as it is uſually ſeen, that a Maſter endeavours to bring up his Diſciples in his own Sentiments, and to be of his humour; ſo the Cardinals of <hi>Richlieu</hi> and <hi>Mazarine</hi> inſpir'd into <hi>Lewis</hi> XIII. and <hi>Lewis</hi> XIV. eager Deſires to make themſelves Great by Uſurpation, infuſing into 'em by all the ways imaginable, that a Prince was always cry'd up in his Undertakings, let 'em be good or bad provided that they proſper'd in their Enterprizes,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:39033:4"/> becauſe the People adore, and like the Sun-flower, turn toward the Glitter of Proſperity. That it was neither neceſſary nor beneficial for a King to be good, ſincere or merciful, only that 'twas ſufficient to appear ſo; in regard it was frequently dangerous to be ſo indeed; and for that it became a King above all things, to be always his own Maſter, by acting quite the contrary, when his Affairs requir'd it, whether it were to make himſelf Great, or for his own Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour; ſeeing that Men judge rather by the Eyes then by the Hands; every body having the Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to behold and conſider the Actions of Kings, but not to handle 'em; that is, to examine and dive into 'em; thoſe are Myſteries conceal'd, like the Oracles of the <hi>Pagans</hi> in times of Old. <hi>Lewis</hi> the XIV is ſo ſtrongly perſwaded that the People are only taken with Appearances, and gaudy Shew, that he affects no more then only to appear out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly honeſt, ſincere and Religious; when in reality and at the bottom of his Soul there is nothing of all this in him, as has been ſeen by all the World, ever ſince his firſt coming to the Crown. Seeing there is no better way to judge of the Inward Heart then by the Conſtancy of a Mans outward Actions; then which there can be nothing more plain, if we conſider the Opreſſions, the Exacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, the Cruelties committed during the whole Courſe of his Reign, as alſo his Uſurpations upon his Neighbours. Nor can the more Moderate of his Subjects alledge any thing fairer in his Excuſe, then only this, that his Deſign is to aggrandize himſelf; and that this is the ſureſt Means to render himſelf formidable as well to his Friends as to his Enemies both at home and abroad. Therefore to
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:39033:4"/> become Great according to <hi>Lewis</hi> the Fourteenth's Method, there was a Neceſſity for him to fail of his Word and Faith, ſo ſoon as he found the Keeping of either prejudicial to Him; to break his Alliances concluded and ſolemnly ſworn with his Neighbours and neareſt Relations, ſo ſoon as an Opportunity preſented it ſelf to invade their Territories. It may be ſaid, that this Monarch has made an excellent Uſe of Cardinal <hi>Mazarine</hi>'s Leſſons. For that ſame Prelate being both Crafty and Cunning, and ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what of a Cheat beſides, fail d not frequently to lay before his Prince the Example of <hi>Alexander</hi> VI. who notwithſtanding his being the Vicar of Chriſt, never forbore to falſify his Word, when he found there was a neceſſity for it: tho' never any man promis'd things with more ſolemn Oaths, and his Deceit prov'd ſucceſsful to him: Nor was <hi>Ferdinand,</hi> King of <hi>Caſtile</hi> and <hi>Aragon,</hi> beholding for his Grandeur to any thing, ſo much as to his Breach of Faith. The Emperour, <hi>Charles</hi> V. was always wont to ſwear <hi>By the Faith of a Man of Honour,</hi> when he had a Deſign to act contrary to what he promis'd. This <hi>Mazarine</hi> maintain'd as a Maxim never to be contradicted, and that it behov'd a Soveraign to obſerve this Rule, if ever he deſign'd Grandeur and Puiſſance, never to ſtick to, or govern himſelf according to the eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſh'd Laws of a Monarchy, when they agreed not with his preſent Intereſt, and the Politicks requiſite to enlarge his Power: becauſe the ſame Laws that were made in former Ages, were good and whole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſom at that time, but could not always ſo continue. As much as to ſay, that a King may break and trample over the Fundamental Law<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of a Realm, when they concur not with his Ambition and his
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:39033:5"/> Inclination to plunder his Neighbours, and ruin his Subjects. For this reaſon it is, that for ſome Years ſince, we have ſeen <hi>Lewis</hi> XIV. practiſe all theſe Maxims with a vehement Swing, but with little Circumſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction; conſulting neither the Laws of his King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, nor the Prerogatives of other Princes. How<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever obſerving this Rule, never to threaten before<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hand, but to execute his Deſign at the ſame time that he ſet forth his <hi>Manifeſto,</hi> that his Adverſary might have no time or leiſure to oppoſe his Tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent.</p>
            <p>Moreover, Men judge of the Inclinations of Princes by the Miniſters and Great Perſonages that are in favour near their Perſons: and the Deceas'd Prince of <hi>Orange, William</hi> the Firſt, was wont to ſay in his time, with great Reaſon and upon ſolid Grounds, That a True Judgment might be given of the Natural Diſpoſition of <hi>Philip</hi> II. King of <hi>Spain</hi> by the Cruelties which the Duke of <hi>Alva,</hi> his Chief Miniſter committed without fear of puniſhment in the <hi>Low-Countries.</hi> If it may be lawful to ſay the ſame thing of <hi>Lewis</hi> XIV, What Sentiment ought we to have of that Prince? If we look narrowly into the Inclinations and Proceedings of the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters that have ſerv'd him all the whole time of his Reign, to begin from <hi>Mazarine</hi> till this very time, we ſhall find 'em to have been all Birds of Prey, and moſt Cruel and Inſatiable Blood ſuckers of the People, Cardinal <hi>Richlieu</hi> was the Firſt who laid the Foundations of this Policy now practis'd by the Court of <hi>France:</hi> For that ſame Miniſter abuſing the Simplicity of <hi>Lewis</hi> XIII. made himſelf abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute Maſter in the Kingdom. He was naturally Vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent, nor could he endure any Companion; all
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:39033:5"/> People muſt ſubmit to Him; He Exil'd, and Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſon'd; he cunningly got rid of the Baron <hi>d'Ancre,</hi> of Monſieur <hi>de Thou</hi> and <hi>Cinqmarc;</hi> choſe rather to eſtabliſh the Security of his Perſon and his Fortune by Rigour and Violence, then to hazard either by Clemency, or by too much Complacency with thoſe that were belov'd by the King, and ſo he triumph'd over all, even over the Proteſtant Party, which was very numerous in <hi>France,</hi> and which he endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour'd to oppreſs by all manner of ways, againſt the Edicts of Pacification, and ruin'd 'em all by ruining <hi>Rochell;</hi> which that he might the better bring to paſs, he deceiv'd the <hi>Engliſh</hi> and <hi>Hollanders,</hi> who in good Policy were bound to have ventur'd all to have preſerv'd that Important Place, which was another State within the State it ſelf, and was a kind of Sanctuary and Place of Retreat for all the Malecontents of the Court. And it may be ſaid that the Loſs of that City was the Source of all the Calamities that befell <hi>Charles</hi> the I. King of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land.</hi> For <hi>France</hi> not only rais'd the Tempeſt in the two Kingdoms of <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Scotland:</hi> ſent Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney into <hi>England</hi> to Kindle the Fire, and feed the Civil War, but encourag'd <hi>Oliver</hi> to lay hands upon the Perſon of the King: in hopes at that time to bring down the Power of that Formidable Monar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chy by Sea, as is eaſie to judge by the Entertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment which the Court of <hi>France</hi> gave to the Princes of the Royal Family of <hi>England</hi> in that Conjuncture.</p>
            <p>Moreover after what a Treacherous manner did <hi>France</hi> act with the Old Duke of <hi>Lorrain,</hi> that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> might have an Advantage to uſurp his Country. For Cardinal <hi>Richlieu</hi> under pretence of Friendſhip drew him to <hi>Lion,</hi> where <hi>Lewis</hi> the XIII then lay with
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:39033:6"/> a Powerful Army, under a falſe pretence, that it believ'd him to come and pay his Reſpects to that Monarch. Thither the Prince, ſuſpecting nothing but honeſt and fair dealing, repair'd, and was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiv'd at firſt with Extraordinary Honour and Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vility, not only by the King and the Cardinal, but by all the Grandees of the Court, who were or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der'd to treat him Splendidly. But that was but the Bait to draw him on: for when the poor Duke, laden with the Honours of the Court, and ſatisfi'd with his Kind Reception, was about to return home, he was ſtopp'd by the Cardinal's Order; nor could he procure his Releaſe, but by delivering back into the hands of <hi>France</hi> a great part of his Territories, which afterwards occaſion'd the loſs of all the reſt, under pretence that the Prince was an active ſtirring Soldier, and devoted to the Houſe of <hi>Auſtria.</hi> But indeed, becauſe the Policy of the Court of <hi>France</hi> could not brook ſo near her a So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veraign Prince, whoſe Territories were a Goad in her ſides, and might ſerve for an Inlet into <hi>France</hi> out of <hi>Germany.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now in regard it is the Policy of a Miniſter of State, to the end he may be lamented and deſir'd after his Death, to juſtifie his Conduct in the Eyes of the People, <hi>Richlieu</hi> was willing to have for his Succeſſour a Miniſter that ſhould out do him, and finiſh what he had begun: therefore he recommen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded Cardinal <hi>Mazarine,</hi> an <hi>Italian</hi> by Birth, and of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ean Extraction, naturally covetous, and deceitful <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> whatever he undertook, covering himſelf with the Foxes Skin, the better to deceive others and play his own part, not caring for whatever People ſaid of him, nor what Miſchief was laid to his
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:39033:6"/> charge, ſo he could bring about his Grand Deſign, which was to get Money; ſo that all the whole time of his Miniſtry he was call'd <hi>The Horſleech of the People.</hi> By good luck, he came to his Miniſtry during the Regency of a Credulous Queen and a Young King, whom he Chriſten'd, that he might acquire to himſelf the more Reſpect and Venera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. It was eaſie for him both to imprint in the mind of this Young Prince, and inſtill into him Precepts according to his own Humour, which were to Sacrifice every thing to his own Intereſt; Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, Word, Alliances, Edicts, Promiſes, Oaths, when all theſe Vertues were oppoſite to his Aggran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dizement: That it behov'd a Prince that would be great, to accommodate himſelf to the Neceſſity of Affairs: that it was ſufficient for a Prince to be Vertuous, when he could not diſpence with being otherwiſe: that it was good and commendable to know what was juſt and honeſt, but not always ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pedient to practiſe it. That there were ſome Vices which no way hinder'd a Prince from Governing well: that <hi>Solomon</hi> was ſubject to Women, yet look'd upon to be the Greateſt and Wiſeſt of all Kings: for that there is always a Diſtinction to be made between the Domeſtick and Publick Life of a Prince, his Royal and his Private Vertues. Cardinal <hi>Mazarine</hi> having thus found out the Geni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us of his Diſciple, 'twas an eaſie thing for him to imprint in his Mind theſe New Lectures of Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licy, which afterwards ſerv'd for a Baſis and Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation to the Reign of <hi>Lewis</hi> XIV. who toget<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> with the Queen-Mother, out of pure Gratitude de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liver'd into the Cardinal's hands the Keys of all the Favours and Honours of his Kingdom, upheld him
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:39033:7"/> in deſpite of all the Princes of the Blood, and not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding all the earneſt Importunities of the Parliament and People, underwent all the Dangers of a Civil War for ſome Years; and not being able to live without the Cardinal's Preſence, the King ſent for him twice out of Baniſhment, and receiv'd him with thoſe Honours that were no way due to him, even to the going ſeveral Leagues to meet him, and to expreſs his exceſſive Joy for his Return by mutual Embraces. I ſhall not here enlarge upon the Authority and Power which that Italian Cardinal had in <hi>France;</hi> 'tis ſufficient to ſay, That the King, during his Minority, had all the Deference and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect for that Prelate which a Son could have for a Father, and that it was the Cardinal who only reign'd in <hi>France.</hi> In lieu of which, he promis'd the King and Queen, That he would make him the Greateſt Monarch in <hi>Europe<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> In order whereunto, he was to do<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Two things. The Firſt, was, To heap up Treaſure, and augment his Revenues. The Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond, was, To lay aſide all Scruples of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, when the main Concern was, the Aggran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dizing his Kingdoms. The firſt Tryal of Skill which the Cardinal made in the behalf of <hi>France,</hi> wa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> during his Nunciature when the Peace was concluded at <hi>Chi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>iaſc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> where the crafty wilely Mi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>iſter deceiv'd the Pope his Maſter, the Princes of <hi>Ital<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> and the King of <hi>Spain,</hi> in favour of the French Court; and ſo well Cully'd the Duke of <hi>S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> that he wreſted out of his Hands that Impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap> Place of <hi>Pigne<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ol,</hi> to deliver it into the Hands <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> which was an Acquiſition that all the King's Money and Power could not obtain before, though he had had an aking Tooth for it a long
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:39033:7"/> time. And this ſame Cheat, and cunning piece of Knavery it was, though the Court of <hi>France</hi> paid for it in good Ready-Money, that purchas'd him the Good-Will of all the Court of <hi>France,</hi> and the Friendſhip of Cardinal <hi>Richlieu;</hi> which <hi>Mazarine</hi> ſtill improv'd, and kept tite by Preſents which he ſent him out of <hi>Italy,</hi> from time to time: and ſo well he underſtood to inveigle all the reſt, that he was call'd into <hi>France</hi> in the Year 1639. where, a little time after his arrival, the Death of Father <hi>Joſeph</hi> the Capuchin, became the Life of <hi>Ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>arine.</hi> This Capuchin was he who ſerv'd Cardinal <hi>Richlieu</hi> in all his Intrigues both within and without the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom; and who was ſent into <hi>England,</hi> during the Reign of <hi>Charles</hi> I. to ſow Diviſion, and raiſe a Civil War, which coſt that Nation Rivers of Blood. So that the Capuchin had good reaſon to ſay, at his return out of <hi>England,</hi> That he had ſet Fire to thoſe Sparkles which would kindle ſuch a Flame as would not eaſily be extinguiſh'd: in Acknowledgment of which, the Court of <hi>France</hi> promis'd to get him a Cardinal's Cap to cover his Bald Pace. But he was not ſo happy as to ſee himſelf clad in Purple, Dea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> ſeizing him in the Habit of a Saint of a Franciſcan. After which, the Court of <hi>France</hi> bent all her Sol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licitations in favour of <hi>Ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>arine.</hi> To which Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinal <hi>Richlieu</hi> was the more willing to give his Conſent, as being glad to ſee himſelf ſucceeded in the Miniſtry by a Perſon of no leſs Rank then he was; who, though he were inferiour to him in Birth, yet was his Equal in Dignity, Both Princes of the Church; yet not without ſome ſecret Jealouſies be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween 'em. But the King and Queen favour'd him, in Conſideration of the Buſineſs of <hi>Pignerol,</hi> and his
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:39033:8"/> declar'd Devotion for the Intereſts of <hi>France;</hi> ſo that he was advanc'd to the Purple toward the End of the Year 1641. Immediately after his Promotion, he went to take Poſſeſſion of the Principality of <hi>Sedan,</hi> which the two Cardinals had wreſted from the Houſe of <hi>Bouillon</hi> by Violence; foraſmuch as that Principality border'd too near upon <hi>France,</hi> and alſo durſt make Head againſt it, but at a time when <hi>France</hi> was not ſo powerful as now it is. 'Tis true, that the Duke of <hi>Bouillon, Frederick Maurice,</hi> who was then Sovereign of the Place, had very much contributed to the loſs of it, by changing his Religion, upon his marrying the Counteſs of <hi>Berghe.</hi> For being at that time Governor of <hi>Maeſtricht,</hi> and in the Service of the States of the United Provinces, whoſe Protection warranted his Territories from all Aſſaults of <hi>France;</hi> yet finding himſelf no longer acceptable to the Prince of <hi>Orange,</hi> his near Kinſman, nor to the States them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, he deſir'd leave to lay down his Commiſſion and retire to <hi>Sedan,</hi> there to lead a private and quiet Life, and wholly to employ himſelf within his Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipality to the Propagation of the Roman Religion, which he had embrac'd; in which Employment he made ſome Progreſs during ſome Years. After which, he met with Buſineſs much more conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> by reaſon of the Refuge which he gave to the Count of <hi>Soiſſons,</hi> one of the Princes of the Blood, and who was retir'd in diſcontent from the Court of <hi>France,</hi> by reaſon of ſome Quarrel with Cardinal <hi>Richlieu;</hi> and this Count was follow'd by the Duke of <hi>Guiſe.</hi> Now the Duke of <hi>Bouillon</hi> thought to have avoided all Occaſion of Trouble, by giving notice to the Court of <hi>France</hi> of the Retreat of thoſe two Princes: but the Cardinal, a ſubtle and crafty
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:39033:8"/> Politician, ſeeing he could not hinder it, perſuaded the King to approve what he had done, till an Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity of Revenge preſented it ſelf, as it appear'd not long after by the King's taking the Field, in order to beſiege the City of <hi>Sedan.</hi> Nor had the Duke, at that time, any other way to preſerve him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, but by clapping up a League in all haſte with the Emperor and <hi>Spain,</hi> by which they were to aſſiſt him againſt <hi>France</hi> with Seven thouſand Men, and Two hundred thouſand Crowns in Ready-Money. But the Emperor only perform'd his Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe, and ſent him ſome Forces under the Conduct of General <hi>d'Amboi.</hi> Nevertheleſs, the Germans, together with about Four thouſand Men which the Duke of <hi>Bouillon</hi> had rais'd at his Charges, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feated the French Army under the Command of <hi>Chatillon;</hi> the Fruit of which Victory was, the Taking of <hi>Doncheri,</hi> not far from <hi>Sedan.</hi> And this lucky Beginning of the Duke made the Court of <hi>France</hi> begin to look about 'em, as being afraid leſt that petty War ſhould kindle a greater. Thereupon the Duke of <hi>Brezé</hi> was ſent the ſame way with Five and twenty thouſand Men; and the Cardinal perſuaded the King, and all the Court, to march as far as <hi>Rethel.</hi> But unfortunately for the Duke of <hi>Bouillon, Lamboy</hi> quitted him, with all his Men, being order'd to march to the Relief of <hi>Aire,</hi> which the French had beſieg'd. So that the Duke finding himſelf conſtrain'd to ſhut himſelf up within the Walls of <hi>Sedan,</hi> and ſeeing himſelf beſieg'd, began to think of an Accommoda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, ſo much the rather, becauſe the Count of <hi>Soiſſons,</hi> who had been the Occaſion of the War, had ſhot himſelf in the Head with a Piſtol Bullet. This was no more then what <hi>France</hi> deſir'd, as having
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:39033:9"/> at that time a War with <hi>Spain,</hi> ſeveral diſcontented Princes and Lords within the Kingdom, who waited only for an Opportunity to riſe, and the Siege of <hi>Aire</hi> begun; uncertain therefore of Succeſs, and having ſo many Irons in the Fire, ſhe durſt not ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture the beſieging of <hi>Sedan,</hi> which they were con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinc'd that the Duke would defend with the laſt drop of his Blood; beſides that he had Great Men that took his Part at Court, as not being willing that Place ſhould fall into the King's Hands, which, upon many Occaſions, ſerv'd 'em for a Retiring Place. Wherefore being alſo no leſs deſirous to ſpite Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinal <hi>Richlieu,</hi> who was look'd upon as the firſt Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor of that War, they perſuaded the King, who was advanc'd as far as <hi>Meziere,</hi> to hearken to an Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commodation. Thereupon the Cardinal ſeeing it was not to be avoided, offer'd his Mediation to the Duke of <hi>Bouillon,</hi> to the end that the Affair paſſing through his Hands, the Duke might think himſelf beholding to him for this Kindneſs, though his De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign were to ruine the Duke ſome other way. To which purpoſe, he made great Proteſtations to the Duke, who took all for Gold that gliſter'd; and being but a new Catholick, believ'd that what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever that ſame Prelate and Prince of the Church aſſur'd him, was ſincere, and truly honeſt. But whatever Proteſtation his Eminency made, he had always a Reſerve which he kept cloſe in his Breaſt: and the better to cover his Deſign, and ſhew his Good-Will, he would needs enter into a Treaty, as a Security for the Duke's Sincerity; and a Gauranty on the King's behalf, That His Majeſty would per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form the Agreement to the leaſt Tittle of the Stipu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation, the better to lull the Duke aſleep, and draw
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:39033:9"/> him to the Court. Thereupon the Articles being ſign'd on both Sides, the Duke went forthwith to pay his Reſpects to the King at <hi>Meziere,</hi> where he was entertain'd with Court-Holy-Water, fair Words and Complements, and receiv'd by the King, the Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinal, and all the Lords, with all the Honours ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginable due to his Dignity. The Cardinal alſo gave him large Demonſtrations of Friendſhip, and made him extraordinary Promiſes, on purpoſe to engage him to have a Confidence in him, and make him believe that he had forgot the injurious <hi>Manifeſto</hi> which the Duke had printed againſt him. Yet all this was nothing elſe but Snare and Decoy. For his Eminency told the King, in the preſence of all the Court, That he could not do better then to entruſt an Army under the Command of the Duke of <hi>Bouillon,</hi> as one that ſo well deſerv'd the Honour, ſeeing that with a handful of wretched Germans he had beaten the Army of <hi>France;</hi> ſo that there was nothing which he might not well expect from his Valour and Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience, when he ſhould once come to Head the Valour of the French. This the Duke took in good earneſt, and ſo fell into the Snare; and though he had been forewarn'd by the Cardinal's Enemies, that the more Affection and Kindneſs that Miniſter ſhew'd, the leſs he was to be truſted; yet he was ſo eaſily wrought upon, as to accept the Command of an Army in <hi>Italy;</hi> and that was the very Place where the Cardinal was deſirous to keep him. For being in that Poſt, he forgot himſelf to that degree, as during the Sickneſs of <hi>Lewis</hi> XIII. to give the Duke of <hi>Orleance</hi> a Letter of Credence to be admitted into <hi>Sedan,</hi> together with the Queen-Mother, and the Children of <hi>France,</hi> under pretence of retiring
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:39033:10"/> thither after the King's Death, to avoid the Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion of the Cardinal, tho' the Count of <hi>d'Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bijoux,</hi> who went to him in <hi>Italy,</hi> promis'd him with great Oaths and Imprecations, that he would never deliver the Letter, unleſs there ſhould be an Abſolute Neceſſity. But the King eſcap'd that Sickneſs, and the Cardinal having notice of every thing to the ſmalleſt Circumſtance, gave him an account of every particular, and thought it a favourable Oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity to revenge himſelf for what was paſt, and to put the Principality of <hi>Sedan</hi> into the Hands of <hi>France</hi> without the Effuſion of Blood. For he ſeldom ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parated the Remembrance of an Injury and the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire of Revenge. It happen'd at the ſame time that the Duke of <hi>Orleance</hi> finding his Brother very Infirm and ſickly, and believing that during the Minority of the Young King, when the Cardinal would have all the Power in his hands, he ſhould lead but an ill life in the Court of <hi>France,</hi> and ſeeing himſelf ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pos'd to the Reſentment of his Adverſary, he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thought himſelf of making a League with the <hi>Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niards</hi> by the mediation of a Gentleman, whoſe Name was <hi>Fourraille,</hi> whom he ſent to <hi>Madrid.</hi> But the Cardinal having got an Inkling of it, ſent his Secretary <hi>Chavigni,</hi> privately to give the King no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice of it, and in the mean time he left no Stone unturn'd to diſcover the Contents of the Treaty that had been concluded at <hi>Madrid;</hi> and he ſet ſo many Engines at work, that he found a way to get a Copy of it from ſome Secretary to the Duke of <hi>Orleance.</hi> So ſoon as he had read it, he ſent it to the King by the ſame <hi>Chavigni,</hi> and order'd him to aſſure his Majeſty that the Copy was drawn from the Original it ſelf; and for this ſame Piece it was that
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:39033:10"/> 
               <hi>Cinqmarc</hi> and <hi>du Thou</hi> were apprehended, and that the King order'd his Brother the Duke of <hi>Orleance</hi> to be very narrowly watch'd, who finding it Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible for him to make his Eſcape out of <hi>France,</hi> took a Reſolution to ſubmit himſelf to the King's Mercy, and implore his Pardon; and wrote a very ſubmiſſive Letter to the Cardinal, which he ſent him by one of his Favourites; wherein he ſet forth his Repentance in very moving Expreſſions, and his deſire to be beholding for the Favour of his Reconciliation with the King to his Eminency, who willingly embrac'd the Opportunity of gaining the Duke of <hi>Orleance</hi>'s Friendſhip, and of having at his Beck an Inſtrument to ruine the Duke of <hi>Bouillon.</hi> Thereupon he made the Duke of <hi>Orleance</hi>'s Peace with the King, upon Condition that he ſhould de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liver into his hands the Original of the Treaty. But the King's Brother proteſted that he had burn'd the Original, and had only kept a Copy ſign'd with his own Hand, and Counter-ſign'd by the Secretary of his Commands; by vertue of which Copy both <hi>Cinqmarc</hi> and <hi>de Thou</hi> were both arraign'd, and the Fatal End they came to is well known. But to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn to the Duke of <hi>Bouillon,</hi> you are to underſtand that <hi>Fontraille,</hi> who was ſent into <hi>Spain</hi> to conclude the Treaty, that he might bring it the ſooner to paſs, and imprint a higher Opinion of the Buſineſs in the Court of <hi>Madrid,</hi> would needs inſert the Duke of <hi>Bouillon</hi>'s Name in the Treaty without his Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge; and promis'd that he ſhould not only ratifie it, but allow <hi>Sedan</hi> for a Place of Refuge; tho' the Duke never ratify'd the Treaty, nor ever caus'd his Name to be inſerted; but quite the contrary had always oppos'd it, when the Duke of <hi>Orleance</hi>
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:39033:11"/> had formerly made ſome Overtures to him of the ſame nature. However there needed no more to ruine him; ſo that the Cardinal diſpatch'd away a Cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rier forthwith into <hi>Italy,</hi> with Orders for ſeizing his Perſon, which was done at <hi>Caſal</hi> by the General Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers, who commanded under him, from whence he was conducted by a numerous Convoy to the Caſtle of <hi>Pierre-en-Cize.</hi> And there it was that the Duke firſt underſtood, That he had been compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hended in the Treaty of <hi>Madrid,</hi> of which the Duke of <hi>Orleance</hi> had given him a Copy ſign'd with his own Hand; and that he at the ſame time had diſcover'd the Queen's and the Duke's Deſign to retire to <hi>Sedan,</hi> upon the King's Deceaſe. The crafty Cardinal obſerv'd by this Confeſſion how much he was fear'd and dreaded, which ſerv'd to render him more abſolute then ever, and impower'd him to revenge himſelf of his Enemies more loftily and more in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>exorably. For whatever Excuſe the Duke of <hi>Bouillon</hi> could make, and tho' it could never be prov'd that he ever ſign'd or ratify'd the Treaty, or gave any order for the inſerting of his Name there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, there was no other Choice for him to make, but either to loſe his Head or his Principality of <hi>Sedan.</hi> Which was no more then what <hi>France</hi> had ſought a long time, and for the bringing of which to paſs, there was no foul Play which the Miniſter had not put in Practiſe, no Snare that he had not laid to entrap the Innocent. The Dutcheſs of <hi>Bouillon,</hi> ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving notice of her Husband's Impriſonment, and of the danger he was in of his Life, ſent her Siſter in Law to Court, to let the Cardinal know, that if the Duke were put to death, ſhe would deliver <hi>Sedan</hi> to the <hi>Spaniards,</hi> to which purpoſe ſhe had already
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:39033:11"/> ſent to <hi>Bruſſells</hi> to ſollicit their Approach to the Town. But Mademoiſelle <hi>de Bouillon,</hi> arriving at the Court of <hi>France,</hi> and underſtanding that <hi>du Thou</hi> had been condemn'd for only being privy to, and concealing <hi>Cinqmarc</hi>'s Deſign, chang'd her note, and was ſo far from delivering the Dutcheſſes Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naces to the Cardinal, according to her Inſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, that ſhe told the Cardinal ſhe had Orders to enter into a Negotiation, and to engage for the Life and Liberty of her Brother. This was that which the Cardinal expected, and therefore with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out giving her any time to recollect her ſelf, the Treaty was concluded, That the Dutcheſs ſhould de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liver <hi>Sedan</hi> to the King of <hi>France,</hi> and that the Duke her Husband ſhould be put into poſſeſſion of other Lands of equal value in the Kingdom; and that at the ſame time that the French Garriſon ſhould enter the Town, the Priſoner ſhould be releas'd. Thereupon, Cardinal <hi>Richlieu</hi> not being able to go himſelf, ſent his Coadjutour in the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtry, who took poſſeſſion of it, and ſecur'd it to all Intents and Purpoſes. Thus that Important City which had withſtood the King, fell into his Hands, partly through the ill Conduct of the Duke of <hi>Bouillon,</hi> but chiefly through the Snares which the Policy of <hi>France</hi> laid for him, ever ſince he quitted his Religion and the Service of the States. For in good Policy they ought to have preſerv'd that City which gave Protection to the Proteſtant Party.</p>
            <p>The Death of the Cardinal happening in one and the ſame year, the Queen being declar'd Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent, and Duke of <hi>Orleance</hi> Chief of the Council, the Duke of <hi>Bouillon</hi> returrn'd to Court, flattering himſelf with being reſtor'd to his Dominions, conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:39033:12"/> that his Misfortune did not befall him, but for the good Services which he was ready to have done thoſe Two Illuſtrious Perſons, that now ſate at the Helm of State, and who had engag'd him without his Knowledge. But when he came to Court, he only found a change of the Regency, but not of the Miniſtry, which was ſtill cunning and wilely: For <hi>Mazarine,</hi> who ſucceeded <hi>Richlieu</hi> in the Government, out-did his Predeceſſor. He found that the Diſciple knew more then the Maſter; that he had a double portion of Avarice and Self-Intereſt; that Italian Knavery had ſucceeded French Refinedneſs, and that he had no mind to let go the Prey which he already held faſt in his Gripes, and for which he had labour'd conjoyntly with his Predeceſſour. 'Tis true, that when the Duke of <hi>Bouillon</hi> firſt ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riv'd, he receiv'd a world of Complements from the Queen, the Duke of <hi>Orleance,</hi> and all the Court; but when he came to talk of Buſineſs, all that Court<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip vaniſh'd, nor could he obtain ſo much as Audience either of the Queen or the Duke of <hi>Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leance,</hi> till at length by dint of Preſſing Importunity he got ſo much favour, that the Abbot <hi>de la Riviere,</hi> a Favourite of <hi>Orleance</hi>'s was appointed to conferr with him about his Pretenſions; and that meerly to be ridd of him: <hi>Bouillon</hi> therefore ſeeing he could do no better, fell upon the Matter with the Abbot, and told him, That he was willing to fulfill the Treaty made with <hi>Lewis</hi> XIII, but that the Evacu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation, the Verification in Parliament, and ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny other Formalities abſolutely requiſite, would infallibly take up a tedious Space of ſeveral Years: therefore till all thoſe Ceremonies were at an end, that 'twas but juſt that <hi>Sedan</hi> ſhould be reſtor'd him
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:39033:12"/> to be ſurrender'd back into the King's Hands, ſo ſoon as he ſhould be put into Poſſeſſion of the Equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>valents: that conſidering the Preſent Poſture of Affairs, he foreſaw long Delays and infinite Cavils; whereas if <hi>Sedan</hi> were in his Hands, it would be look'd upon as the King's Buſineſs, no leſs then the Enlarging of <hi>France</hi> by the Acquiſition of a Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raignty, and a City of great Strength and Impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance. That if theſe Reaſons would not work up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Queen nor Monſieur, he deſir'd the Abbot to lay before 'em, that the One or the Other might happen to dye before Things could be brought to that perfection, as to be fit to be put in Execution, which would inevitably prove the Ruine of his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily; and that they were engag'd as well in Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour as in Conſcience not to expoſe him to that Extremity. To this he added, That tho' the Queen and the Duke had the leaſt reaſon in the world to diſtruſt his Words, nevertheleſs he offer'd to give his Children in Hoſtage, or to ſubmit to whatever Precautions they deſir'd to take, for the Security of the Young King. But this was like knocking at a deaf Man's door; for the Abbot, who had his Inſtructions, told him with a great many Complements, That he had only Orders to hear him; but that he would make a faithful Report of what he had ſaid; adding with great Proteſtations, That it ſhould be none of his Fault that he had not a favourable Anſwer: but that was a thing which was never intended. So that <hi>Bouillon</hi> finding that the Abbot never came at him more, reſolv'd to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſs himſelf directly to the Queen and the Duke of <hi>Orleance:</hi> but both the One and the Other knew ſo well how to avoid meeting him, that he could
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:39033:13"/> never find an Opportunity to ſpeak to 'em. Which put him into a Rage, and caus'd him to let fall ſome hard words againſt the Queen and the Duke, as being too forgetful of what he had done for 'em. However <hi>Bouillon,</hi> unwilling to return Home with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a poſitive Anſwer, apply'd himſelf again to the Abbot: but then he could never find the Abbot at home, his Servants having Orders ſtill to deny him whenever <hi>Bouillon</hi> came to ask for him. Nay, it happen'd one day, that tho' he knew that the Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bot was at home, by certain Perſons of Quality that waited in his Antichamber to ſpeak with him, yet the Abbot was ſo unmannerly as to ſend out one of his Servants to tell him bluntly in the hearing of thoſe Gentlemen, That the Abbot was gone abroad; which put the Duke of <hi>Bouillon</hi> into ſuch a Rage, that he bid the Servant tell his Maſter, That had it not been for the Reſpect which he bore the Duke of <hi>Orleance,</hi> he would have return'd him ſuch a Treatment for his Sawcineſs, that ſhould have ſtuck to him as long as he liv'd.</p>
            <p>This Tranſport of Paſſion in the Duke made a great noiſe at Court, ſo that the Queen, and the Duke of <hi>Orleance</hi> were glad of this pretence to ridd them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves of a Perſon whoſe preſence continually Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach'd 'em with his paſt Services, and the Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinal propos'd in Council a ſecond ſeizure of his Perſon. But <hi>Bouillon</hi> having notice of it underhand, took Poſt for <hi>Turenne,</hi> there to ſpend the Remain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of his days, having loſt not only the Impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant City of <hi>Sedan,</hi> but the promis'd Equivalent beſides. Nor does the Court of <hi>France</hi> do any thing more for the Family of <hi>Bouillon,</hi> then only lull 'em aſleep with Cardinals Caps and Benefices of
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:39033:13"/> the ſame value. Thus we ſend Trifles to the <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dians,</hi> and bring away their Gold and Silver.</p>
            <p>I would fain have the French Emiſſaries tell me what reaſon the Moſt Chriſtian King had to make himſelf Maſter of the Principality of <hi>Orange,</hi> to beat down the Fortifications of the Caſtle in the year 1667, when the Sovereign was under Age, and afterwards utterly to demoliſh the Caſtle and Walls of the City, and not content with that ſame De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolation, to ſollicite the Corporations to ſubmit themſelves to the King, threatning, if they refus'd, to burn and totally ruine the Inhabitants, as after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the French Forces did, notwithſtanding their Independant Sovereignty. I am perſwaded the beſt reaſon thoſe Emiſſaries can give, is becauſe the Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licy of <hi>France</hi> cannot brook a Foreign Sovereignty within her Dominions: and ſo it was the Intereſt of the Court to make themſelves Maſters of it, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Sovereign was in a Condition to withſtand their Power, by means of his Friends and Confede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rates: and all the while they pretended that they had done the Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> a ſignal Piece of Service, becauſe they had ſpar'd him the Expence of a Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſon. But if ſuch be the Charity of the Moſt Chriſtian King, what may we expect from his Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verity?</p>
            <p>Without Queſtion the ſame Spirit it was that in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpir'd <hi>France</hi> to ſeize upon <hi>Burgundy</hi> and <hi>Franche Conté,</hi> without any pretence of Claim, after the <hi>Pyrenaean</hi> Treaty, and without any other reaſon, but becauſe <hi>Spain</hi> being weak, was not able to defend her ſelf, and becauſe it is really the Court of <hi>France</hi> to aggrandize her ſelf ſo ſoon as ſhe finds an Oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity, without any reſpect to Treaties or Alliances.
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:39033:14"/> And it may be ſaid, that the Miniſtry of <hi>Maza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rine</hi> was a continu'd Chain of Oppreſſions, and that he made it his Study all his Life-time to extinguiſh the Nobility of <hi>France</hi> by all the ways imaginable, whether right or wrong: tho' he were cunning e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough to ſupport 'em during the Troubles which happen'd in the Kingdom during the reigning King's Minority.</p>
            <p>But ſo ſoon as he had manag'd 'em, ſo ſoon as he had humbled their Power by ruining 'em: for he who deprives a Prince of Money, takes from him the Soul of Authority; the Princes of the Blood did nothing but cry out and openly reproach the Court, that ſhe was full of nothing but Craft, Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifice and juggling Tricks to abuſe the People and the Confederates; but they might cry as loud as they pleas'd, the Miniſtry went its own way, and the Cardinal let 'em ſay what they pleas'd, provided he did his own buſineſs. For it may be ſaid of him, that his Tongue bely'd his Heart, and that his Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance quite differ'd from his inward Thoughts. He was often wont to ſay, that the <hi>French</hi> were na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turally Turbulent, given to Novelty, and prone to Sedition, and that the Court was full of Reſtleſs Spirits. Which was the Reaſon that he always en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour'd to cut 'em out Employment without the Kingdom. But in regard he had no reaſon to be ſatisfy'd with the People, he was the Inventor of the greateſt part of the Taxes now raging in <hi>France,</hi> the Father of the Publicans and Toll-gatherers. He ſuck'd the Blood of the Subjects, in imitation of the Grand Signior, for the Support of the Soldiery, preferr'd before the People, at the Expence of the People, and tho' it ſhould be to their utter Ruin; to
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:39033:14"/> the end he might be able to quell 'em, when ever they ſhould be inclin'd to Mutiny and Inſurrection; In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſinuating into the Young King, that the Preſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of his Crown depended upon his Soldiers; as heretofore the <hi>German</hi> Legions vaunted to hold the Empire in their Hands. And in purſuance of that Maxim we have ſeen, that during this Reign, the Court of <hi>France</hi> has practis'd this Leſſon, which has ruin'd her People, that ſhe has impoveriſh'd her Subjects, depriv'd the Nobility of their Privileges, and all this meerly by keeping great Armies on foot, to ſerve her at all times with both Hands to ruin the People, when ever they went about to ſhake off or complain of the Exceſſive Taxes and Impoſts with which they are daily overwhelm'd: to chaſtize the Parliaments when they refus'd to verifie the Edicts and Impoſitions which the Kings ſends to 'em: as alſo that ſhe may have her Legions al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways ready to invade the Dominions of her Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours, when they leaſt dream of any ſuch Acts of Hoſtility; or are otherwiſe employ'd, relying up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Faith of Treaties. As we have ſeen how that after the Peace of <hi>Nimeghen,</hi> when <hi>France</hi> finding her Treaſures quite exhauſted, and her numerous Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies ruin'd by Sickneſs &amp; Hardſhips, was conſtrain'd to make freſh Proviſion, fearing a Change of Fortune, as ſhe had already felt at the Battel of St. <hi>Dennis.</hi> For this reaſon ſhe ſought Peace to break the Union, and obtain'd it in deſpite of thoſe who well fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaw that <hi>France</hi> would no longer keep it after ſhe had once recover'd Breath, or that ſhe found a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitious Opportunity to break it. For ſince the King of <hi>France</hi> falſify'd his Oath to obſerve the <hi>Pyrenaean</hi> Peace, ſo ſolemnly ſworn upon the Altar, Since<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:39033:15"/> is fled from the Court of <hi>France,</hi> and return'd to Heaven, from whence it deſcended, and Corruption has taken the Place of Juſtice and Integrity. In regard the Miniſtry of <hi>France</hi> was only meditated to aggrandize the King. And therefore the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaſed Sieur <hi>de Colbert,</hi> Chief Miniſter, never ſcrupled to aſſert, That the King might break and make Laws at his own pleaſure; Privileges being Chimera's odious and offenſive to it, and that Law was only the Inclination, Reputation and Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of the Prince.</p>
            <p>When the King of <hi>France</hi> has a mind to make himſelf Maſter of a Country, or only of a ſingle Town, he never conſiders the Outward Situation, but the Inward Condition of it; by whom it is go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vern'd, who defends it; and the Louidores are moſt commonly the Cannons with which he attacks it. And therefore <hi>Pompone,</hi> formerly Embaſſadour at the Court of <hi>Sweden,</hi> had in ſome meaſure good Reaſon to ſay, that <hi>France</hi> with her Money would always do what ſhe pleas'd; and that it was by means of that Metal, that ſhe was at that time become Miſtreſs of his <hi>Swediſh</hi> Majeſty's Cabinet, and that ſhe became Miſtreſs of ſo many Places after the Peace of <hi>Nimeghen,</hi> under pretence of Appendences and Dependences, of which a great Volume might be made. This is a Truth not to be deny'd, ſince we have ſeen it with our Eyes, and that we ſtill be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold the Inhabitants of thoſe Places groaning un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the ſevere Servitude of the Deſpotick Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of <hi>France.</hi> But in regard that Uſurpation cannot always long ſubſiſt, and for that ſo many Princes are at laſt awaken'd from their Oppreſſion, the Court of <hi>France</hi> finding her ſelf very much embar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raſs'd
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:39033:15"/> to preſerve what ſhe has uſurp'd ſince the Peace of <hi>Nimeghen,</hi> all her Policy could find out no better Expedient then to propoſe a Truce while the Emperour and the Empire were engag'd in a War againſt the <hi>Turk.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Court of <hi>France</hi> had two Proſpects in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiring this Truce. The firſt, That in detaining all the Places of which ſhe had made her ſelf Miſtreſs, ſhe at the ſame time lull'd aſleep the Court of <hi>Vienna</hi> on the <hi>Rhine</hi> ſide, that ſhe might oblige the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour to continue the War with the Grand Signior. Secondly, Not to obſerve the Truce any longer then till one or other of the Two Empires were reduc'd to a Low Condition. Had it been the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour's misfortune to have loſt <hi>Vienna,</hi> then the Bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſs was concerted and decreed, That the King of <hi>France</hi> was to have invaded the Empire with a powerful Army, and to have been proclaim'd Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour with a high hand. On the Other ſide, if the <hi>Turks</hi> were beaten, he was to declare War againſt the Emperour, to prevent him from growing too great by his Conqueſts. But the latter falling out for the good of <hi>Chriſtendom,</hi> preſently <hi>France</hi> without any regard had to Truces or Alliances, openly attacqu'd <hi>Philipsburgh,</hi> carry'd it, and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards march'd with his Army into the <hi>Palatinate</hi> which he over-ran with Fire and Sword, and by Violence, and Conflagrations, got ſure footing all along the Banks of the <hi>Rhine<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> where we to this day behold the ſad and deplorable Remainders of the Rage and Fury of the <hi>French</hi> Armies. However in regard that Violence never wants a Pretence, and that the moſt Impious Actions veil themſelves in like manner with ſome Outward Appearances;
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:39033:16"/> the King of <hi>France</hi> to juſtifie himſelf before all the World, out of a kind of Generoſity pretends to declare the Reaſons why he was conſtrain'd to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume Hoſtile Arms, to the end he might perſwade all <hi>Chriſtendom</hi> of his ſincere Intentions to eſtabliſh the publick Repoſe, while his Soldiers in all Places ruin'd and burnt whole Provinces, and carry'd away the Goods and Cattel of the Poor Inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants.</p>
            <p>To this purpoſe the Moſt Chriſtian King fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows his begun Hoſtilities with a <hi>Manifeſto,</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the Principal Reaſons that <hi>France</hi> alledges to co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver her Breach of Faith, are firſt, That ſhe was well inform'd that ſo ſoon as the Emperour ſhould have made a Peace with the <hi>Turk,</hi> he had reſolv'd to bend all his whole Force upon the <hi>Rhine</hi> againſt <hi>France.</hi> To which I ſhall anſwer hereafter in Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular: but in general thus much is to be ſaid, that the Moſt Chriſtian King, after he had broken the Truce, deſir'd to make a Peace upon two Conditions. Firſt, That the Truce for Twenty Years might be chang'd into a Perpetual Peace: and Secondly, That the Cardinal <hi>de Furſtenbergh</hi> might be put into the Poſſeſſion of the Electorate of <hi>Cologne;</hi> and that afterwards the King would en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour to bring the Cardinal and the Chapter to ſuch Accommodations as ſhould be propos'd for the Satisfaction of Prince <hi>Clement</hi> of <hi>Bavaria;</hi> that is to ſay, to cauſe him to be declar'd Coadjutour to the ſaid Electorate.</p>
            <p>As to the firſt point the Politicks of the Court of <hi>France</hi> were very fine Spun and extreamly Crafty; ſeeing that while the Emperour and the Empire were engag'd againſt the <hi>Turks,</hi> it was the proper
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:39033:16"/> time for her to appropriate to her ſelf all the Places, Lands and Signiories which by the Truce were not left to the enjoyment of <hi>France</hi> but for Twenty years, of which three were expir'd, and which the King was fully perſwaded in his Conſcience that he could not juſtly keep, but muſt be forc'd to reſtore at the Expiration of the Truce.</p>
            <p>As for the Poſſeſſion of <hi>Cologne</hi> by the Cardinal of <hi>Furſtenbergh,</hi> (the detaining of which from the ſaid Cardinal was another ſpecious Pretence for his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuming Arms) all <hi>Europe</hi> is ſufficiently acquainted with the Engaging Reaſon which the Moſt Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian King had to make himſelf Maſter of that Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biſhoprick: ſeeing the Cardinal and the King were all one, and ſo by means of that Poſſeſſion, the King of <hi>France</hi> had one Foot in the Empire, and upon the Territories adjoyning, belonging either to the States of the United Provinces, or the <hi>Palatine</hi> and <hi>Brandenburgh</hi> Electors. But becauſe it will be a difficult matter for us to treat otherwiſe then con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſedly of the Policy of <hi>France</hi> in general, we ſhall deſcend to Particulars, thereby to render it more Intelligible, beginning with the Holy See.</p>
            <p>The Kings of <hi>France</hi> have always held themſelves highly honour'd with the Title of Eldeſt Sons of the Church, and would have made War upon any one that ſhould have ventur'd to diſpute that Title with 'em. In like manner, they have all along given Marks of their Filial Obedience, and a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vout ſubmiſſion to what ever came from the Holy See. And to have ſeen <hi>Lewis</hi> XIV. perſecute the <hi>Huguenots</hi> in <hi>France,</hi> there is no body but would have ſworn that he had been the moſt Zealous Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholick in the world. Nevertheleſs we have ſeen
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:39033:17"/> the contrary, and that what he has done in refe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence to the <hi>Proteſtants,</hi> was only to ward off the Accuſations that might have been charg'd upon him for openly oppoſing the Holy See, while he affronted, as all the world knows he openly did, Pope <hi>Innocent</hi> XI. only becauſe the Holy Father would not give way to his Uſurpation of the Regale in <hi>France;</hi> which produc'd the Aſſembly of ſome Prelates of the <hi>French</hi> Clergy in the Year 1682. wherein the Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biſhop of <hi>Paris</hi> who preſided there, being flatter'd in caſe of a Rupture, with the hopes of being Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triarch of the Kingdom, or in caſe of an Accommo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation, with the expectation of a Cardinals Cap, got all the Prelates who were preſent at the Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly, to degrade the Papal Authority, and of a Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſal Pontiff, to make him a Simple Biſhop, ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected to Councils. And the King conſtrain'd all the Preachers in the Kingdom, and Rectors of U<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niverſities to declaim and teach a Doctrine in Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition to the Authority of the Pontiff Nay, the Buſineſs went ſo high, that the Court of <hi>France</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertook to govern <hi>Rome</hi> it ſelf, in oppoſing the Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion of the Franchiſes of Embaſſadours Quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters in <hi>Rome;</hi> which indeed were no more then a Sanctuary for Robbers and Bankrupts. More<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>over, the King of <hi>France,</hi> that he might remain peaceable Poſſeſſour of the Regale, went about to ſet a foot an Old Pretenſion of the Duke of <hi>Parma</hi> to the States of <hi>Caſtro,</hi> and <hi>Ronciglione,</hi> ſuppoſing 'em Guarranties only of the Treaty of <hi>Piſa,</hi> which was a Pretence to ſeize upon the City and Country of <hi>Avignon,</hi> which the Court of <hi>France</hi> had for a long time look'd upon as an Eſtate that lay convenient for her, and only ſought an Opportunity to detain
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:39033:17"/> it, without being oblig'd to make Reſtitution; and which had taken effect, had not <hi>Innocent</hi> the XI. been a quiet and peaceable Pontiff, ſuffering with a Chriſtian Patience while he liv'd, all the Affronts of the Court of <hi>France,</hi> referring the Revenge of 'em, as he was often wont to ſay, to his <hi>Crucify'd Saviour;</hi> and to him it was, that the Holy Father appeal'd, when <hi>France</hi> ſent him a Copy of the Extract of the Regiſters of the Parliament of <hi>Paris,</hi> in the enſuing Words.</p>
            <q rend="margQuotes">
               <p>This day the King's Advocate-General coming into the <hi>Chamber of Vacations,</hi> and declaring, That the Matters of Fact explain'd by the Letter which the King wrote to Cardinal <hi>d'Eſtrees</hi> the 6th. of this Month, having oblig'd his Majeſty to let our Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Father the Pope know, That for the future he could not but look upon him as a Prince engag'd with his Enemies, conſequently that he could not acknowledge him for a Judge of every thing that concern'd his Majeſty's Intereſts, the King's Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocate General thought it his Duty, at the ſame time to take the Precautions ſettl'd by the Law, practis'd upon ſeveral Occaſions, and grounded upon the Opinions of the <hi>Italian</hi> Canoniſts them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, to hinder his Holineſs from pronouncing Effectual and Regular Judgments upon theſe Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters. To which purpoſe, he has put in to a Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſal Council an Appeal Extrajudicial, as to all Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings of his Holineſs at preſent, or for the Future; and as to all Sentences which he may have given, or hereafter pronounce, to the Prejudice of the King, or the Prerogatives of his Crown, or of his Majeſty's Subjects. Of all which, the Reſpect which he owes the Crown, has oblig'd him to
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:39033:18"/> come and give the Court an Account, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent to their view the Act which he has made, wherein he cannot but acknowledge the Piety; Wiſdom and Moderation of the King in this par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular, which ſeem to have extinguiſh'd in the Perſon of the King, thoſe Paſſions that moſt ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hemently agitate other Men. He hopes that the Court will approve his Conduct, and aſſures him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf that they will both zealouſly and faithfully uſe all the Authority with which it has pleas'd the King to inveſt 'em, to maintain the Reſpect which is due to his Majeſty, and to preſerve the Prerogatives of his Crown, the Tranquillity of his Subjects, and the Liberties which are not only particular to the <hi>Gallican</hi> Church, but which ſhe has preſerv'd with more Learning and Vigour then any other. Which things being conſider'd, the Chamber Ordains,</p>
               <p>That the ſaid Act of Appeal be Regiſter'd in the Regiſters Office, that recourſe may be had to it, as occaſion ſerves, and that Thanks be return'd to the King for ordering his Advocate-General to proceed according to the Uſual Practiſe upon the ſame Occaſions, and that the Firſt Preſident do aſſure the King in the Name of the whole Society of their Devotion to his ſacred Perſon and his Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice; and that they will at all times make uſe of that Authority which the King has conferr'd up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on 'em, to ſupport the Prerogatives of the Crown, the Liberties of the Kingdom, and the Repoſe of his Subjects.</p>
               <p>It was alſo further added by M. <hi>Harlay,</hi> the King's Counſellor in his Council of State, and his Advocate-General, That the Reputation and Piety of our Holy Father <hi>Innocent</hi> XI. cauſing his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:39033:18"/> to rejoice at his Exaltation to the Pontificate, his Majeſty endeavour'd to cloſe with his Holineſs, in order to a unanimous Care of what ever might be for the Glory and Service of God.</p>
               <p>That his deſires and the Progreſſes he made in or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to ſuch a Pious Deſign, not having had that Succeſs which he expected, the King however ſtill continu'd on his part to employ the Power which God has put into his hands for the preſervation of the Purity of the Faith in his Kingdom, and to bring back to the Boſom of the Church a Great Number of Children that are gone aſtray, as alſo to afford the Church all the Protection, which ſhe could ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect from the Authority of a Great King: his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty alſo has edified by his Example, and inſtructed all his Subjects by his particular Piety.</p>
               <p>Nevertheleſs, our Holy Father the Pope, to whom ſo many wonderful Vertues and Actions ought to have render'd the Perſon of the King ſo dear, has with great heat embrac'd the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaint of the two Biſhops about the Right of the Regale; and his Holineſs at the ſame time rejected the Teſtimonies of all the reſt of the Prelates of the Kingdom, touching the Favours they have receiv'd from the King in that particular to the Prejudice of his Prerogatives.</p>
               <p>He went about to take from the King's Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſadours at <hi>Rome</hi> the Franchiſes which they en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy'd, even under his Pontificate, in a City where it became the Gratitude of the Popes to have pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerv'd to our Kings, more ſingular Marks of that Sovereignty, of which they formerly deſpoil'd themſelves, to enrich the Holy See.</p>
               <p>Our Holy Father has alſo look'd upon as a dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous and ſuſpected Doctrine, the Declaration
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:39033:19"/> which the Aſſembly of the Clergy made in the Year 1682. of their Opinions concerning Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſtical Power; at ſuch a Conjuncture too, when ſome of his Predeceſſours would rather have been baniſh'd to the Extremities of the Earth, then have ſuffer'd ſo many New Converts.</p>
               <p>He refus'd his Bulls to ſeveral Eccleſiaſticks no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minated by the King to ſupply the vacant Churches in his Kingdom.</p>
               <p>The partial Behaviour of our Holy Father in reference to the Archbiſhoprick of <hi>Cologne;</hi> his Reſolute Refuſal to acknowledge or give Audi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to the King's Ambaſſadour at that Conjun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture; but thundering out Anathema's againſt him, and Interdicting him from St. <hi>Lewis</hi>'s Church in <hi>Rome,</hi> will perpetuate an Example almoſt Incre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dible to Poſterity of the King's Zeal for Religion, and his deſire to preſerve the Peace of <hi>Chriſtendom,</hi> and of the Pope's proceedings ſo contrary to the Obligations of the Place which he ſupplies.</p>
               <p>Wherefore ſeeing His Holineſs ſtops his Ears to all the King's moſt juſt Complaints, we are conſtrain'd at length to defend our ſelves, and to maintain the Dignity of the Crown, and the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe of the King's Subjects by the Rules of Juſtice, at a time that his Majeſty does the ſame, with ſo much glory, by the Puiſſance of his Armes.</p>
               <p>Thereupon the King's ſaid Advocate-General, having firſt obtain'd the King's permiſſion, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clares, That he is Appellant in the King's behalf, and in behalf of all his Subjects to a Univerſal Council, which His Holineſs ſhall be pleas'd to call in due and Canonical Form, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Proteſting in the mean time in the Name and by the Expreſs Command
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:39033:19"/> of the King, that 'tis his Intention to remain inviolably devoted to the Holy See as the true Center of the Church's Unity, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And ſo ſoon as our Holy Father, being better inform'd, ſhall ſhew the Equity, the Sentiments and Partiality of a Judge and common Father, his Majeſty will pay to his Perſon the ſame Filial Reſpect, as he did before; and from which nothing but the ill Conduct of his Holineſs cauſes him to abſtain.</p>
            </q>
            <p>After the Court of <hi>France</hi> had put theſe unheard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of Affronts upon the Holy See, and thus debas'd the Authority of the Sovereign Pontiff, inſtead of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king uſe of thoſe means which the Catholick Church and Councils have put into his Hands to bring back Princes and People to their Chriſtian Duty, the Pope out of a peculiar Fund of Charity and Piety, contented himſelf with making appear to all the World, the Juſtice of his Proceedings and the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſtice of the <hi>French</hi> Court, declaring all along, that he was perſwaded that the Truth of Affairs had never been truly repreſented to the King of <hi>France;</hi> only that the Artifices and Paſſions of thoſe who are no Lovers of Peace had infus'd into him an Idea altogether different. Otherwiſe that it was never to be believ'd that the King would have harbour'd in his Mind thoſe Injurious Sentiments contain'd in Cardinal <hi>d'Eſtree</hi>'s Letter: his Holineſs having ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver fail'd to ſhew himſelf a true Father to all Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licks, but more particularly to <hi>France;</hi> who upon ſeveral Occaſions had receiv'd various Teſtimonies of his Indulgence and Eſteem; but inſtead of being repay'd with Grateful Acknowledgment, his Holineſs had been expos'd to moſt heinous Injuries
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:39033:20"/> and Affronts not only offer'd to his Perſon but the Holy See, by extending the Regale to above half the the Churches in <hi>France</hi> that are no way ſubject to it; but by the Second General Council of <hi>Lion,</hi> by preſcription of almoſt 400 Years. by the Teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies and Evidences of Edicts of ſeveral Kings, De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crees of Parliament, and Regiſters of the Chamber of Accounts, as alſo by the Opinion of the moſt ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lebrated French Lawyers, ought to be exempted from it.</p>
            <p>The Pope loudly complain'd of the Violence done to the Convents of the <hi>Carognes</hi> and <hi>Urbaniſtes;</hi> and that, only for applying themſelves to the Holy See, in Oppoſition to an Invaſion of their Privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leges, and the Canonical Rules of their Orders, which imports, That Abbots and Superiours ought to be Elective, and continue for three Years toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. In contempt of which, the King had intro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duc'd Abbots of his own Nomination. Beſides the Rending away of Five Abbies, without the conſent of the Apoſtolick See, to erect a Commandery, and applying to Other uſes the Revenues poſſeſs'd by ſeveral Monks and Nuns, according to the Will of the Donours.</p>
            <p>But that which was more enormous, was the King's Prohibiting the Biſhops to have any Recourſe to the Pope, according to their Duty and the Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtom of all Times, to ask his Counſel in matter of Religion; as alſo in reference to what concern'd Prince <hi>Clement</hi> of <hi>Bavaria:</hi> tho' in granting him the Eligibility for three Churches that were Legally poſſeſs'd by the deceas'd Electour of <hi>Cologne,</hi> all <hi>Chriſtendom</hi> ſaw that the Pope had no other Aim then the Publick Good. For beſides the high Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lue
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:39033:20"/> which it behov'd him to have for that Illuſtrious Houſe, the Merits of the Electour his Brother, who had ſo gloriouſly defended <hi>Chriſtendom</hi> againſt the Invaſion of the <hi>Turks,</hi> his Holineſs had done nothing in that particular, but only imitated the Liberality of his Predeceſſours, who conferr'd the like and greater Favours alſo upon Perſons much Inferiour in Birth, Age and Merit, then Prince <hi>Clement,</hi> and that too at the Requeſt of the Kings of <hi>France.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And for the Bull granted to Prince <hi>Clement,</hi> the Pope could not be accus'd of any Injuſtice for ſo doing, ſince that Affair was exactly and ſeriouſly examin'd in a Conſiſtorial Congregation at <hi>Rome.</hi> Beſides that the King of <hi>France</hi> had neither any Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon nor Right to intermeddle in that Affair, ſince it was a Buſineſs that only related to a <hi>German</hi> Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biſhoprick, and an Electour of the Empire, which no way concern'd <hi>France</hi> either directly or indirect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, but the Pope only in reſpect of Apoſtolick Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmation, and the Emperour, as to the Inveſtiture of the Pincipality in admitting him into the Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctoral College, to which belongs the Right of Electing a new Emperour, and which has a very great Sway in managing the Affairs of the whole Empire. So that the Pretence for War which <hi>France</hi> lays hold on from the Proceedings at <hi>Cologne</hi> is to be imputed to the King's Paſſion, and his own Intereſt.</p>
            <p>After what paſt in the Aſſembly of ſome Part of the Clergy at <hi>Paris,</hi> where among other things, the King caus'd the Regale to be adjudg'd his Right, notwithſtanding the Appeal of the Biſhops of <hi>Alets</hi> and <hi>Pamiſe,</hi> to the Pope; and the Propoſitions ſo injurious to the Apoſtolick See, ſupported by Royal
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:39033:21"/> Edicts, enjoyning every Body to receive and pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lickly profeſs and teach 'em in ſuch a manner as was never yet practis'd, His Holineſs had great Reaſon to refuſe his Bulls to the Eccleſiaſticks no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minated by the King to ſupply the vacant Biſhop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ricks, becauſe they were preſent at the ſaid Aſſembly of 1682. and there openly declar'd themſelves E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies of the Apoſtolick See; and for that the Canon Law, and the Agreement made with <hi>France,</hi> that the Pope ſhould be judge of the Capacity of the Perſons nominated, prove moreover, That the ſaid Eccleſiaſticks nomianted by the King, were not Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons proper to be entruſted with the Inſtruction of the People, but abſolutely addicted to their pleaſures, and their worldly Intereſts, ſeeing that they never ſcrupl'd to revolt againſt their Spiritual Chief, and to betray the Liberty and Privileges of the Church, to the end they might gain the King's Favour, and augment their Temporal Means. Upon this, the Court of <hi>France</hi> being deſirous to vex the Pope, made choice of the Marquis of <hi>Lovardin</hi> for his Embaſſadour to <hi>Rome,</hi> becauſe he was a Known Enemy of the Apoſtolick See, and was both able and willing to affront and moleſt his Holineſs. No wonder then if he never had Audience of the Pope, ſeeing that according to the General Rule, no Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter ſhould be ſent to a Soveraign Prince, but ſuch a one as is acceptable to the Prince with whom he is to negotiate: beſides that it is not ſufficient for a perſon to be ſent by a Prince, to entitle him to the Prerogatives of an Embaſſadour, but according to the Laws of Nations, he muſt be acknowledg'd for ſuch a one by the Soveraign to whom that Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter is ſent. Therefore the Court of <hi>France</hi> had
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:39033:21"/> no reaſon to complain that the Pope refus'd to give Audience to the Marquis. Nor indeed would any Soveraign have ſuffer'd the Marquis, as he did, to enter <hi>Rome</hi> with Armed Force, as it were to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prive him of one Part of his Sovereignty, and on purpoſe to affront him after ſuch a manner, unheard of even among <hi>Barbarians</hi> themſelves.</p>
            <p>'Tis obſervable that when <hi>France</hi> has any occaſion to court the Favour of the Holy See, ſhe ſends Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lates, Cardinals and Biſhops for her Embaſſadours; in regard it is a Thing both decent and becoming Eccleſiaſticks to be ſubmiſſive to the Pope; beſides that they are allow'd Admittance, when Seculars are excluded. But when <hi>France</hi> has a mind to af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>front the See, ſhe ſends a Lawyer or a Sword-man, who neither depends upon the Pope, nor expects any Kindneſs from him, and who dares ruffle him ſtoutly, when it is to promote the Intereſts of <hi>France.</hi> But <hi>France</hi> ſeeing the Pontiff inflexible, and that he was not to be gain'd either by his Nephew nor by the Cardinals that were moſt Intimate with him, reſolv'd either to rid him out of the world or to wait for his Death. But Old Age ſparing <hi>France</hi> the Labour of her firſt deſign, he was no ſooner dead, but <hi>France</hi> began her old Cuſtom of making Parties, and ſcattering her Louidores up and down <hi>Rome,</hi> to purchaſe a Pope of her own Faction; and the Lot fell upon a <hi>Venetian, Ottoboni,</hi> who took upon him the Name of <hi>Alexander</hi> VIII. <hi>France</hi> thought him her Friend, and attributed the whole Glory of his Election to her ſelf. But ſhe found him to be a <hi>Venetian,</hi> that is to ſay, one that conceal'd his real Sentiments as long as he liv'd, and never declar'd himſelf till he came to lie upon his Death-Bed; but
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:39033:22"/> then he did it in ſuch a Manner as was no way for the Advantage of <hi>France.</hi> Now in regard he was very Old, and deſirous to make the beſt of thoſe few Years he had to live, to raiſe the Fortune of his Family, the <hi>French</hi> Miniſters fail'd not to be li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beral of their inchanting Golden Philters, to allure his Kindred into the Intereſts of the <hi>French</hi> Court. But how willing ſoever, or how Importunate to Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lige their Uncle to do ſomething in favour of the King, could never procure from him any thing more, but only that while he held the Pon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tificate he did <hi>France</hi> neither good nor harm. How<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever, the <hi>Italians</hi> ſay this of him, That he did like the Swan, that is, he Sung a little before his Death. Nevertheleſs <hi>France</hi> ſuffer'd patiently that petty Mortification, and the loſs of all her Preſents to the Family of the <hi>Ottoboni,</hi> in hopes to have at length a Pontiff more favourable to her Purpoſes. At laſt after much canvaſſing, moſt Voices were for a Neopolitan, of the Family of <hi>Pignatelli,</hi> whom the Cardinals of the <hi>French</hi> Faction would not ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude, upon his promiſe to the <hi>French</hi> Cardinals that the <hi>French</hi> Court ſhould have no reaſon to be diſſatisfy'd with his Pontificate. But being elected he forgot the Promiſes he had made, the rather be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the Imperial and Spaniſh Embaſſadours diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded him, as much as lay in their Power, from the obſervance of 'em. The Court of <hi>France</hi> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore finding that they had to do with one that was not leſs weak in Mind then infirm in Body, preſs'd it upon him that he would occaſion the damnation of a great number of People that were without Paſtours, if he perſiſted in the Refuſal of his Bulls to the Biſhops of <hi>France,</hi> who were preſent at the Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembly
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:39033:22"/> of the Clergy in the Year 1682. And at the ſame time the <hi>French</hi> Cardinals, according to their Inſtructions, gave the Pontiff to underſtand, that a War was very near breaking out in <hi>Italy,</hi> and that he would be anſwerable for the Blood that ſhould be ſpilt; ſeeing the Moſt Chriſtian King's Patience was at an end, and that moſt certainly he would withdraw himſelf from his Obedience to the See of <hi>Rome,</hi> and ſet up a Patriarch in his own Kingdom, and thereby retain ſeveral Millions that went every year to <hi>Rome.</hi> Thereupon, thoſe Fears that uſually ſeize People ſuperannuated, and the Delicacy of Conſcience without any neceſſity of a Pontiff, made him determine to ſatisfie the Court of <hi>France,</hi> upon frivolous Promiſes that the Biſhops ſhould ſubmit, tho' to the prejudice of the Holy See; ſince the King retracted nothing of what he had done publickly againſt the Authority of the Pontiffs and the Religion of the See, and for that the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſters of the Parliament of <hi>Paris</hi> (containing the Inju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Appeal of the King's Advocate-General) ſtill remain upon Record, and for that <hi>France</hi> will one day revive it again, when ſhe finds a favourable Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity to humble the Court of <hi>Rome.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Neither the Pope nor the Holy See are to judge of the Catholicity of <hi>Lewis</hi> XIV. or his Court by the Paſſion which he has ſhown in perſecuting the <hi>Huguenots</hi> within his Kingdom. So far from that, ſeeing that while the French Monarch perſecuted the <hi>Huguenots</hi> in his own Realm, and deſtroy'd their Churches and their Exerciſes, he ſuccour'd Count <hi>Teckeli,</hi> the Head of the ſame Sect, that were re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volted from their Soveraign in <hi>Hungary:</hi> and the Court of <hi>France</hi> was not only more cloſely Ally'd
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:39033:23"/> for his ſake with the <hi>Ottoman</hi> Port, to which he al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo gave conſiderable Aſſiſtance, but made Vows for the Proſperity of the <hi>Mahometans,</hi> and repair'd their Moſques even as far as <hi>Vienna</hi> it ſelf. More<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>over, I have frequently heard the Director of my Conſcience ſay, and have heard ſeveral of the queint Doctors of the <hi>Sorbonne</hi> preach, that the Fruits of the Chriſtian Religion were Charity, and that he who was void of it could not be a True Catholick; that Charity was a Vertue which produc'd a Patient Spirit, that it was benign, that it was not covetous of other mens Goods, nor ſought its own advanta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges; that it neither commits Injuſtice nor poſſeſſes any thing unjuſtly got: that it endures every thing, believes every thing, bears with every thing; ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver carries it ſelf inſolently or diſhoneſtly. This is the Character of a True Chriſtian, according to the Learned. Now if the Pope finds but one of theſe Vertues in the King of <hi>France,</hi> I mean that Since<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity which Pope <hi>Gregory</hi> requir'd from a true Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholick, which conſiſts in fulfilling by our Actions what we have promis'd in Word: in that caſe I agree, that the Pope may not only embrace him as his Eldeſt Son, but canonize him after his Death, and I will be the firſt that will pay my Homage to the Great St. <hi>Lewis.</hi> If it be enquir'd, From whence this way of proceeding ariſes, ſo different and irregular in reference to the Holy See, more eſpecially in a King who adorns himſelf with the Title of Moſt Chriſtian; I anſwer, that 'tis from hence, becauſe that whatever he took in hand was for the Service of that Great and Ambitious Deſign which aim'd at nothing leſs then to be the Maſter of all <hi>Europe.</hi> To which purpoſe he had it in view,
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:39033:23"/> by the Perſecution of the Religionaries of his King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom to acquire to himſelf the Suffrages, the Eſteem, the Aſſiſtance of all the <hi>Roman Catholicks,</hi> in the midſt of thoſe great Deſigns which he had to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vade the Empire by means of that Succour which he gave the <hi>Turk.</hi> There is nothing makes the King of <hi>France</hi> ſo ſick at heart, as the Proſperity of the Emperour. He would willingly make War againſt Heaven, becauſe God did not give him all the Earth to himſelf, or at leaſt becauſe he thinks his Neighbour has the better ſhare, and poſſeſſes the more lovely part. For this Reaſon you ſee that <hi>France</hi> is always upon the Enquiry; Her Emiſſaries continually inform themſelves what Territories, what Splendour others enjoy, that their Monarch may have an Opportunity to fall upon This or t'Other, or Both together. Envious Perſons are as it were the Animated Skeletons of Demons, that are nouriſh'd only by their own Torments. <hi>Agrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pina,</hi> the Mother of <hi>Nero,</hi> was wont to ſay, <hi>That there was nothing in the World which a Prince ought not to Sacrifice for a Crown.</hi> And therefore it was, that <hi>Katherine de Medicis,</hi> Queen of <hi>France,</hi> finding her ſelf ready to ſink under the Burden of the Civil Wars, after the death of her Son <hi>Francis</hi> II. and not knowing any longer, after ſhe had tyr'd 'em all out, to what Saint to recommend her ſelf, went to the Devil with her three Younger Children, <hi>Charles</hi> IX. the Duke of <hi>Anjou</hi> and the Duke of <hi>Alanſon.</hi> And the Medal is ſtill to be ſeen with this Device beneath her Figure, engrav'd in Copper, and the Figures of her three Children which ſhe offer'd to the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon, <hi>Soit, pourvu que je regne. Let it be, ſo I may reign.</hi> If theſe Miſerable Women have carry'd
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:39033:24"/> their Ambition ſo high for a ſingle Crown, what may it not be Lawful for <hi>Lewis</hi> XIV. to do, ſo he may gain the Univerſal Monarchy? For ſtill what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever he does, the <hi>French</hi> have a Name for it; they call it <hi>Grandeur of Soul.</hi> They offer Incenſe at this very day to the Divinity of <hi>Lewis</hi> the Great, and below his Statue, the Head of which is environ'd with a Glory, there are written theſe Blaſphemous words, <hi>Numini Ludovici Magni.</hi> This is the Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, and this is the Idol of the Court of <hi>France,</hi> and of their Emiſſaries, that compaſs the Earth to make Proſelytes to embrace and adore the Intereſts of <hi>France.</hi> If among ſuch proceedings as theſe, if in ſuch a Dreary Chaos, the Holy See can find out <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholicity,</hi> I will acknowledge him to be like God himſelf, who alone can bring Light out of Dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs.</p>
            <p>But <hi>Lewis</hi> the XIV. was not content with the Crown of <hi>France,</hi> nor to make himſelf Emperour, but to be the Univerſal Monarch of the World, and then not having any more to conquer here below, like the Gyants of Old he would have built a Tow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er to ſcale Heaven, and Dragoon the Inhabitants of the Eternal Manſions. However the Soveraign KING of Kings, who derides the Folly of Men, has in a good Meaſure confounded the Counſels of <hi>France,</hi> and diſſipated all her Great Deſigns; parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cularly ſince the raiſing the Siege of <hi>Vienna,</hi> upon the 12th. of <hi>September</hi> 1683. a fatal day for <hi>France,</hi> but glorious for the Emperour and Empire, and Happy for all <hi>Chriſtendom.</hi> This unexpected Blow, contrary to the Hopes and Expectations of <hi>Lewis</hi> the XIV. and his Miniſters, conſtrain'd him to ſeek a Truce, which was granted him for Twenty years;
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:39033:24"/> and by which the Policy of <hi>France</hi> had a fair Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of Keeping thoſe Towns of which ſhe was Miſtreſs; and on the other ſide had gain'd time to ſee the Iſſue of the War between the two Empires, with a Deſign however, as already has been ſaid, no longer to obſerve the Truce, till the King beheld the Fate of the Two contending Parties. If the Emperour fell, then the King was to march in Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon into <hi>Germany,</hi> and cauſe himſelf to be proclaim'd Emperour and Protectour of the <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> at the Head of his Army. If the Grand Signior had the worſt of it, then the King was to ſend his Forces to his Aid, by ravaging all <hi>Germany,</hi> and dividing the Forces of the Empire, as he did under imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary Pretences; which was more then openly to Succour the <hi>Turks,</hi> who in Truth had broken with the <hi>Chriſtians</hi> barely upon the Sollicitations of Count <hi>Teckeli</hi> and the King of <hi>France,</hi> promiſing great Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtances, if they happen'd to prove the weakeſt, and in that alone the <hi>French</hi> Monarch may be ſaid to have kept his Word. 'Tis alſo no leſs true that his own Intereſt was at the Bottom, he not enduring to behold the Proſperity of the Imperial Arms; and fearing leaſt the Emperour, proving Victorious, ſhould one day re-demand the Towns and Territories which he had uſurp'd from him.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>France</hi> then ſeeing the Emperour's Succeſs, the <hi>Chriſtians</hi> winning Battel after Battel, the <hi>Turks</hi> dri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven beyond <hi>Belgrade,</hi> his Deſign upon <hi>Cologne</hi> fru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrated, the Baron of <hi>Plettenberg</hi> choſen Biſhop of <hi>Munſter,</hi> the Baron of <hi>Elderen</hi> elected Prince and Biſhop of <hi>Liege,</hi> and by this means all the vaſt De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigns of <hi>Lewis</hi> XIV. quite ranvers'd, ſhe was no longer to be reſtrain'd within the Bounds of a Truce,
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:39033:25"/> ſo that her Fury fell firſt upon <hi>Phillipsburgh,</hi> which the Emperour not being in a Condition to defend, the King carry'd the Town, the 29th. of <hi>October</hi> 1688. and thus neither <hi>Decorum,</hi> nor the Intereſt of the <hi>Chriſtians;</hi> neither promis'd Faith, nor all the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholick Religion it ſelf, could hinder the perfidious Victor from declaring openly for the Infidels and Enemies of Chriſt and the Chriſtian Name. How<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever if on the one ſide <hi>France</hi> in ſome meaſure wreck'd her Revenge by the War which ſhe un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſtly declar'd againſt the Emperour, it may be cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly ſaid, that the Acquiſition of <hi>Philipsburgh</hi> coſt King <hi>James</hi> his Crown, as being at the ſame time abandon'd by <hi>Lewis</hi> the XIV. to his Evil Fortune. The Council of <hi>France</hi> ſoon after, but too late, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledg'd their Fault, and could find no other way to excuſe the Blunder, but by entring into a War with <hi>England, Spain,</hi> and the <hi>United Provinces,</hi> at the ſame time that they declar'd War againſt the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour: and this ſame miſtaken piece of Policy occaſion'd that ſtrict and ſincere Confederacy, which we ſee a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> this day, between the greateſt part of the Chriſtian Princes to preſerve themſelves from the Invaſions of <hi>France;</hi> and <hi>Lewis</hi> the XIV. to wreck his Revenge upon 'em for the ſad Fate of K. <hi>James,</hi> his moſt dear Allye, whoſe Misfortunes were only the Conſequences of his having follow'd the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels of <hi>France</hi> and her pernicious Politicks, was ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lig'd to raiſe Great Armies and equip a Numerous Fleet, to reſtore K. <hi>James</hi> to his Throne; tho' hitherto he has not been able to accompliſh any thing in his Favour, but rather has liv'd to ſee the Diſappointment of all the Hopes that flatter'd his firſt Attempts. Whereas if the Ambitious Monarch
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:39033:25"/> had turn'd his whole Force againſt the Empire on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and bent all his ſtrength on that ſide, he might have gone a great way into the Empire, and have given <hi>Mahomet,</hi> his Dear Friend and Allye, a fair Opportunity to recover his Loſſes. But while he labour'd the Re-mounting of two unhors'd Princes, he ruin'd both the One and the Other. And here it is that we ought to adore the Divine Providence that confounded and ſtrook with a ſuddain Stupidity the Counſels of <hi>France,</hi> on purpoſe to diſſipate thoſe unjuſt Deſigns which her Falſe Politicks had ſug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſted to her, no leſs then the Aſſailing of all <hi>Europe</hi> at a Time; according to the Proverb, <hi>Covet all, and Loſe all.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There is no queſtion but that <hi>France</hi> was ſenſible of her Errour, after the Revolution in <hi>England;</hi> for which reaſon ſhe diſcharg'd all her Fury upon poor <hi>Germany,</hi> where the <hi>French</hi> Soldiery exercis'd the utmoſt Extremities of Cruelty and Barbariſm, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe that Electorate belong'd to the Emperour's near Relation and Confederate.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>France</hi> being thus Embark'd upon this Tempeſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Sea, the Proſperity of the Imperial Arms, the Revolution in <hi>England,</hi> and the ſtrict League of all the Confederate Princes for the Defence of the Common Cauſe could not chooſe but raiſe prodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious Storms about his Ears; and therefore finding there was no repairing the Fault ſhe had commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, ſhe was conſtrain'd to careſs and promiſe the <hi>Ottoman</hi> Port whatever Succour the Infidels de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded both of Men and Money to oblige the <hi>Turks</hi> to continue the War. With a Deſign however to deceive and forſake 'em, ſo ſoon as the Court of <hi>France</hi> ſhould find it convenient to agree with the
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:39033:26"/> Emperour. But in regard the <hi>French</hi> have drawn in the <hi>Ottoman</hi> Port, and blinded with their Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſents the Principal Miniſters, and more eſpecially the Mufti, who holds his Dignity for Life, 'tis al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt impoſſible to open the Eyes of the Grand Sultan, who is willing to flatter himſelf with the Hopes of recovering that part of <hi>Hungary</hi> which he haſt loſt. So that as long as the <hi>French</hi> are able to domineer at the Port as they do, 'tis in vain to ſend Embaſſadours thither, to make propoſals of Peace, ſince it ſo abſolutely behoves the Court Politicks of <hi>France</hi> to hinder it, by all manner of means, coſt what it will, either by Money or Poyſon, as we have ſeen. 'Tis not long ſince, that the <hi>French</hi> per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiv'd, that the Miniſters of the Mediatours had made ſome Progreſs in the Interim that our Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter was haſtning to the Port; but their Emiſſaries both at <hi>Conſtantinople</hi> and <hi>Adrianople</hi> overturn'd with Money all the Meaſures that had been taken. So that there is nothing but an Inſurrection in the <hi>Ottoman</hi> Empire, that can ranverſe the Practices and Machinations of <hi>France;</hi> and this is that which the <hi>Chriſtians</hi> ought to meditate, if they deſire a Peace between the two Empires; and there are ways to bring it about, if they would but put 'em in Practice.</p>
            <p>Nor is it to be queſtion'd but that <hi>France</hi> drives on all the Intrigues imaginable in the <hi>Ottoman</hi> Court, where ſhe is in daily fear, leaſt early or late a ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den Truce ſhould be clap'd up between the two Empires, by reaſon of ſome unexpected Inſurrecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, as I have already ſaid. And therefore it is, that the Court of <hi>France</hi> endeavours to ſupplant her Confederate, and to make a Peace with the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour and the Empire, by reſtoring ſeveral Places
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:39033:26"/> which ſhe now holds in <hi>Germany;</hi> becauſe that <hi>Lewis</hi> XIV. and his Miniſters ſee very well, that they can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not continue the War, ſo long as the Confedera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy continue their Union, as hitherto they have done: that being alone by himſelf to bear the Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then of ſo many Enemies, he ſtands in need of Nu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merous Armies to oppoſe the ſame Adverſaries that environ him on every ſide, in <hi>Germany, Flanders, Bra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bant, Catalogna, Navarr</hi> and <hi>Piemont;</hi> but above all, the Conjoyn'd Fleets of <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Holland,</hi> that threaten his Coaſts, and enforce him to an Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſive Expence to guard himſelf from a Deſcent: his Trade being quite loſt, his Subjects reduc'd to utmoſt Miſery, and his Exchequer decreaſing every day, through the decay of Trade, and the Poverty of the Inhabitants of his Kingdom. We muſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve, that <hi>France</hi> would fain have a Peace, while ſhe thinks ſhe has ſome Advantage, before any Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible Blow befall her, which would enforce <hi>Lewis</hi> the Great, to accept of ſuch a Peace as it would pleaſe the Emperour and the Confederates to afford him. 'Tis no leſs certain then, that his Imperial Majeſty, together with the Confederates, have no more to do then to continue the War a little longer, to compaſs their Ends upon <hi>France,</hi> that can never be able to make Head againſt 'em for any long time. Which is the reaſon that we find her already begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning to change her Batteries, at the ſame time that ſhe ſees her ſelf oblig'd to alter her Deſigns in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of the Empire. Formerly nothing would ſerve <hi>Lewis</hi> the XIV. but the Imperial Crown for himſelf, and the Title of King of the <hi>Romans</hi> for the <hi>Dauphin</hi> his Son. But now no more of that: The Grapes are out of his Reach, and therefore
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:39033:27"/> he cries, <hi>They are ſowre.</hi> All thoſe vaſt Deſigns ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving fail'd, and all his Lofty Enterprizes being come to nothing, the Policy that <hi>France</hi> made uſe of when the <hi>Turks</hi> were marching to the Siege of <hi>Vienna,</hi> is now no farther uſeful: the End failing, the means muſt of neceſſity ſurceaſe. Formerly <hi>France</hi> was all for dethroning the Emperour; but now 'tis well if ſhe can keep the Crown upon her Monarch's own Head, in preſerving by the force of her Arms what he has uſurp'd from his Neighbours. Heaven has alter'd the Face of Affairs, by the ill ſucceſs of the <hi>Ottoman</hi> Armes, and thereby confounding the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels of <hi>France;</hi> the deſigns of both being the ſame, and both acting in order to the ſame Ends.</p>
            <p>And as the Deſigns of <hi>France</hi> are chang'd in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of the Emperour, who is the Chief and Head of the Empire, ſo they may be preſum'd to be the ſame in regard of the Electours, who are the Members of it: Formerly, 'twas the Policy of <hi>France</hi> to careſs 'em one after another, to dazle 'em with the Gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deur of <hi>Lewis</hi> the Great, and perſwade 'em to ſide with the Intereſts of that Monarch; ſparing neither for Promiſes nor Preſents to render 'em inclinable to elect <hi>French</hi> Coadjutours. But afterwards they were clearly convinc'd that this was the Apple of Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord which the King of <hi>France</hi> threw into the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire, to the End he might ſwallow 'em up one after another. Now therefore let us ſee what new courſe he takes to manage the Princes of the Empire. They can now no longer be ſerviceable to him in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king the <hi>Dauphin</hi> King of the Romans, in regard they have Check-mated him on that ſide already. So that they have ſpar'd him a world of Trouble, and a great deal of Money which he was wont
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:39033:27"/> to throw away by Shovel-fulls upon that Occaſion. Much leſs is it to be thought that <hi>Lewis</hi> has now any Hopes of being Emperour, ſince I am told, that the Book entitul'd, <hi>The juſt Pretenſions of the King to the Empire,</hi> written by the Sieur <hi>Aubri,</hi> Advocate in the Parliament of <hi>Paris,</hi> ſerves now to no other uſe, then to wrap up Butter and Cheeſe in the Chandlers Shops.</p>
            <p>The Miniſtry of <hi>France</hi> now labours to ſeparate the Electours and Princes of the Empire from the common cauſe (not by the means of Gold or Silver becauſe he finds 'em incorruptible) but by inva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding their Territories by Fire and Sword, as he has done the <hi>Palatinate,</hi> the Dioceſes of <hi>Cologne, Mayence</hi> and <hi>Treves,</hi> with a deſign to enforce 'em to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade the Emperour to accept of a Separate Peace; by which means <hi>France</hi> will remain the Miſtreſs ſtill of the Greateſt part of all her Uſurpations. To which purpoſe ſhe makes a dextrous Uſe of the eaſie Acceſs which the Monks and Jeſuits have to the Perſons of the Roman Catholick Princes, and to intrude among the Miniſters of State, every where extolling the King's Catholicity, and his great deſign to have exterminated Hereſie, had not King <hi>James</hi> been dethron'd. But ſome have ſaid very well in Anſwer to thoſe Emiſſaries, that all thoſe forward Acts of ſeeming Zeal were no other then a ſort of Clumſie Trapans; that they muſt go and tell their Stories to Children and Fools, for that they were no Strangers to the King of <hi>France</hi>'s Religion.</p>
            <p>There is one thing very Remarkable, that <hi>Lewis</hi> XIV. deſigning the Deſtruction of the Empire, was the occaſion of the ſtrengthning it, and of under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>propping
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:39033:28"/> it in ſome meaſure with new Supports, by adding a Ninth Electour to the Electoral College, and more particularly by the Choice which the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour and the Electours have made of the Duke of <hi>Hanover,</hi> to ſupply that Place, to the great Grief of the Court of <hi>France,</hi> who with all her wilely Stra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tagems and falſe Politicks, could not prevent it. The Election of a King of the <hi>Romans,</hi> of Prince <hi>Clement</hi> of <hi>Bavaria,</hi> to the Electorate of <hi>Cologne,</hi> of the Baron of <hi>Elderen</hi> to the Biſhoprick of <hi>Liege,</hi> of the Baron of <hi>Plettenberg</hi> to that of <hi>Munſter,</hi> but more eſpecially the Revolution in <hi>England,</hi> were bitter Morſels for the Moſt Chriſtian King to ſwallow, and ſtill lie heavy upon his Stomach. And whenever <hi>France</hi> comes once to ſee the Bottom of her Exche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quer, there is no queſtion but her Fall will be very great, ſince it was her Money that only upheld her in all the Courts of <hi>Chriſtendom,</hi> that ſhe has plai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter'd over all her Uſurpations, and that ſhe has lull'd ſeveral Princes aſleep, whoſe real Intereſt it was to oppoſe her. Silver is a ſort of Mettal every where acceptable, and the Avarice of the <hi>Switzers</hi> has ſpread it ſelf into ſeveral Courts, according to the ſaying of <hi>Alexander, That there was nothing inacceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to Silver:</hi> tho' <hi>Matchiavell</hi> upholds, <hi>That 'tis a hard matter for Steel to keep poſſeſſion of that which is purchaſed with Gold.</hi> Nevertheleſs we have ſeen the Contrary both in <hi>Germany</hi> and <hi>Flanders,</hi> where the King of <hi>France</hi> bought ſeveral Places with good rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy Money, and has held 'em for ſeveral Years. But give me leave to add this Reaſon for it, I mean the little good Correſpondence at that time between the Princes of the Empire, and the Powder of Gold which their <hi>Jupiter</hi> rain'd among 'em. That Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narch
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:39033:28"/> not only got great Footing within the Terri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tories of his Neighbours, but made his Poſſeſſion good. Witneſs <hi>Strasburg, Hunninghen,</hi> and ſeveral other Places upon the <hi>Rhine,</hi> as <hi>Mayence</hi> and ſeveral Fortreſſes in the Dioceſs of <hi>Cologne,</hi> if Heaven, by a Blow that <hi>France</hi> little expected, had not linked together that Sacred Union, in the Empire, for the Common defence, which all the gilded Politicks of <hi>France</hi> could never prevent, nor her Poyſon put a ſtop to. And this is a Truth never to be contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicted, that the Sincere Union of the Princes of the Empire preſerves 'em from being corrupted, and early or late will render 'em Victorious over the Common Enemy, and put 'em in a Condition of being able to recover what they have, and fix 'em in the Poſſeſſion of what they hold untouch'd. No wonder then that the <hi>French</hi> deſtroy and ruine <hi>Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>many</hi> where they come, becauſe they find they can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not hold it, but muſt ſurrender back all their Uſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pations: tho' by the Havock which they make, they are in hopes to weaken the Strength of their Enemies. 'Twould be but Juſtice then, and what the King of <hi>France</hi> has no ſuch reaſon to wonder at, that he ſhould be one day conſtrain'd to repay the Damages, for the Spoil which his Armies have com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted, in purſuance of his Infernal Politicks.</p>
            <p>During the Reign of <hi>Philip</hi> the II. King of <hi>Spain,</hi> it may be ſaid, that <hi>France</hi> and <hi>Spain</hi> divided <hi>Europe</hi> between 'em; and that they were truly the Two Scales of a Ballance, which the Other Soveraigns endeavour'd to keep in an Equilibrium, and ſided ſometimes with the One, ſometimes with the Other, as their Intereſt directed 'em, in order to keep an Equality of Force, for fear of being ſwallow'd up
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:39033:29"/> by the Strongeſt. But ſince King <hi>Philip</hi>'s time, it may be ſaid, That <hi>Spain</hi> has been continually ſink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing lower and lower; that ſhe has been in good part the Prey of <hi>France;</hi> and that had it not been for the Allies, the French at this Hour would have been not only Maſters of the <hi>Low-Countries,</hi> but of <hi>Madrid</hi> it ſelf. And indeed it may be ſaid, that the Duke of <hi>Alva</hi> lent the firſt helping Hand to the fall of the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Puiſſance, by his Proclamation con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the Tenth Penny in the Year 1569. by his Depriving the People of the Liberty of Conſcience, and the <hi>Maſſacers</hi> that ſucceeded, and which was the real Cauſe of the Revolt of part of the <hi>Low-Countries,</hi> and the Fountain and Original of all the Misfortunes that afterwards befell that Monarchy, which inſtead of ſtriking Dread and Terrour into all <hi>Europe,</hi> and the Other World, is dwindl'd away to that degree of Impuiſſance wherein we now behold it; govern'd 'tis true, by one of the beſt Princes in the World, leading a Pious and Exemplary Life, and void of any Vicious Inclination: and it may be certainly ſaid, that the People and Grandees of the Kingdom are happy under ſo Juſt a King, if they underſtood their Felicity, and would but correſpond with the Pacifick Genius of their Prince. But moſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly the Miniſters and their Adherents make their Advantage of the Good Nature of their Prince to fill their own Purſes by emptying his, and by that means deprive him of his Ability to withſtand the Sworn Enemy of <hi>Spain,</hi> who environs him on every ſide, and who for more then one Age together, has ſtudy'd nothing but his utter Ruine, and makes a dextrous uſe of his Imbecility. The King of <hi>France</hi> has been a long time acquainted with the Conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:39033:29"/> of the preſent Catholick King, and upon that Knowledge it is that the Policy of <hi>France</hi> has built her Deſigns, and ſo well underſtood to carry on her Affairs, that ſhe brought about a Marriage of that Monarch with a Princeſs of <hi>France,</hi> Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to the Duke of <hi>Orleance,</hi> and that meerly to be inform'd of what paſt even in this Catholick Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty's Bed-Chamber, as was ſeen by the Relations frequent in the Court of <hi>France,</hi> and which meerly ſerv'd for Sport among the <hi>French</hi> Ladies, who are naturally enclin'd to Goſſipry, Tittle Tattle, and Railliery. And therefore 'tis a pernicious ſort of Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licy in the Court of <hi>Madrid,</hi> to beſtow the Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of <hi>Spain</hi> upon <hi>France,</hi> and to match their Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigns with the Daughters of <hi>France:</hi> and of this there are recent Proofs that make us ſenſible. For it is certain that the Marriage of the Infanta <hi>Maria Tereſa</hi> to <hi>Lewis</hi> XIV. has brought nothing but War and continual Trouble upon <hi>Spain,</hi> and ſtill will be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come the Occaſion of More, by reaſon of the <hi>Dau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phin</hi>'s Pretenſions, in caſe the Catholick King hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pens to dye without Heirs. 'Twill be in vain then to alledge that <hi>Lewis</hi> the XIV. at his Marriage re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounc'd his Claims with a Solemn Oath: for if he brake his Oath, and all the Princes blame him for doing an unlawful and unjuſt Act, tending to Uſurpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, a Sin againſt Reaſon and Conſcience: 'tis pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently told ye, that he could do nothing to the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judice of a Third Perſon, meaning the <hi>Dauphin</hi> of <hi>France,</hi> the only Offſpring by that Marriage; and uſually in ſuch differences between Soveraigns, the longeſt Sword carries it. <hi>Ratio ultima, Regnum,</hi> was the Motto which Cardinal <hi>Richlieu</hi> caus'd to be engrav'd upon the Armes of <hi>France.</hi> Or if it be not
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:39033:30"/> reaſon, 'tis the definitive Will of Kings, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes Reaſon, if once it proves ſucceſsful. The want of Iſſue by the Catholick King's ſecond Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage with the Princeſs <hi>Palatine</hi> of <hi>Newburgh,</hi> increa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes and ſwells the Ambition of <hi>France;</hi> and 'tis very probable, that <hi>Lewis</hi> the XIV. would not be wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling that the King of <hi>Spain</hi> ſhould happen to dye (which God forbid) during his being enga'd in a War with almoſt all <hi>Europe;</hi> in regard that not ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving his Hands free, he could not ſo eaſily fall upon <hi>Spain</hi> with a ſufficient Force, as he might be able to do, to make himſelf Maſter of that Monarchy, in proſecution of his Hopes and Pretenſions, if his Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholick Majeſty did not prevent him, in his Life<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time. 'Tis the Policy of <hi>France</hi> to inſinuate into the Grandees of <hi>Spain</hi> deſires of enriching themſelves, while they have an Opportunity; to the end that after his Death, they may be able to erect Petty So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vereignties in every Corner of the Kingdom, for there is not any Prince among 'em who wants a Pretenſion, with a promiſe to every one that ſhe will ſtand by Him, and grant him her Protection againſt all Aſſailants; They not conſidering all this while, that <hi>France</hi> will at laſt ſwallow 'em all up, one after another, and that they will become the Sport of <hi>Lewis</hi> the Great, their ſecret Enemy. Who in the mean time by this means enfeebles <hi>Spain,</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenuates the King's Treaſure, and deprives him not only of the power to recover the Places he has loſt, but to defend thoſe which he has yet in his Poſſeſſion, which the <hi>French</hi> wreſt from him by degrees, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe that <hi>Spain</hi> is not in a Condition to make a Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent Oppoſition; as Experience had taught us too apparently, not only during the War, but alſo in
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:39033:30"/> time of Peace. For that ſince the <hi>Pyrenaean</hi> Peace, <hi>Spain</hi> has ſuffer'd the Uſurpation of a great many Provinces, as <hi>Burgundy, Franche Conté,</hi> and Conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derable Portions of the <hi>Low-Countries</hi> and <hi>Catalonia.</hi> And all this, becauſe that <hi>Spain</hi> is a languiſhing and ſickly Body, whoſe Forces waſte by degrees, through the too much ſoftneſs of the Soveraign, and the Greedy Covetouſneſs of the Grandees of the Kingdom. Whereas if the Catholick King would make uſe of his Authority; forſake his Cabinet and Head his Armes, there is no queſtion but that the Face of his Affairs would quickly alter. It be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hoves him for the repleniſhing of his Coffers to ſqueeze the Spunges that have ſwell'd themſelves with his Treaſures, and enrich'd themſelves at the Expences of his Crown and People. A Prince that leads a Soft and Effeminate Life is neither fear'd by his Enemies, nor belov'd by his People. He is lookt upon as a Statue, and reſembles thoſe that wiſh for mighty Things, as if they deſign'd to leave only their Dreams to Poſterity. Whereas a Monarch ought with his own Sword to make the Pen that is to write his Hiſtory: that is to ſay, that his Valour and Proweſs ought to afford his Hiſtoriographer, Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter: otherwiſe he only ſerves to fill up the Cata<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logue of the Kings, and the Day of his Birth, and the Day of his Death are the moſt Illuſtrious and Memorable Parts of all his Hiſtory. A King re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceives his Crown from his Anceſtors, but his Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nown muſt ſpring from himſelf. The Council of <hi>Spain</hi> falls aſleep preſently after a Peace, and many times after a Truce, not conſidering that <hi>France</hi> is always awake, and that ſhe never lays down her Armes but that it Coſts the King of <hi>Spain</hi> ſome or
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:39033:31"/> other of his beſt Towns. It would be ſuperfluous to ſet forth in Painting to the <hi>Spaniards,</hi> the miſery of their Condition, ſhould they once fall under the Deſpotick Dominion of <hi>France.</hi> They need no more then caſt their Eyes upon the lamentable and wretched Eſtate to which the <hi>French</hi> are at this day reduc'd; while ſome are forc'd to wander about the World, expos'd to utmoſt Miſery, to Hunger and Cold, and all this meerly to avoid the Cruelty and Tyranny of their Monarch; and they that remain behind, lie Groaning under the weight of his Iron Scepter that continually bruiſes 'em to death with his Oppreſſions and his Impoſts. The only way therefore for the <hi>Spaniards</hi> to prevent their Ruine, is to countermine the Policy of <hi>France:</hi> to ſuppli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate their Monarch to appoint his Succeſſour in his Life-time; to the end he may be bred up in the Court of <hi>Madrid,</hi> and be ready to oppoſe the Invaſions of <hi>France</hi> after the King's deceaſe. But more eſpecially to beg of the Emperour to put a ſpeedy End to the Turkiſh War, that he may have his Hands at Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty to be aſſiſting to <hi>Spain</hi> at a time of need.</p>
            <p>'Tis alſo an Affair of Great Importance, and moſt Eſſential toward the Preſervation of the Remainder of the <hi>Low-Countries,</hi> and not to relie as the Council of <hi>Spain</hi> does upon her Neighbours; which is the reaſon that they neglect to ſend the True Succour, which it would behove 'em to ſend in time into thoſe Provinces which were within a Fingers Breadth of being utterly loſt, during King <hi>James</hi>'s Reign. And indeed there happen ſo many Changes and Revolutions in the World, that a well advis'd Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narch ought never to relie upon the Forces of Other Princes but his own.</p>
            <pb n="59" facs="tcp:39033:31"/>
            <p>While the Provinces of the Spaniſh Low-Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries were govern'd by Intereſted Vice-Roys, who preferr'd their own private Concerns, before the Preſervation of the Provinces, with which they were entruſted, we ſtill found that <hi>France</hi> ſeiz'd up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on City after City, and is now in Poſſeſſion of whole Provinces; and it may be ſaid that a better thought never came into her Head, then when ſhe abandon'd the Conqueſt of <hi>Italy</hi> (where ſhe Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hauſted her Men and Money) to turn her Forces upon <hi>Flanders,</hi> where all Appearances ſeem'd more eaſie, ſince ſhe ſaw well that Governours were ſent thither only to enrich themſelves: among whom the Greateſt Part minded more the getting of a Million into their Purſes, then the preſervation of the Beſt City in the <hi>Low-Countries!</hi> To avoid which Miſchief, there is a neceſſity of having a Prince for Governour, whoſe particular Intereſt it is to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve 'em, who will march at the Head of his Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, lay out the Subſidies of the People, in defraying the Neceſſary Expences of the People, and take care for the Timely Returns of Money; for that the <hi>Low-Countries</hi> can never ſubſiſt without an Army well pay'd.</p>
            <p>We have met with all theſe Advantages in the Perſon of his Electoral Highneſs the Duke of <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>varia;</hi> and it may be ſaid without flattery, That the Choice which his Catholick Majeſty made of that Prince for the Government of the <hi>Low-Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries,</hi> was one of the beſt and moſt important Hits of State that <hi>Spain</hi> has been for ſome time guilty of. Twas ſuch a Blow to <hi>France,</hi> as broke all the Mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures ſhe had taken, during the Government of <hi>Gaſtanaga;</hi> nor could <hi>Lewis</hi> XIV. ward off this
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:39033:32"/> Blow which the King of <hi>England</hi> gave him, without ever giving him warning to guard himſelf.</p>
            <p>'Tis a thing no leſs obſervable then wonderful, That the Council of <hi>Spain</hi> having no more then this little Corner of the Earth to guard, ſhould neglect it as They do; ſeeing that good Policy re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires, that <hi>Spain</hi> ſhould drein herſelf, rather then part with it, were it for nothing elſe but to ſerve her as an Amuzement to the Arms of <hi>France,</hi> as we have found it to have been in all the laſt and preſent Wars, and the Counterguard that keeps the moſt Chriſtian King from Marching to the very Walls of <hi>Madrid</hi> it ſelf. The reaſon of this Careleſsneſs may well be thought to be the Popular Errour of the Inhabitants of <hi>Flanders</hi> and <hi>Brabant,</hi> who tell the Hollanders, when they upbraid 'em with their Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſsneſs as to their own Preſervation, <hi>'Tis you that ought to defend us, for the ſake of your own Interest.</hi> And indeed, there is ſome reaſon for this Opinion. But the chief reaſon proceeds from the Avarice of the Spaniſh Miniſters, who ſhroud themſelves under this Miſtake, which ſerves 'em to heap up Wealth, while the King their Sovereign is engag'd on every ſide to preſerve himſelf.</p>
            <p>The Policy of <hi>France,</hi> together with her Louid'ors, works now the ſame Effect with the which formerly <hi>Philip</hi> II. wrought by virtue of his Doublon's. For I have heard ſay, That ev'n in Time of Peace, there was not any Place in the <hi>Low-Countries</hi> where <hi>Lewis</hi> XIV. had not his Creatures and his Cabals rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to declare themſelves in Time and Place, and when an Opportunity requir'd. And certain it is, That if this were not the whole which was then ſaid, 'tis
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:39033:32"/> a good part of the Truth. For having beheld what we have ſeen in our days, in reference to that impregnable City of <hi>Luxemburgh,</hi> and the Acquiſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the whole Province that follow'd, we ought to be convinc'd, that that ſame Place of ſo great mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment was not obtain'd by the Bravery and Courage only of the French. There is no better way then, to diſappoint thoſe Treacheries, then by often chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging the Garriſons, and ſometimes the Governors themſelves; but above all things, to Pay well, and Puniſh without Exception, when there is the leaſt Fault committed. The <hi>Low-Countries</hi> are, at pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, like an Inſolvent Houſe, that muſt be re-ſettl'd by good Oeconomy, and by affording the Inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitants the Means of being able to contribute to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards it.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Low-Countries</hi> have a long time been the Mark at which the Court of <hi>France</hi> has aim'd. Upon the leaſt Diſpute, or Pretence of a Quarrel with the Court of <hi>Spain,</hi> in ſhe pours with all her Fury upon the <hi>Low-Countries,</hi> like an impetuous Torrent; plun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, burns, and never retreats without ſome conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derable Loppings which ſhe diſmembers from the Body of the Tree. Which nevertheleſs is not a Miſchief never to be remedy'd; ſince the Sea it ſelf is many times reſtrain'd by Cauſeys and Mounds, though it be an Element a thouſand times more to be fear'd then the Policy and Pride of <hi>Lewis</hi> XIV. And this is that which the Duke of <hi>Bavaria,</hi> and the reſt of his Brave Confederates muſt do, to ſtop and curb the rapid Inundations of <hi>France.</hi> They muſt look upon the French Monarch as one that thun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders in all his Forces and his Fury upon thoſe Places where he is ſure to find but little Reſiſtance, and
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:39033:33"/> from ſuch Victories as thoſe he reaps his greateſt Honour. I confeſs, that a Prince who is violent, and a Uſurper, is happy ſo long as Fortune goes hand in hand with his Natural Humour. But in regard ſhe grows weary, for the moſt part, of al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways carrying one Man upon her Back, we alſo find that the ſame Prince becomes unproſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous, when Fortune changes her Mind, or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, when there is an Oppoſition made againſt him. And therefore, if we may build upon out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Appearances, and if there be any thing of Prognoſtication in the Preſentiments of Wiſe and Judicious Men, the <hi>Low-Countries</hi> may well hope, by the Bleſſing of Heaven, the prudent Conduct of their Great and Sage Governor and Leader, and the ſincere Intentions of the Confederates, to be ſoon deliver'd from the Yoke and Barbarity of <hi>France,</hi> and enjoy the Fat of a fruitful Soil, that has ſo long fed ſo many Thouſands of Foreigners, both Men and Beaſts.</p>
            <p>From the <hi>Low-Countries</hi> I croſs over into <hi>England,</hi> where I find, that the Revolution which hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen'd in the Year 1689. affords a large Field, and ample Matter to ſupply my Diſcourſe. The Court of <hi>France</hi> not only cry'd <hi>The Town's our's,</hi> but <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rope</hi>'s <hi>my own</hi> ſo ſoon as ſhe beheld <hi>James</hi> II. upon the Throne of <hi>Great Britain.</hi> I ſhall not here en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>large upon the Accident that ſet him in the Throne. But certain it is that, <hi>France</hi> and He had long and paſſionately waited for the happy Minute; for that according to their Saying between 'em, <hi>Charles</hi> II. was a meer Slugg, and had neither vigour nor cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage to put in Execution the Projects that <hi>France</hi> was a Brewing. But far from that, <hi>Charles</hi> II. wanted
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:39033:33"/> neither Policy nor Ingenuity, and might have gone to his Grave with the Character of Prudent and Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous, but for his ſcandalous Inclinations for Women. However, it may be aſſuredly ſaid, That the Match to which he was in a manner driven againſt his own Conſent, made him diſguſt Matrimony, and threw him into a Vein of wanton Courtſhip. 'Tis true, 'twas a Weakneſs in him too apparent for his Honour; but <hi>France,</hi> and his Brother the Duke of <hi>York,</hi> knew how to make their Advantage of it. And therefore the Joy of <hi>Lewis</hi> XIVth's Court was not to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiv'd, ſo ſoon as both He and his Adherents under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood the Death of that good Prince, and the Eleva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of <hi>James</hi> II. to the Throne; the Jeſuits rejoyc'd in particular; and never was ſuch Poſting backwards and forwards between <hi>Verſailles</hi> and <hi>London,</hi> as after the King of <hi>England</hi>'s Death came to be publickly known at the French Court. And there was ſome reaſon for it; for that then it was, that the French Council began to take terrible Reſolutions, in order to the putting in Execution a Deſign that <hi>France</hi> had kept conceal'd in her Breaſt for many Years before. She began with the Revocation of the Edict of <hi>Nants;</hi> a Thing which ſhe durſt not meddle with, ſo long as King <hi>Charles</hi> was alive, (though that Prince, in his heart, was none of the Devouteſt Religionaries; but a Politician much more, and one who obſerv'd his Meaſures, by reaſon of his Parliament, that was well inform'd that <hi>England</hi> was the Garrantee of that Edict.) But ſo ſoon as <hi>James</hi> II. became ſole Maſter in <hi>England,</hi> the Court of <hi>France</hi> gave her ſelf her full ſwinge, and puſh'd on her Deſign upon <hi>Europe,</hi> might and main, becauſe that then there was no longer any fear of <hi>England,</hi> which was the only Puiſſance that
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:39033:34"/> could either diſappoint or advance her Enterp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap> And this was a Truth at all times ſo well know<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> the Kings of <hi>England,</hi> that <hi>Hen.</hi> VIII. made a Me<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> of Gold, upon which was engrav'd a Hand ſtret<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it ſelf out of a Cloud, and holding a Pair of Sca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> that were equally poiz'd, with this Motto, <hi>M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Friendſhip turns the Beam.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But in King <hi>James</hi>'s Time it was not <hi>Eng<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> turn'd the Scale, but <hi>France,</hi> while <hi>England</hi> like <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Ox, ignorant of his own Strength, tamely ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>render'd her Neck to the Golden Yoke of <hi>Lewi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> XIV.</p>
            <p>Formerly the Policy of <hi>France</hi> ſent to the Court of <hi>England</hi> Lovely French Nymphs to cultivate the Hearts of the Engliſh Lords, and of the Monarch himſelf. But during King <hi>James</hi>'s Reign, another ſort of Vermin were made uſe of, and Monks and Jeſuits were ſent in Shoals, that like ſo many Caterpil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers and Locuſts devour'd the Country; and who had already diſpers'd themſelves over all the Kingdom, and had made themſelves Maſters of the King and his Privy-Council, to the great grief of all his good Subjects. What a Heart-breaking muſt it needs be to the ſounder Party at Court, to ſee a Father <hi>Peters</hi> Chief in the Privy-Council, pearch'd upon one of the higheſt Dignities in the Kingdom, ſlighting and domineering over the Lords and Peers of the Realm, as having got the Soveraign Authority into his Hands, and for that the King and the Queen (a Princeſs tranſported altogether by her Paſſion) ſuffer'd them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to be deluded and govern'd by this <hi>Tartuff</hi> of a Hypocrite, and he over-rul'd by Father <hi>La Chaiſe,</hi> who had all his Orders from the Court of <hi>France.</hi> By which it may be eaſie to judge in what Condition
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:39033:34"/> 
               <hi>France</hi> was at that time; what Devils haunted both <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Court and the Kingdom, trampl'd o're the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>ks of the King's beſt Subjects, and were juſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>oſing the People to the Rage of Queen <hi>Mary</hi>'s <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ign, who allow'd her Subjects no other Choice <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> of the <hi>Maſs</hi> or the <hi>Faggot.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ey who ſeriouſly conſider the Policy of <hi>France</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> reſpect of <hi>England,</hi> during the Reign of King <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ames</hi> the II. will find the Game but very ill play'd, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eeing that in ſo ſhort a time it gave an occaſion to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Revolution ſo dangerous to <hi>France.</hi> But ſo it hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen'd, becauſe that <hi>Lewis</hi> XIV. not foreſeeing the Conſequences, after he had once given a looſe Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty to the Monks and Jeſuits, was no longer Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter of the Affair; and thoſe Vermin puſht on King <hi>James</hi> with ſo much precipitancy, that he being de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſirous to do too much at once, they ranvers'd at the ſame time all the Deſigns of <hi>France,</hi> and caſt him headlong from the Throne into an Abyſs, from whence he will never be able to riſe again ſo long as he lives: nor will all the Power of <hi>France,</hi> nor the deteſtable Wealth and Politicks of the Jeſuits be able to reſtore him again.</p>
            <p>If the Court of <hi>France</hi> were ſo exceſſive in their Rejoycing upon the Coronation of King <hi>James,</hi> we may aſſure our ſelves, that they were no leſs drown'd in Tears of Grief and Rage upon his A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bandoning the Crown. And then it was, that all the beſt Head-pieces, both Jeſuits and Courtiers, met together which way to apply ſome proper Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medies to a Blow ſo fatal and ſo unlookt for: and then it was that <hi>Lewis</hi> XIV. acknowledg'd his Error in following the Marquis of <hi>Louvois</hi>'s Counſel, which was to attack <hi>Philipsburgh</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtead
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:39033:35"/> of <hi>Maeſtritcht,</hi> and give the Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> an Opportunity to paſs un-diſturb'd into <hi>England</hi> But that which deceiv'd <hi>France,</hi> was an Army o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Forty thouſand Men which King <hi>James</hi> had a-foot, of which a great part were Iriſh, and a Fleet of Forty Men of War riding out at Sea; which indeed was a Force ſufficient both by Sea and Land to have reſiſted ſo ſmall a number as attended the Prince in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>England.</hi> But it may be ſaid, that that ſame great Body was a meer Monſter, all Arms but no Head, and whoſe Veins were fill'd with Water only inſtead of Blood. And if <hi>France</hi> had bethought her ſelf to have ſounded in the firſt Place, the Heart of King <hi>James,</hi> ſhe would have found there more of Cowar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice then Courage, and without queſtion ſhe would have march'd her Troops to the Lower inſtead of ſend<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ng them to the Upper <hi>Rhine.</hi> But by this we ſee that there is a certain Deſtiny which all the Wiſdom, all the Force and Induſtry of mortal Man cannot eſcape.</p>
            <p>But now the Conſtitution of the Court of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> being chang'd by the Alteration of the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, there was a neceſſity for the Court of <hi>France</hi> to change her Batteries, and to employ all her Politicks which way to dethrone the reigning King, whether by the Sword, by Fire or by Poyſon, 'twas indifferent to her, provided ſhe attain'd her Ends: and for the Truth of this, we have ſufficient Proofs; the Teſtimony of <hi>Grandvall</hi> at his Death, and the authentick Depoſitions of <hi>Demont,</hi> who is ſtill living to the Shame and Confuſion of <hi>France;</hi> the Remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance of which will be a laſting Stain to her Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour; a Fact which her ſucceeding Princes will deny, as a Reproach to their Poſterity, and for which Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtories
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:39033:35"/> only furniſh us with the Exrmple of <hi>Darius,</hi> King of <hi>Perſia,</hi> who not being able to vanquiſh his Enemy <hi>Alexander</hi> in Battel, treacherouſly labour'd to have won the Grecian Soldiers either to kill or be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tray their Prince. And for that it was that the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedonian Victor upbraided <hi>Darius</hi>'s Embaſſadors, when they came to ſue for Peace, and to return him Thanks for the Civilities he had ſhew'd to his Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, his Wife and his two Daughters; to which Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſadour the <hi>Macedonian</hi> Monarch thus began his Anſwer. <hi>Tell your Maſter, that Thanks are ſuperflu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous among Soldiers that make War one upon another; and therefore if I were Civil and Courteous towards his Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations, 'twas only to ſatisfie my ſelf, and not out of any Affection that I bear to him; for 'tis not my Humour to inſult over the Miſerable. I never attack Priſoners nor Women, I only aſſail thoſe that I meet with Weapons in their Hands, and who are in a Condition to defend them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves. So that if he ſincerely deſir'd Peace, I ſhould conſider what I had to do, but ſeeing that he ſtill continues by Letters and Money to ſollicit my Soldiers, to betray me, and my Friends to Kill me, I am reſev'd to purſue him to the uttermoſt of my Power, no longer as an Enemy, but as a Poyſoner, and a Ruffian,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>'Tis not to be deny'd, but that when any man de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigns to murther his Enemy, 'tis becauſe he dreads him with a more then Ordinary Fear, and to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prive his more valiant Adverſary by ſuch a Coward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and deteſtable Action of the Honour of vanquiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing him in Battel. But ſuch Aſſaſſins never come to good End: for <hi>Darius</hi> periſh'd miſerably, being murder'd by his own Subjects, and at the ſame time <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oſt both his Life, his Diadem and all the Wealth of <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>ſia.</hi> But to return to our Subject.</p>
            <pb n="66" facs="tcp:39033:36"/>
            <p>During the Reign of King <hi>James, France</hi> ſent into <hi>England</hi> whole Legions of Monks and Jeſuits, under pretence of Propagating the Faith, and to ſcrew themſelves into the moſt conſiderable Families of the Realm, under pretence of Religion, as alſo to aſſiſt this Unfortunate Prince, to obſerve his Footſteps and dive into his ſecret Thoughts, to the end he might not be able to avoid the Chains which the Court of <hi>France</hi> had prepar'd for him. But now the Emiſſaries of <hi>France</hi> have alter'd their Language; and whereas at that time they preach'd nothing to the <hi>Engliſh</hi> but Peace and Obedience there; now they breath nothing but Fire and Flame, Sedition and Murder where e're they come, fomenting Rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lion in all parts of the Kingdom, and ready once more to fire the City of <hi>London,</hi> if they believ'd the Conflagration would contribute any thing to their wicked Deſigns.</p>
            <p>The whole Policy and Craft of <hi>France</hi> is at a great Loſs at this Conjuncture, to find that all her Machi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations againſt the Life of the King of <hi>England,</hi> at preſent proſperouſly Reigning, are ſtill diſappoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. Nor is it leſs a bitter Choak-Pear to <hi>Lewis</hi> XIV. the Proudeſt Monarch upon Earth, to ſee himſelf at laſt conſtrain'd to acknowledge his Britta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nick Majeſty the Lawful Monarch of the Three Kingdoms, and ſue to him for Peace; and all this after he had Vaunted before all the World that he would never lay down his Arms <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ll he had reſtor'd King <hi>James</hi> to his Throne, not without a prophane and Daring Application of the words of God the Father to the Son. <hi>Sit thou at my Right hand till I make thy Enemies thy Foot-ſtool.</hi> Now after ſuch a Bounce, a man would think it ſhould be a trouble to
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:39033:36"/> the Court of <hi>France</hi> to find her ſelf conſtrain'd to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſs this poor unfortunate Prince. But there will be no ſuch Thing: For when Perſons that have been profitable to the Court of <hi>France</hi> become once un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerviceable, ſhe never ſcruples to ſend 'em packing in cold Blood. 'Tis true that ſhe obſerves ſome Mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures, and lets yee know her Mind at firſt by Hints and indirect Whiſpers: but if you do not underſtand her Mute Language and Dumb Signs, ſhe fails not to inform your Stupidity with plain and down-right Expreſſions: it being a Maxim of the <hi>French</hi> Court, never to love the Unfortunate. But you'l ſay, what Benefit can accrue to <hi>Lewis</hi> XIV. by keeping King <hi>James</hi> in <hi>France:</hi> 'tis not for the Benefit of his Counſel; for he could never give or take any him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf; nor is it out of any heat of Concupiſcence for the Queen of <hi>England;</hi> for he has much handſomer and Prettier in his Seraglio of St. <hi>Cyr,</hi> where Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam <hi>de Maintenon</hi> out of her Pious Care, for ſeveral Years together has kept in good <hi>decorum</hi> a numerous Bevie of young handſome Ladies, who are as it were ſo many Victims which ſhe offers to the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinity of <hi>Lewis the Great;</hi> and though that Monarch had not that Reſerve for his little Pleaſures, the Court is full of <hi>Coquetts,</hi> and the Mothers are ſuch <hi>Ninny-hammers</hi> as to carry their Daughters thither, to try whether or no their good Fortune will advance 'em to the Embraces of that Great Monarch, and all this in hopes to raiſe the drooping condition of their Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily. Inſomuch that I have known ſome Parents condeſcend to that point of Panderiſm, as to Leſſon their Daughters and inſtruct 'em what they were to ſay and do, in caſe the King ſhould happen to take notice of 'em. So that moſt aſſuredly, it would not
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:39033:37"/> be to Queen <hi>Jemmykin</hi> that the Sultan of <hi>France</hi> would throw his Handkerchief, unleſs it were with that Limi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation that <hi>Alexander</hi> obſerv'd, who refus'd to exerciſe at the Olympick Games, unleſs he might have Kings for his Competitors. And thus <hi>Lewis</hi> XIV. grown more Great perhaps then formerly, would have the World believe, that he'll no longer be a Gameſter in the Sports of Love, unleſs he may have Queens for the Objects of his Paſſion. However, the King grows old, and therefore let us be ſo favourable to him as to believe, that if the Court of <hi>France</hi> did entertain King <hi>James</hi> and all his Train at St. <hi>Germains,</hi> 'twas not for any Affection the <hi>French</hi> Monarch bare him, but becauſe the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Fugitive who generally, feeds upon Chimera's, fancy'd Himſelf, and endeavour'd to perſwade the Court of <hi>France</hi> that he had a Great Party in <hi>England;</hi> not only all the <hi>Roman Catholicks,</hi> but all the Fanaticks in the Kingdom. That the <hi>Quaker Penn,</hi> who indeed is no other then a Jeſuit in Maſquerade, aſſur'd him of the Abſolute Devotion of that whole Sect to his Party and Service. But the Court of <hi>France</hi> has been well inform'd, that all theſe Aſſurances were meer Illuſions, ſeeing that neither Catholicks nor Quakers are admitted into the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, nor into any the meaneſt Offices in the Kingdom; and that it would be a very difficult thing not to ſay an Impoſſibility to embody all thoſe that go by the Name of <hi>Jacobites,</hi> ſcatter'd up and down in ſeveral Parts of the Kingdom, and for the moſt part known to be ſuch. Beſides that, we find that no ſooner a Dozen of theſe Rebels meet together, but they are preſently diſcover'd; a viſible Sign of the Care that Divine Providence takes for the Preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation of their Brittanick Majeſties; and that the
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:39033:37"/> ſame Providence watches over 'em, while they, without intermiſſion, labour to ſettle the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, to protect the Nation againſt their Enemies, and to re-advance the Honour of the Britiſh Name, beyond what the Princes, their Predeceſſors, have done for ſeveral Ages.</p>
            <p>There is no queſtion to be made but that the King of <hi>France,</hi> or his Council, is very well inform'd of the Conſtitution of <hi>England,</hi> and that it will be in vain for their Enemies to attempt any thing there, ſo long as the King and his Parliament are united together, as we find 'em at this Day. Inſomuch, that this good Correſpondence has furniſh'd the King with powerful Supplies, to oppoſe his Enemies both by Sea and Land, tho' their Number were double to what it is at this Day. For that ſo long as the Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh have a formidable Fleet upon their Coaſts, who ſhall be ſo daring as to attack 'em? Not <hi>France,</hi> I'm ſure. Beſides, that if they can but come to grapple with their lurking Enemy, the French would ſoon be conſtrain'd to quit their Coaſts. So that all things being conſider'd, there is nothing more for <hi>France</hi> to do, but to give over the War with <hi>England;</hi> for that unleſs they be Maſters of the Sea, their Trade is loſt, and they are abſolutely ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in'd, not being able to ſell their Wines, their Bran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, and other Products of the Kingdom; beſides that, they are forc'd to drein themſelves of all their ready Money to pay the King's Subſidies; with a number of Impoſitions and Taxes with which the Kingdom ſwarms. And which is worſt of all, their Harveſts having fail'd for Two Years together, from whence ſhall they have Corn if they be not Maſters of the Sea? more eſpecially being at War with the
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:39033:38"/> Hollanders, and excluded out of <hi>Spain,</hi> which has ſeveral times ſupply'd their Wants. So that 'tis no marvel that the French begin to be weary of the War, eſpecially with <hi>England;</hi> and that he no longer ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerves any Meaſures with King <hi>James,</hi> who at pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent reſembles one of one thoſe petty Saints, to whom they will not put themſelves to the trouble of light<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing up a ſmall Wax Candle, becauſe they neither cure any Diſeaſes, nor are able to make their Guardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an's Pot boil.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>France</hi> has begun a War, which ſhe will not get quit of when ſhe pleaſes her ſelf. Her Monarch has a long time acted <hi>Orlando Furioſo,</hi> and affronted both in Word and Deed, a Prince that was not in a Condition to defend himſelf; but now that Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> by a miraculous Conduct, has plac'd the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jur'd Prince upon the Brittiſh Throhe, 'tis not for the Court of <hi>France</hi> to think, that God, by his Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence has ſo highly exalted that Prince, has con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferr'd upon him the Government of ſeveral King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms and Provinces, and put ſo great a Power into the Hands of the only Prince that <hi>France</hi> is afraid of; a Prince that has ſo well united the greateſt part of the Princes of <hi>Europe,</hi> in order to make a vigorous War againſt the common Enemy, who by degrees has ſo largely uſurp'd upon their Domini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and all this only to render more conſpicuous the Honour of <hi>Lewis</hi> XIV. as his Emiſſaries give out. 'Tis never to be believ'd; and they that ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine it, muſt be either void of Sence, or be of the Number of thoſe Phanaticks that have no more Wit then to adhere to King <hi>James.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But if <hi>France</hi> can get nothing by a War with <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> ſhe may be much a loſer, conſidering the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:39033:38"/> Condition of her Affairs. For ſhould the Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh once happen to ſet Foot in <hi>France,</hi> they have not forgot their Right to <hi>Normandy, Guienne, Poiton,</hi> and <hi>Lunguedock.</hi> When the Engliſh quitted <hi>Calais,</hi> they promis'd the French Governour, who came to take poſſeſſion of it, to return when their Sins were not ſo crying loud as thoſe of the French. At leaſt the Court of <hi>France</hi> is not to believe that the Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh will let 'em alone in the quiet Poſſeſſion of <hi>Dun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kirk;</hi> a Place that is no more the Patrimony of the Kings of <hi>France,</hi> then <hi>Strasburgh.</hi> They that ſold both the one and the other of thoſe Cities, had no right to make the Bargain: <hi>France</hi> treated with thoſe that were under Age. Now we know that what an Infant Sells or Contracts for, is lyable to be cancell'd. <hi>Charles</hi> the Second had neither conquer'd nor pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chas'd <hi>Dunkirk;</hi> he found it annex'd to the Crown upon his return to his Kingdoms; nor was it for him to ſell it, to ſatisfie the Avarice of his Chancel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lor. So that the Kings his Predeceſſors, have ſtill an undeniable Right, either to regain it by Force of Arms, or recover it by Treaty of Peace, with much more Equity and Juſtice, then the Chamber of <hi>Metz</hi> can pretend, to make Reunions to the Crown of <hi>France.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The words <hi>ſurrender back,</hi> are doubtleſs very hard of Digeſtion to <hi>Lewis</hi> the Great, who pretends at all times to be the only Perſon that can reſtore Peace to <hi>Europe:</hi> and therefore he ought in the firſt place to underſtand what Reſtitution is. The Greateſt and Wiſeſt of Kings aſſures us, That De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction preſſes cloſe upon the Heels of the Proud; and as I have already ſaid, Fortune grows weary of always carrying the ſame Prince upon her Back.
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:39033:39"/> There are many Reaſons why <hi>France</hi> ſhould ſink, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter all the Cruelties ſhe has committed, and which are not yet at an end. People trail their Chains after 'em for ſome time without much complaint; but 'tis with a deſign to break 'em upon the firſt Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity: and there is no queſtion to be made, but that if the <hi>Engliſh</hi> once ſet Foot aſhore with their Prince at the Head of 'em, but that the greateſt part will receive him as their Deliverer. And I dare be bold to affirm, that there are at Preſent a Great Number in <hi>France</hi> who wiſh it, and wait for their Deliverance, and that there is hardly a Lord at Court, or a Prince of the Blood, who does not pray for the bringing down their Monarch, and the Proſperity of the Confederates Armes. The Race of <hi>Valois</hi> ended in <hi>France</hi> for leſs Crimes then thoſe that <hi>Bourbon</hi> has committed. But there is a preciſe Time appointed for humbling the Monarchs of the World, conceal'd from Humane Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, and it is a Folly to go about to penetrate in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a Secret which Divine Providence has reſerv'd to it ſelf. However we ſee the King of <hi>France</hi> tries all Ways and Means to Support himſelf, like a Man that ſtrives againſt Death. He ruins his Subjects to maintain his Armies; he Impoveriſhes 'em, to conſtrain 'em to turn Soldiers. He calls in all their Money, embaſes it, and pays 'em with New Money enhaunc'd above a Third part of the True Value, to fill his Coffers, He ſeizes upon all the Church-Pla<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e, and what belongs to private Perſons, and coins it into Money; and the better to inveigle the People as it were to follow his Example, he ſends his own Plate Firſt of all to the Mint, and ſends for it back the next day. There is not
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:39033:39"/> any Tax, or Toll, or Impoſition that has eſcap'd the Invention of his <hi>Flint-Skinners;</hi> ſo that the greateſt part of all the Handycraft Tradeſmen and Peaſants have abandon'd their Farms and their Houſes, to wander about and beg their Bread, or elſe to ſeek their Livelihoods in foreign Countries. I have often with my own Ears heard very good Men and Old Catholicks cry out, <hi>When will the Prince of</hi> Orange, meaning the King of <hi>England</hi> now reigning, <hi>come and deliver us from all our Miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries.</hi> Rightly judging, That the Engliſh are They who can only give that Lucky Blow; by reaſon that their nearneſs to the Coaſts of <hi>France</hi> facilitates their Entrance into the Kingdom. The Court of <hi>France</hi> knows this to be true, and therefore takes ſo much care to line their Coaſts: tho' the King of <hi>France</hi>'s whole Army would not ſuffice to guard a Compaſs of 300 Leagues in Extent ſo well as they ſhould do, to prevent the Enemies landing in ſome part or other: Where they that land have no more to do then only to ſtand the Firſt Shot; for the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond Diſcharge will prove very moderate; and for the Third, there will be no occaſion to fear it.</p>
            <p>I affirm then, that the <hi>Engliſh</hi> alone are able to harraſs <hi>France</hi> more then any of the Confederates, to put her to an Exceſſive Expence, which dreins her Treaſury, forces the King to oppreſs his Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects that he may repleniſh his Coffers, provokes the Malecontents to ſhake off the Yoke of a Deſpotick Government, and to deſire a Government like that of <hi>England,</hi> which beyond all contradiction is the moſt Juſt and moſt Equitable, as well for the King, as for the People; every one there enjoying their
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:39033:40"/> Rights and Privileges, the King his due Preroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives, and the People their Repoſe.</p>
            <p>If any one of the Republicks of <hi>Europe</hi> be able to infuſe Jealouſies and Fears into <hi>France,</hi> it is the Republick of the United Provinces, which is at preſent the moſt potent, the moſt Illuſtrious, the moſt glorious, and the moſt wealthy Republick in the World. I acknowledge that <hi>Venice</hi> may diſpute the Point of Antiquity with her: otherwiſe there is no Compariſon to be made between 'em. No wonder then that her Neighbouring Puiſſance has drawn upon her the Envy of <hi>France.</hi> The Policy of her Miniſters, ever ſince the Beginning of this Reign, has very Judiciouſly exercis'd it ſelf in finding out the moſt clever and probable ways to ſwallow up thoſe Provinces, either by Conqueſt or by Ruining 'em, to which purpoſe Meaſures have been taken a long while ago. And <hi>Lewis</hi> XIV. at the Beginning of the War 1672. did ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily believe to have compaſs'd his Deſigns: having invaded the States at a Time when they rely'd upon the Faith and Sincerity of Treaties, and had neither any Forces a foot, nor any General to lead 'em; Good Husbandry being Natural to Republicks in Time of Peace. Nevertheleſs <hi>France</hi> could not ſtrike that Blow ſo home as ſhe deſir'd, without the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent of <hi>England;</hi> and therefore it was that the Court of <hi>France</hi> was ſo careful to improve their Friendſhip with <hi>Charles</hi> II. ſparing neither for Money nor the Allurements of Pleaſure to inveigle and faſten him to their Intereſts, and to cauſe him to bury in Obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vion all the Benefits he had receiv'd from the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>publick and the Houſe of <hi>Orange.</hi> Nor would <hi>France</hi>
               <pb n="75" facs="tcp:39033:40"/> quit her Hold, till <hi>England</hi> had in conjunction with her, declar'd War againſt the United Provinces, where the Embaſſadors of <hi>France</hi> had for ſome Years labour'd underhand by the Inticing Baits of Gold and Silver to gain Creatures within the Republick, ſince which time the Count <hi>d' Avaux</hi> underſtood ſo well to follow their Steps, that he out-did 'em. For that being Young, and a Courtier, he made his Love of Women ſerviceable to get him Admittance into certain Families that had ſome ſhare in the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment; and there were few Cities where he had not his Creatures, who gave him Intelligence of all things that paſt in Council; and ſome there were, who like <hi>Nicodemus</hi>'s came to him by Night, not daring to appear in the day-time.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="75-142" type="pages">
            <p>The Greateſt Policy of <hi>France</hi> was always to fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment Diviſion between <hi>England</hi> and the United Provinces; afraid of nothing more then a good Correſpondence and Union between the Two Puiſſances. Nor did ſhe ſee any way more Probable to compaſs her Ends upon the United Provinces then by ſticking cloſe to <hi>England;</hi> which had fallen out luckily for her, during the two preceding Reigns while ſhe amus'd thoſe two Princes with Hopes of ſharing in the Conqueſt. And upon this Score <hi>Lewis</hi> XIV. had very little trouble to perſwade <hi>James</hi> the Second to cloſe with him; for that in his Heart he was an Enemy to the United Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinces and the Houſe of <hi>Orange;</hi> beſides that he was beſieg'd by the Monks and Jeſuits, and parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cularly by Father <hi>Peters,</hi> who kept him under the awe of the <hi>Ferula,</hi> putting him in hopes of Great Rewards from Heaven, in caſe he would lend his
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:39033:41"/> Helping hand to deſtroy the Hereticks; perſwading him that the United Provinces were the Center of Hereſie. So that he added to his private Hatred that Biggotry, which thoſe Hypocrites of Monks continually blew in his Ears. And indeed, all Things were in a ready forwardneſs to recommence, in Conjunction with <hi>France,</hi> a new War againſt <hi>Hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land.</hi> The King's Inclinations were altogether bent that way, and the Thing would have had the Effect deſir'd, ſo ſoon as <hi>James</hi> the Second had once ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain'd to be Maſter of his Parliament, had aboliſh'd the Fundamental Law of the Kingdom, and lay'd low the Heads of ſome of the principal Lords, the beſt Affected toward the Wellfare of the Kingdom, and the Preſervation of the Privileges of the Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. But the Revolution in <hi>England</hi> falling out ſo unexpectedly toward the end of the Year 1688. and the Year following, fended off the Blow, and broke all the Meaſures of thoſe Two Princes; to which we may add, the rejecting of the Cardinal of <hi>Fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtenburgh</hi> from being Archbiſhop of <hi>Cologne.</hi> All theſe Events, ſo contrary to the Expectation of <hi>Lewis</hi> XIV. very much contributed toward the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation of the <hi>Low-Countries.</hi> For there is no doubt but the Cardinal, who is a Man dangerous; turbulent, actuated by the Demon of <hi>France,</hi> to whom he has ſold and devoted himſelf, ſince he with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drew himſelf from his Obedience to the Emperor, his lawful Sovereign, was int<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oduc'd into the Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of <hi>Cologne,</hi> only to be the Tool and Organ, by whoſe means the Moſt Chriſtian King might the more eaſily diſturb the States of the United Provin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces But all theſe ways failing, tho' not his good Will, and finding he could not be aſſiſted, either
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:39033:41"/> by <hi>Cologne,</hi> nor <hi>England,</hi> nor by the Biſhop of <hi>Mun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter,</hi> as in the preceding War, <hi>France</hi> could no lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger contain her ſelf, but under pretence of aſſiſting King <hi>James,</hi> preſently declar'd War, and fell upon the United Provinces to prevent 'em from aggrandi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zing themſelves by the ſincere and ſtrict Union which they were about to make between the King and Queen at preſent proſperouſly reigning. But in regard that frequently Revenge never conſiders the Danger to which it expoſes it ſelf for the ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction of its Rage, in like manner the King of <hi>France</hi> has drawn upon himſelf, all of a ſudden, the the moſt numerous, and the ſoundeſt part of the Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſſances of <hi>Europe,</hi> who will never lay down their Arms till he has made thoſe Reſtitutions, which they ſhall think convenient for the Welfare of <hi>Europe;</hi> there being no other way of Reliance upon the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes and Faith of the Moſt Chriſtian King.</p>
            <p>I believe that <hi>Lewis</hi> XIV. ſpake juſt according to the Sentiments of his Heart, when he happen'd one Day to ſay, <hi>That he neither Fear'd nor Lov'd the Hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>landers,</hi> who nevertheleſs fill'd him full of Jealouſies and Fears, and often broke his Meaſures. And yet 'tis to that warlike Nation, that he is at this Day be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holding for his having got the upper-hand of <hi>Spain:</hi> For as <hi>France</hi> formerly made uſe of the Hollanders to humble <hi>Spain,</hi> ſo the Spaniards are now glad of ſuccour of the United Provinces to humble the Pride of <hi>France:</hi> And the Moderation and Flegm of the Hollanders, proves very effectual to abate the Fury of the French, which only affrights thoſe the fear it, and are not acquainted with it.</p>
            <pb n="78" facs="tcp:39033:42"/>
            <p>In the Year 1672. the United Provinces alone made Head againſt the Two Potent Kings of <hi>France</hi> and <hi>England,</hi> were Victorious at Sea, and conſtrain'd the latter to make a Peace, and the other ſu'd for the Peace of <hi>Nimeghen.</hi> Tho' through a remiſsneſs Injurious to the Honour of the Parties, the Plenipo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentiaries, out of a Complyance not to be endur'd, ſuffer'd the ſlipping in of thoſe Words, <hi>That the King of</hi> France <hi>being deſirous to reſtore Peace to</hi> Europe, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Whereas it was he that begg'd for it, and made ſuch Condeſcentions to the City of <hi>Amſterdam,</hi> that ſhe conſented to it; ſo that to ſpeak properly, 'twas ſhe, and not <hi>Lewis</hi> XIV. that <hi>reſtored Peace to</hi> Europe. But in regard it was made without any great Precau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and without taking any other Guarranty, then the Sincerity of a Prince who never had any, therefore it laſted but a ſhort while; and within the ſpace of Six Years, the Peace-Reſtorer committed ſeveral Hoſtilities, took many Cities and Fortreſſes, ſo that there was need of a new Peace, and a Truce follow'd, to the end he might retain what he had uſurp'd: Nor were all theſe Treaties Mounds ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciently ſtrong to reſtrain the impetuous Torrent. He breaks through all the Tyes of Sanctity and Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, and falls upon <hi>Philipsburgh,</hi> the loſs of which was attended with ſeveral other ſcurvy Inconveniences. Now upon what Foundation could the States of the United Provinces treat with a King that obſerv'd no Rule of common Morality, but broke his Faith, his Word, his Promiſe, even with the Emperor himſelf. Certain barbarous People, whom <hi>Alexander the Great</hi> would have oblig'd to ſwear Fidelity to him, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn'd him anſwer, That they never ſwore any Oaths,
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:39033:42"/> but gave their Word, which they kept inviola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly; from whence I obſerve that they were not <hi>French.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Miniſtry of the Court of <hi>France</hi> imagines with it ſelf, that <hi>Lewis</hi> XIV. not having uſurp'd any thing upon the Republick of the United Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinces, during the Peace, nor won any Place from her, during the War, that it would be always an eaſie thing for their Monarch to make a Peace with her: beſides that, the Hollanders are greatly inclin'd to Peace, by reaſon of their Trade, which is much obſtructed in time of War; neither is it the Intereſt of a Republick, to enlarge her Confines, or to add new Provinces to thoſe ſhe has already, but to preſerve Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted what already ſhe poſſeſſes, and to ſecure her Frontiers the beſt ſhe can. But tho' <hi>France</hi> may be in the Right, as to ſome Circumſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, yet is ſhe deceiv'd in the main: For it is not ſo eaſie to make a Peace with the Hollanders, as the King of <hi>France</hi> imagines. Thoſe Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, tho' naturally good-natur'd and eaſie, are not readily twice deluded. That Prudence which never forſakes the Counſels of their Soveraigns, has ſeen, by the Conſequences of the Peace of <hi>Nimeghen,</hi> that there is no truſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to <hi>France;</hi> but that all her Promiſes and Treaties were only meer Amuſements, that is to ſay, a ſort of Recoiling to fetch the
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:39033:43"/> greater Leap: he muſt be a very mean Politi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cian, and very dull-ſighted, who does not per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cieve, that <hi>France</hi> had a great mind to have made her ſelf Miſtreſs of the United Provinces, their Wealth, and their Religion; thoſe three things ſo precious and ſo neceſſary, that the Inhabitants neither can nor ought to loſe 'em, but with their Lives. And therefore as they ventur'd all to purchaſe thoſe Bleſſings, ſo they will uſe their utmoſt Endeavours to preſerve 'em, as the moſt precious Jewels of the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>publick. For the Hollanders are not like King <hi>James,</hi> who left the care of his Crown to the Count of <hi>Lauſune,</hi> while he ran away before the Battel of the <hi>Boyne,</hi> and before his Perſon was in any evident Danger.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>France</hi> knows not as yet the ſtrength of the United Provinces, as being ignorant of what ſhe can do, if once ſhe be hard put to it: See<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that if they could find the way, not only to ſhake off the Chains of Servitude, but to make head for ſeveral Years againſt one of the moſt Potent, and one of the greateſt Monarchs of <hi>Europe, Philip</hi> II. and come off with Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, why ſhould the Miniſters of <hi>France</hi> flat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter themſelves under this Reign that they are able to deſtroy 'em? 'Tis only becauſe Men are apt to flatter themſelves that they can compaſs what they deſire; and generally they never
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:39033:43"/> care to be diſ-abus'd, in regard that Hope ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ports, and in ſome meaſure, ſatisfies an ambi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious Mind. Uſually the Court of <hi>France</hi> is crowded with Flatterers, who make no other Prayers then for the Glory of their Monarch, and ſing no other Hymns then in his Praiſe; all their Opera's ſound forth the Grandeur and the Conqueſts of their new Deity, <hi>Jupiter-Bourbon.</hi> They perſwade him that he was ſent into the World to reign by himſelf, and to ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>due all the People of the Earth under his Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minion; they have given him the Sirname of <hi>Dieu-donné,</hi> or <hi>God's Gift,</hi> and they make their Oblations to the immortal Man, <hi>Viro Immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tali.</hi> To which purpoſe they have erected his Statue in the Piazza of <hi>Victory,</hi> at <hi>Paris,</hi> to the end that all his Subjects ſhould pay the ſame Homages to his Figure as to his Perſon. Marſhal <hi>de la Fueillade</hi> would needs pay it the firſt Honours: For being a Collonel of the Foot-Regiment of Guards, he march'd his whole Regiment before the Idol, ſaluted it with his Pike, and order'd all his Soldiers to ſalute it with a Royal Volley; inſomuch that at firſt there was no Body durſt paſs by it, without ſome kind of Genuflexion. And by that Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue it is that Men may make a ſhrew'd Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jecture of the Deſign and good Intentions of <hi>Lewis</hi> XIV. ſince he had caus'd to be engrav'd upon the Pedeſtal of the Idol, the Hollanders,
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:39033:44"/> as well as other Nations link'd and chain'd to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether like Slaves under his Feet. By which 'tis eaſie to diſcern, as in a Mirror, the very inſide of <hi>Lewis</hi> XIV. and his kind Intentions toward the United Provinces, in caſe he could attain his Ends. And he diſcover'd his wicked Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſes ſo openly, after he thought himſelf aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſur'd of King <hi>James,</hi> upon his Elevation to the Throne by the haſten'd Death of <hi>Charles</hi> II. that 'twas the publick Diſcourſe in the Court of <hi>France,</hi> how they were going to fall upon the Hollanders, and that they would drown their Provinces under Water, to the end they might never riſe again, to vex the King by their oppoſing his juſt Deſigns. This was the common Language of the Court, and he that ſhould have contradicted it, would have been Empal'd after the Turkiſh manner. I muſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs, that at preſent they ſee with other Eyes at the French Court, and their Language is quite another thing. 'Tis the main Buſineſs of the Court at this time to flatter and careſs the Hollanders, by that means if ſhe can to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burthen her ſelf of a War too ponderous for a Kingdom groaning under Famine and many other Calamities; and which are more likely to encreaſe then abate. So that if the United Provinces, together with the reſt of the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſederates, do but ſtand their ſtation, tho' they ſhould gain no ground upon the Enemy, <hi>France</hi>
               <pb n="85" facs="tcp:39033:44"/> muſt be forc'd to condeſcend to what Condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions they pleaſe.</p>
            <p>But ſay ſome of the more peaceful and qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>et ſort of People, what Aſſurances have we of being able to conſtrain the King who makes Head againſt all the Confederates, to reſtore to <hi>Spain</hi> ſo many Towns and Fortreſſes, and ſo well fortifi'd, which he has in his Hands, to the end the Hollanders may enlarge their Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riers? I anſwer, That in this War the King of <hi>France</hi> is in an Aſſociation with the Turk, who by the Diverſion he makes, cuts out Work for the moſt conſiderable Forces of the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror and Empire: That the Ottoman Empire conſiſts of a capricious and giddy-headed Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, who have been ſeveral times of late, and indeed upon all the moſt conſiderable Occaſions defeated, and that by conſequence there is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of certainty for <hi>France</hi> to truſt to on that ſide, who only ſways the Port by the force of her Money, and a few frivolous Promiſes. So that there needs no more then an Inſurrection of the People, or a humour of the Grand Sig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nior, the Prime Viſier, or the Mufti, to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce a Treaty of Peace and overturn all the Hopes of <hi>France.</hi> Beſides, that if we do but conſider the Bottom of things, we ſhall find that this War which the Turk continues with ſo many Diſadvantages, coſts the French Year<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:39033:45"/> thoſe Summs which they are unwilling to boaſt of. Secondly, <hi>Lewis</hi> XIV. alone by himſelf, is bound to pay and maintain above Four hundred thouſand Men, to make head againſt his Enemies. Whereas the Confede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rates are not bound to keep ſo many Men in conſtant Pay; for the ſupply of which, every one bears his Proportion: nor does he that is moſt burthen'd bear a Fourth part of the Load of <hi>France.</hi> 'Tis true, the Body of the Confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derates is a bulky Fabrick, but it moves upon ſeveral Engines which makes it go the ſurer. Now I dare maintain, that 'tis impoſſible for the King of <hi>France,</hi> to act alone by himſelf, above Six Years, as he does, againſt a Confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derated Body, without ruining his People. At the long-run, the Soldier turns the Citizen out of his Houſe, and reduces him to beggary for want of Trade: The Taxes devour that little which the Inhabitants have heap'd up during the Peace. The Treaſury fails be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the Springs are grown dry; the Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chant is ruin'd by his Loſſes. The Cuſtoms and Gabells, which were formerly the beſt and moſt ready Money the King had, by reaſon of the great quantity of Salt that us'd to be utter'd all over the Kingdom, muſt needs be very low, when People want Money to buy Bread more then Salt. And 'tis not long ſince that I heard one of the Farmers ſay, That the
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:39033:45"/> Gabells of Salt are fallen above half in half; and it is the ſame thing with all the other Farms in <hi>France.</hi> A Monarch without a full Exchequer, is like a Man without Hands and Eyes.</p>
            <p>Of all the Soveraign Puiſſances at preſent in Confederacy with <hi>France,</hi> there is not any one can contribute more to her Ruine, then the United Provinces, and that two ways: the one by preventing all Commerce and all man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of Trade with <hi>France,</hi> and forbidding un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der ſevere Penalties the carrying of Proviſion and Corn to the Enemies Country; in regard that Merchants are greedy of Gain, and care not whether they ſupply Friends or Enemies: inſomuch that 'tis ſaid of ſome People, to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs their Extraordinary Thirſt after Profit, that if there were a Fair or Market in Hell, they would carry their Goods to the Infernal Gate, ſo they might put 'em off. The Other way to Ruine <hi>France,</hi> is to make themſelves Maſters of the Sea, which they might eaſily do in reſpect of the <hi>French,</hi> and by that means prevent any thing for going or coming out of the <hi>French</hi> Ports. Add to this, the Neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty that <hi>France</hi> is in to ſend for Horſes into the United Provinces, to remount her Caval<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, which it is in the Power of the States with eaſe to prevent.</p>
            <pb n="88" facs="tcp:39033:46"/>
            <p>Beſides all this, the United Provinces have had a vaſt advantage over <hi>France</hi> during the Continuance of this War, by the Trade which ſhe has driven all along into the <hi>Indies, Italy, Turky, Spain, England,</hi> the <hi>Baltick</hi> Sea, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> whereas the French have only <hi>Italy</hi> and <hi>Turky</hi> free to themſelves: for if they will have any thing from the <hi>Baltick</hi> Sea, they muſt put up Swediſh or Daniſh Colours to protect 'em from the Engliſh. On the other ſide, I muſt confeſs that ſeveral Merchants Ships of both Nations fall into the Hands of the French Capers, and a far greater Number then thoſe that are taken either by Dutch or Engliſh. But then we muſt conſider that there are a hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der'd Engliſh and Dutch Ships for one miſerable French-man, continually trading upon the Sea; and many times our Capers meet with French Prizes that are hardly worth the Taking. Then again the Number of French Privateers ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſes double and Treble the Number of the Dutch; in regard that the French Merchants having nothing elſe to do with their Veſſels, turn 'em all into Privateers, that ſo they may not lie idle. Inſomuch that all the Ports of <hi>France</hi> are become Neſts of Pyrates and Sea-rovers only. Nor do we find all this while that their ill-gotten Purchaſes enrich either the Soveraign or the People. For according
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:39033:46"/> to the common Proverb, <hi>That which is got with the Flute is ſpent with the Drum.</hi> And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it is, that the Inhabitants of St. <hi>Malo</hi>'s and ſome other Ports of <hi>France</hi> are not a little trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled, that they have no better employment then to addict themſelves to Pyracy; but their Trade with <hi>Holland</hi> and <hi>Spain</hi> being quite ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in'd for the preſent, they are conſtrain'd to turn Sea-rovers for their Subſiſtance.</p>
            <p>Now then we may aſſure our ſelves that 'tis ſo far from being the Intereſt of <hi>France</hi> to ruine and deſtroy the United Provinces, that 'tis the Study of all her moſt ſerious Policy to gain their Friendſhip, and inveigle 'em by fair Promiſes to accept a Peace, either ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate or general, becauſe the Intercourſe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the two States in times of Peace, brings more Profit to <hi>France</hi> then all the reſt of <hi>Europe</hi> beſides. But this Peace is not to be obtain'd by <hi>France</hi> either from the United Provinces or from any other of the Confederates but upon ſafe Conditions. For to ſuch a <hi>Dilemma</hi> has the Moſt Chriſtian King reduc'd himſelf, by begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning an Unjuſt and Cruel War, neither pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vok'd nor compell'd to it by any other Motives then thoſe of an Inordinate Ambition. So that it may be ſaid of the Sun, which <hi>Lewis</hi> XIV. has made choice of for his <hi>Impreſs,</hi> that it re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembles the Sun in <hi>March,</hi> which ſtirs and
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:39033:47"/> raiſes the Humours of the Body, but has not Heat ſufficient to conſume their Malignity.</p>
            <p>To ſay Truth, <hi>France</hi> may be look'd upon as one of the worſt Neighbours in the World: for ſhe lets no Prince alone that has the Miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortune to lie near her. So that after <hi>Lor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raine,</hi> the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Low-Countries and the Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Provinces had felt the Effects of her Fury, ſhe began again to proſecute her Old Deſigns upon <hi>Savoy.</hi> And the Firſt courſe ſhe took to get footing in that Family, was by the means of ſeveral Matches with French Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſes, to the End ſhe might have her Spies and Creatures in the very Beds of thoſe Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces. For that is one of the moſt Refin'd Pieces of French Policy for the King to make the Matches himſelf and to give 'em their Dowry, to engage 'em the more Cordially to his In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſts. And at the ſame time he ſends 'em home to their New Spouſes, full of Great Idea's of the Monarch of <hi>France,</hi> and the vaſt Obligations which they owe him, beſides that before their Departure, he cauſes 'em to Swear upon the Holy Evangeliſts, <hi>That for the future they ſhall be abſolutely devoted to</hi> France; <hi>that they ſhall uphold the Intereſts of that Crown at all Times and against all Perſons whatever, in the Courts where they reſide, and ſhall inform either him or his Miniſters of all that paſſes in their Huſbands
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:39033:47"/> Cabinets; and blindly obey the Orders that are ſent 'em by the King, or given by his Miniſter re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiding in the Court.</hi> And then there is no rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to wonder at the Troubles which <hi>Hen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rietta Maria,</hi> and <hi>Chriſtina,</hi> the Daughters of <hi>Hen.</hi> IV. marry'd by <hi>Lewis</hi> XIII. into <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Savoy,</hi> occaſion'd in thoſe Countries. The firſt never ceaſing till by her ill Conduct and exaſperating her Husband to act contrary to the Laws of the Kingdom, ſhe had brought <hi>Charles</hi> I. to an Untimely End; and her go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing into <hi>England</hi> may be ſaid to be as it were the Source and Leaven of all the Misfortunes that enſu'd in our days.</p>
            <p>Leaving <hi>England,</hi> take a view of the greateſt part of all the other Courts of <hi>Europe,</hi> and you ſhall find French Princeſſes who play their Parts with the Louidores of <hi>France.</hi> In <hi>Tuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cany,</hi> we have ſeen the preſent Grand Duke, that he might procure his own Peace at home, ſend a Bill of Divorce to the Grand Dutcheſs, his Wife, (who is a Princeſs of the Houſe of <hi>Orleance</hi>) and return her back to <hi>France,</hi> to undergo the ſame hard Fortune as <hi>Henrietta Maria,</hi> waſting the remainder of her Days in a mean Condition, depending upon the Incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant Humour of the King of <hi>France.</hi> To whom ſuch a return cannot chooſe but be a tacit Reproach of the Misfortune befallen her
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:39033:48"/> for upholding his Intereſts: But in regard that Large Conſciences are all the Mode of the Court of <hi>France,</hi> they can never be injur'd by Petty Stings or little Keckings. If you look upon <hi>Portugal,</hi> you ſhall find there Mademoi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelle <hi>d' Aumale</hi> marry'd to two Brothers one af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter another, tho' the firſt were alive at the time of the ſecond Marriage. King <hi>Alphonſo</hi> VI. ſomewhat moroſe by nature, and not wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to comply with the Counſels and Careſſes of that Princeſs, the Court of <hi>France</hi> found a way to be rid of that Prince, who was ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh'd to the Iſlands of <hi>Tercera,</hi> and his Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage after diſſolv'd by the Duke of <hi>Mercoeur,</hi> the Queen's Uncle, made a Cardinal at the Sollicitation of <hi>France,</hi> and ſent Legate into <hi>Portugal</hi> with a deſign to cut the Nuptial knot (a Secret all this while unknown to the Pope, who was ignorant of the Contrivances of the French Court) and tho' that during the Three firſt Months of the Marriage it was given out that the Queen was with Child, yet they parted the Wedded Couple for all that, under pretence of Impotency, and marry'd her to <hi>Don Pedro,</hi> Succeſſour to the Crown and her Husband's Brother; and if <hi>Charles</hi> II. of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> would have conſented to a Divorce be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween Him and Queen <hi>Katherine,</hi> the Court of <hi>France</hi> had deſign'd him the Princeſs of <hi>Nevers. Spain</hi> has ſeveral times experienc'd
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:39033:48"/> to her coſt, the fatal Conſequences of Matches with <hi>France:</hi> and his Royal Highneſs of <hi>Savoy</hi> at preſent ruling, had been within a Finger's breadth of loſing his Territories, had he purſu'd his Journey into <hi>Portugal,</hi> to eſpouſe the Infanta, at the earneſt Sollicitation of the Princeſs his Mother who is a French Woman, and by the Perſwaſion and Management of the Court of <hi>France,</hi> who were very Induſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous to procure that Match, on purpoſe to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>move the Duke out of his Dominions, and oblige him to ſtay in <hi>Portugal</hi> in Hopes of a Crown, while <hi>France</hi> took the Opportunity to make himſelf Maſter of <hi>Piemont</hi> and <hi>Savoy.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>France</hi> has been a long time contriving and ſtudying for a favourable Pretence to colour the the Execution of this Deſign. <hi>Harry</hi> the Great in his time agreed with the Duke of <hi>Savoy,</hi> that upon his reſigning up to him all the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenſions that the Duke had in <hi>Milanois,</hi> he ſhould oblige himſelf to conquer it, and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards exchange it for ſuch Lands as the Duke held on this ſide the Mountains, which conſiſt in <hi>Genevois,</hi> all the Principality of <hi>Niſſa,</hi> the County of <hi>Fouſſigni,</hi> and a part of <hi>Savoy</hi> as far as the <hi>Alps;</hi> to the end it might be in his Power to call himſelf Maſter from the <hi>Pyre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naeans</hi> to the <hi>Alps.</hi> But the Tragical End of <hi>Hen.</hi> IV. put a ſtop to that Enterprize. How<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:39033:49"/> it did not quench the greedy Thirſt of the Court of <hi>France,</hi> which was rather en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creas'd then abated, as we have ſeen, by what was aim'd at by the Match with <hi>Portugal,</hi> which Heaven prevented by a Kind of Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racle, his Royal Highneſs having already taken leave of his Eſtates.</p>
            <p>The Court of <hi>France</hi> has always ſo narrow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly watch'd the Duke, that ſhe thought it im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible for him to eſcape her Trains, or to withdraw himſelf from the King's Pleaſure, who had ſo near a Relation at the Court of <hi>Turin,</hi> that he had Intelligence of every thing which was acted there, and of every Petty Reſolution that was taken; and the main Bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſs was to hold the Duke under the King's <hi>Ferula;</hi> but above all, from holding any Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſpondence with the Houſe of <hi>Auſtria.</hi> And for proof of the Truth of this, it may be remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber'd that the Duke of <hi>Savoy</hi> could not go for his Diverſion to <hi>Venice</hi> with his Electoral High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of <hi>Bavaria,</hi> but he was follow'd and watch'd by the Envoy of <hi>France,</hi> who was then at his Court, and who knew ſo well to work and undermine with his Louidores, that he was inform'd of all that paſt at that Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>view. Which gave the Firſt Occaſion that Kindl'd the Fire of the War at preſent be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween <hi>France</hi> and <hi>Savoy.</hi> And tho' there be
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:39033:49"/> a great Diſproportion between the two Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenders, nevertheleſs the Duke gives no ſmall diſturbance and trouble to the Court of <hi>France<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> whether it be by the Alliances which the Duke has enter'd into, or by the Conſtitution of the Italian Climate, which has always coſt <hi>France</hi> a world of Men, as having been always call'd the <hi>Church-yard</hi> for the French; and notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding the inequality of Puiſſance, the King has been conſtrain'd to keep up a numerous and chargeable Army on that ſide, to which he is oblig'd to ſend, at vaſt Expences out of the <hi>Dauphinate</hi> and <hi>Provence,</hi> his Ammuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and Proviſion, for their Subſiſtance. More<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>over <hi>France</hi> never imagin'd that the Duke of <hi>Savoy</hi> could or durſt have undertaken any thing againſt her. For which reaſon the Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licy of <hi>France</hi> ne'er thought it worth while to fortifie her Frontiers on that ſide, to prevent in time of War the <hi>Savoyards</hi> from entring into <hi>Provence</hi> and the <hi>Dauphinate.</hi> Nor was ever the King more ſurpriz'd, or madder, then when he heard that the Confederates had got footing in thoſe two Provinces. So that had it not been for the Accident that befell his Royal Highneſs, and the unhappy Conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quences of his confiding too much in the Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuits of <hi>Ambrune,</hi> which was in part the Cauſe of the Return of his Army, certain it is that the Duke had enter'd Victorious into <hi>Grenoble.</hi>
               <pb n="96" facs="tcp:39033:50"/> The Dread of his March reach'd not only to <hi>Lion,</hi> but as far as <hi>Paris.</hi> A good part of the Inhabitants of the <hi>Dauphinate</hi> and <hi>Provence</hi> had already quitted their Country, but the Great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt part impatiently waited for the Conqueror's coming to deliver them out of their Miſery, and break their Chains: but they were fru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrated in their Hopes for the Reaſons above mention'd. The Court of <hi>France</hi> always flat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter'd her ſelf till now, that if ſhe reſtor'd to the Duke of <hi>Savoy</hi> ſome Town that ſhe had taken from him, that he would be glad to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>new his Alliance with her: Nay, ſhe believ'd it an Honour which he would ſue for; but ſhe found her ſelf deceiv'd. For ſhe met with a Haughty and undaunted Prince, who would not liſten to any Propoſals that tended to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unite him from his Confederates: and beſides, knowing <hi>France</hi> too well, his Royal Highneſs was abſolutely convinc'd, that there was no relying upon the Promiſes and Word of a King, much leſs upon the Faith of his Miniſters, who glory in deceiving thoſe with whom they have to deal, if any Benefit redounds from thence to <hi>France.</hi> The Court of <hi>France</hi> had her Aim and her Proſpects in her Offers which ſhe made laſt to the Duke of <hi>Savoy,</hi> and it was the Strife of her Policy to bring him off from the Confederates, and to have render'd him liable to their Ill Opinion; who would doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:39033:50"/> have abandon'd him, and thereby have left <hi>France</hi> at her Liberty to have invaded his Country. For ſhould <hi>France</hi> reſign to the Duke all the Places ſhe had taken from him, but keep <hi>Pignerol</hi> and <hi>Caſal</hi> in his Hands, that were ſtill no more then lying always between the Ham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer and the Anvil. His Royal Highneſs there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore having drawn his Sword againſt <hi>France,</hi> that continually oppreſs'd him, it behoves him never to ſheath it again, till he has pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cur'd his full Freedom, and ſecur'd himſelf from future Dangers, ſeeing he may well ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect to be ſincerely ſuccour'd by the Confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derates, who never will forſake him, but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways ſtick by him as hitherto they have done. So much the rather, becauſe they may be able in caſe the Catholick King dyes without Iſſue, to ſeat him in a better Station, to which he has already Great Pretenſions by the Marriage of <hi>Charles Emanuel,</hi> in the Year 1561. with <hi>Ka<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therine,</hi> Infanta of <hi>Spain,</hi> the Daughter of <hi>Philip</hi> II. So that by the Addition of <hi>Piemont</hi> to <hi>Milanois,</hi> he may take upon him the Name and Title of King of <hi>Lombardy:</hi> Which is an Advantage he can never attain to, if he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part from the Intereſts of the Houſe of <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtria,</hi> to embrace the Promiſes of <hi>France,</hi> which early or late will deceive him.</p>
            <p>'Tis never to be thought that <hi>France</hi> will
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:39033:51"/> ever mend, or that ſhe will act for the future with more Fidelity then hitherto ſhe has done. To truſt to her, would be for a Man to put a willing Cheat upon himſelf. The Black<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moor can never change his Skin, nor the Leo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pard alter his Spots: So <hi>France</hi> can never help her Uſurping upon her Neighbours: Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bition is an inveterate Diſeaſe that has ſeiz'd her, never to be Cured, but by the Proſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of the Confederates. I know very well that they flatter his Highneſs with a Match between the Duke of <hi>Burgundy</hi> (the Dauphin's Eldeſt Son, and who in his Turn may wear the Diadem of <hi>France</hi>) with one of the Young Princeſſes of <hi>Savoy:</hi> but this is ſtill to caſt Oyl into the Fire, and give <hi>France</hi> a New Handle to lay hold on, who is ready enough to graſp all Advantages without giving her an Oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity. Theſe are Baits, which the Emiſſaries of <hi>France</hi> throw about at a venture, to try whether they will take or no. If not, how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever it fails not to make ſome Impreſſion in the Breaſts of the Ladies, who being Members of the Frail Sex, eaſily fall into the Snare, and willingly feed themſelves with worldly Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours, never conſidering what they will coſt 'em, nor the Dangers that attend 'em.</p>
            <p>The Antipathy between the <hi>Danes</hi> and <hi>Swedes,</hi> whether it proceeds from any Hatred
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:39033:51"/> of the two Nations one of another, or from Intereſt of Trade, by reaſon that the Dominions of Both Kings lie ſo cloſe together, has in ſome meaſure parallel'd 'em with <hi>France</hi> and <hi>Spain.</hi> Which is the Reaſon that the King of <hi>France</hi> has always endeavour'd to procure their Ami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty; or at leaſt to have the one or the other on his ſide. And this has been his Care all along during this War, which began in 1672. at what time <hi>Sweden</hi> declar'd openly for <hi>France.</hi> Tho' he repented of it afterwards; whether it were by reaſon of his Ill Succeſs and the Advantage of the Electour of <hi>Brandenburgh,</hi> during that War, or the Infidelity of the Court of <hi>France,</hi> ſo far from obſerving her Word, that ſhe never pay'd the Money which ſhe promis'd to that Crown, but on the other ſide depriv'd the Northern Prince of his Dutchy of <hi>Deux Ponts.</hi> Which ill Uſage loſt the French all their Credit in the Court of <hi>Sweden,</hi> where they were afterwards look'd upon as Cheats: inſomuch that the Good Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſpondence formerly between thoſe two Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions turn'd into Hatred and Scorn. After this Change, in regard the Policy of <hi>France</hi> found it Convenient to have one of theſe two Northern Princes tack'd to her Intereſts, ſhe caſt her Affection upon <hi>Danemark,</hi> and ſo well ply'd the Miniſters of that Court with her Louidores, that now ſhe governs 'em as ſhe
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:39033:52"/> Pleaſes, and makes 'em daunce to the French Ayres. I muſt acknowledge that the King of <hi>France</hi> pays the Violins, but ſtill <hi>Lewis</hi> XIV. has the Pleaſure to ſee the <hi>Danes</hi> dance and foot it to his advantage. The Siege of <hi>Rat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>z<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nburgh</hi> coſt <hi>France</hi> Three hunder'd Thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand Crowns, which were pay'd at <hi>Hambo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rough,</hi> upon throwing the Firſt Bomb into that Fortreſs. For the Policy of the Court of <hi>France</hi> would needs venture that Summ at a time when ſhe had little reaſon to have ſpar'd it, in hopes that this Siege would have made a notable Diverſion, and that all the Princes of the Houſe of <hi>Luneburg</hi> would have recall'd all their Forces from the <hi>Low-Countries</hi> and the <hi>Rhine,</hi> to defend that Place. But here the French were cully'd by the Danes. For the Difference was made up between both Parties, <hi>France</hi> not being able to prevent the Reconciliation, which ſeem'd to her, to have been Impoſſible. But this is not the Firſt Attempt of the Court of <hi>France</hi> that has come to no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing: So that it cannot be ſaid that ſhe takes her meaſures ſo truly as never to be miſtaken; as her Emiſſaries give out with high applauſe. For to hear them Chatter, a man would ſwear that the Reſolves of the Cabinet of their Great Monarch were the Decrees of Heaven that never err; which <hi>France</hi> does often and more frequently then ſhe would her ſelf.</p>
            <pb n="101" facs="tcp:39033:52"/>
            <p>In the Preſent Conjuncture, <hi>France</hi> ready to ſink under the Burthen of a Long &amp; Chargeable War, makes uſe of <hi>Daniſh</hi> Flags and Veſſels, to get Corn and Naval Stores for her Men of War. In ſhort, at preſent ſhe embraces the <hi>Danes</hi> whom ſhe contemn'd before, as her on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Patrons and Deliverers to whom ſhe can have Recourſe: and ſhe would ſain have the King of <hi>Danemark</hi> declare War againſt the Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Provinces. The Miniſter of <hi>France</hi> reſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding at <hi>Coppenhaghen,</hi> is continually beating his Brains day and night, to furniſh the <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh</hi> Miniſters with Pretences to begin a Rup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture; he promiſes Ships and Money to aſſiſt 'em, and that tho' it ſhould be their Misfortune to come by the worſt, yet upon the making of the Peace he would never forſake 'em, no more then he did the <hi>Swede</hi> when the Peace of <hi>Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meghen</hi> was concluded. The Louidores of <hi>France</hi> are moſt alluring Baits at the Court of <hi>Coppenhaghen,</hi> but their Intereſt ſo undeniably requires 'em to hold a good Correſpondence with the <hi>Hollanders</hi> rather then with any other Nation, that only that Conſideration out-ballances all the Golden Perſuaſions of the French Embaſſadour <hi>Bonrepos;</hi> who having quitted his Religion to pleaſe his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, labours by all the Artifices of Fallacy and Deceit, to become ſerviceable to him, in
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:39033:53"/> acknowledgment of the Honour done him in ſending him upon an Embaſſy for which he thought him a more fit Perſon then any Body elſe, by reaſon of his Employment in the Sea Affairs under the Marquis of <hi>Segnalai.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But that which moſt embarraſes <hi>France</hi> and <hi>Danemark</hi> both together, is this, that <hi>Swede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> which is the far more potent Kingdom of the two, being engag'd in a ſtrict Alliance with the Emperor and the United Provinces, and having alſo Pretenſions to <hi>Danemark,</hi> will not be wanting to croſs the Enterprizes of the Daniſh King, who, all things being conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der'd, can ne'er hope for any great Aſſiſtance from the French, in the Preſent Conjuncture. Moreover ſuch is the Jealouſie between thoſe two Nations upon the ſcore of Trade, that the <hi>Danes</hi> are always afraid leaſt the <hi>Swedes</hi> ſhould be too hard for 'em, and agree with the <hi>Hollanders</hi> to furniſh 'em with all the Wood and other Naval Stores, which other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe they fetch from <hi>Danemark,</hi> and which would be a loſs to 'em that <hi>France</hi> would never be able to repair.</p>
            <p>If the King of <hi>France</hi> cannot oblige <hi>Dane<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mark</hi> to break with the United Provinces, he is bound at leaſt to procure as much Succour as he can from the North, and to make uſe
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:39033:53"/> of Daniſh Colours, to paſs freely without mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſtation, with promiſe to reimburſe all the Loſſes which the <hi>Danes</hi> ſhall ſuſtain by their Protection: in regard the Daniſh Miniſters readily foreſee that ſo great a Number of Paſs<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ports which they give, for Money, to all Veſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels, and all ſorts of Nations that deſire 'em, muſt at length open the Eyes of the Confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derates, and force 'em to put a ſtop to a Trade that only ſerves to carry Counterband Goods into <hi>France,</hi> contrary to Juſtice and Reaſon, and to the prejudice of the Treaties. <hi>Bonre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pos</hi> does all he can to continue this Game, and he keeps by him whole Reams of Blank Paſs<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ports, to fill 'em up in favour of thoſe who deſire 'em; and to encourge 'em to ſail for <hi>France</hi> he gives 'em to ſome, and promiſes 'em to others, and bequeaths himſelf a hunder'd Times a day to the Devil to aſſure 'em of the Honeſty and Sincerity of his Maſter. In ſhort, that Embaſſadour takes a world of Pains; ſo that if he ſucceed in his Negotiation, the King his Maſter may well beſtow upon him the Collar of the Order of St. <hi>Lewis,</hi> in recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence of his Toil and Labour, and in exchange for his Religion.</p>
            <p>The Count <hi>d' Avaux,</hi> a Cunning and Craf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty Miniſter, at preſent the French Embaſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dour at <hi>Sweden,</hi> is ſo well known in the World,
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:39033:54"/> that we ſhould do him wrong to write his Panegyrick He acted his part ſo well during his Embaſſy at the <hi>Hague,</hi> that his Maſter ſent him to King <hi>Jam<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> to aſſiſt him with his Counſel<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> during the Heroick Expedition of that Prince in <hi>Ireland.</hi> His Inſtructions are not altogether the ſame with thoſe of <hi>Bonre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pos</hi>'s at <hi>Coppenhaghen,</hi> becauſe thoſe two Courts are not both of one Opinion; and for that the Promiſes of <hi>France</hi> have not that Reputation at <hi>Stockholm</hi> as at <hi>Coppenhaghen.</hi> And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore while <hi>Bonrepos</hi> preſſes the <hi>Danes</hi> to a Rup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, <hi>d' Avaux</hi> only ſollicits the Court of <hi>Swe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den</hi> to ſtand Neuter, and to continue their Trade with <hi>France,</hi> or inſtead of that, to grant Paſsports to ſuch as ſhall deſire 'em, to the end that <hi>Sweden</hi> and <hi>Danemark</hi> may be equally con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern'd, in caſe the Confederates ſhould take diſguſt at the Great Number which the <hi>Dan<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s</hi> give out to all Commers. And indeed it is to be ſaid, to the Praiſe of <hi>Sweden,</hi> that that Crown has always acted ſincerely with her Confederates, and even with <hi>France</hi> it ſelf, at a time when <hi>Sweden</hi> could not have reap'd any great Advantages by a Correſpondence with her; and when no leſs ſedulous Endeavours were us'd to have drawn off the Court of <hi>Sweden</hi> from her. <hi>France</hi> has always courted <hi>Sweden,</hi> to remove the Obſtacles that continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally lie in her way: which is the Reaſon of that
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:39033:54"/> Infidelity of the French, who break with their Allies at all times, when the Humour takes 'em; and well underſtand that <hi>Sweden,</hi> being ſo potent and conſiderable, is able to counter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poize Affairs, provided ſhe will but concern her ſelf: For in that reſpect ſhe has always obſerv'd a very prudent Conduct, neither does ſhe approve all the Invaſions of the French. She knows the Truth of what M. <hi>Lyonne</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ports in his Memoirs, where he ſays, <hi>That there is not any State, which is not bound to oppoſe the Aggrandizement of the Court of</hi> France; <hi>and</hi> Sweden <hi>ab<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ve all the reſt ſeeing that if the King had taken the Low-Countries, he would have ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken no further notice of her, as believing he had no more Occ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſion for her.</hi> This is a ſolid Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion and to the purpoſe, and ought to make a deep Impreſſion in the minds of thoſe who have prejudice againſt the Court of <hi>Sw<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>den,</hi> either deluded by the Flat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teries of the Miniſters of <hi>France,</hi> or ſome baſe and ſordid Intereſt of their own, which greatly prevails in the world, and leads a world of People aſtray. But certain it is, that <hi>Swe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den</hi> has long ſince ſounded the Ambition and Arms of <hi>France,</hi> more eſpecially at the Peace of <hi>Oſnabrug;</hi> and if at any time ſhe hearkens to the Miniſters of <hi>France,</hi> 'tis without doubt becauſe ſhe finds ſome little pleaſure in drein<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>France,</hi> and doing her but little Good.</p>
            <pb n="106" facs="tcp:39033:55"/>
            <p>'Tis alſo certain and viſible that the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of <hi>Sweden</hi> and <hi>Danemark,</hi> who reſide in Foreign Courts, and more eſpecially in thoſe of the Confederates, are frequently and vigo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rouſly aſſail'd by the Emiſſaries of the French, on purpoſe to fiſh out, how Squares go among the Confederates, and may well retort upon the French Satans, the Words of the Lord's Prayer, <hi>Lead us not into Temptation, but deliver from Evil:</hi> but above all, from the Evil Spirits of <hi>France,</hi> that continually environ us. For indeed a man ought to be ſhod with Froſt-Nails, to preſerve himſelf from falling in ſuch ſlippery Ground, and he that can ſurmount thoſe Temptations, may well be number'd in the Catalogue of Upright Miniſters, and Faithful to the Intereſts of his Maſter.</p>
            <p>Corruption or Bribery is now a General Miſchief in the world, but never any advanc'd the Price of it ſo high as the King of <hi>France:</hi> for moſt certain it is, that that one ſingle Expence amounts to above Twenty Millions a Year. For it is a Thing paſt all diſpute, that <hi>France</hi> upholds her ſelf more by her Gold then by her Sword. 'Tis true, ſhe is many times put to her Plunges in time of War, which dreins her Exchequer, and enforces her to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance her Coin; by which ſhe gains conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derably.
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:39033:55"/> Formerly inſtead of enhauncing her Money, <hi>France</hi> made uſe of another Strata<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gem, which was to coin Louidores rais'd in value, but mix'd with a baſer Alloy then thoſe that went current in the Kingdom, which were diſtinguiſh'd by a little Mark quite diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent from others. And ſome there are in the Court of <hi>Danemark,</hi> who if they durſt own the Thing, could bring a Cloud of Witneſſes to make it out; as having experienc'd upon ſeveral Occaſions the full ſwing that French Knavery allow'd it ſelf. I know likewiſe, that the Thing was murmur'd at, but the Cheat paſs'd for that time, upon promiſe of doing better the next time. Therefore <hi>Charles</hi> II. King of <hi>England,</hi> who was well acquainted with the Knavery of <hi>France</hi> when he receiv'd any French Penſion, which was uſually pay'd him in Louidores, order'd the Receivers to cut 'em in two pieces, to ſee what Mettal they were made of; and then caus'd 'em to be refin'd into Guinea's. So natural it is for the Court of <hi>France,</hi> not to leave any Cheat omitted to defraud all thoſe that relie upon her.</p>
            <p>As for <hi>Poland,</hi> in regard it is a Kingdom re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mote from <hi>France,</hi> it can do her neither<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> any great Good, nor any great Harm; nor is there much Trade or much Communication
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:39033:56"/> between the Two Nations. Corn is the Only Merchandize wherein <hi>Poland</hi> abounds, and which it Tranſports from <hi>Dantzick</hi> into Fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reign Countries. But the Kings of <hi>Poland</hi> may in ſome meaſure ſometimes be profitable to the Deſigns of <hi>France,</hi> tho' it were only to moleſt the Emperour in many occaſions that may and frequently do fall out. For this Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon the King of <hi>France</hi> takes Great Care to ſend an Embaſſadour with Money to the Dyets, upon the Election of a New King; or elſe if they are not marry'd, to offer 'em a Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs born in <hi>France;</hi> and 'tis very probable that the French Embaſſadour <hi>Beauvais,</hi> and Cardinal <hi>Fourbin,</hi> who was then at the Dyet in <hi>Poland,</hi> contributed very much to the Electi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Preſent King; for which he has not been ungrateful. However he was guilty of two Bold Strokes, which tho' they were great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly for his Honour, were no way delightful to <hi>France.</hi> The Firſt was the King of <hi>Poland</hi>'s March to the Relief of <hi>Vienna,</hi> which was ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectually perform'd with the loſs of 60000 <hi>Turks</hi> to the great Grief of <hi>Lewis</hi> XIV. and contrary to his Expectation and his Wiſhes. And tho' ſome Remains of <hi>Decorum</hi> and Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour retain'd the Court of <hi>France</hi> from open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly diſplaying her Reſentment, yet the Silence of the French diſcover'd how much they were vex'd and mortify'd by it, at a time when all
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:39033:56"/> 
               <hi>Europe</hi> reſounded with loud Acclamations of Joy and Gladneſs, and all the Churches, with Thanks givings to Heaven. Only the Sorrow of <hi>France</hi> notoriouſly diſplay'd it ſelf, by her Prohibiting the Biſhops of the Conquer'd Cities in the Low-Countries to ſuffer <hi>Te De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ums</hi> to be ſung within their Dioceſſes.</p>
            <p>The ſecond Blow which his Majeſty of <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> gave to the Contrivances of <hi>France,</hi> was the Marriage of Prince <hi>James</hi> to one of the Princeſſes of <hi>Newburgh,</hi> Siſter to the Empreſs, notwithſtanding all the Oppoſitions of the French Miniſters, and particularly of the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quis of <hi>Arquin</hi> the Queen's Father; wherein the Conteſts grew ſo high, that the King of <hi>France</hi> order'd one of his Miniſters to tell his Majeſty of <hi>Poland,</hi> That ſince he could not hinder the Marriage, he would hinder the Prince from being King. But in theſe two Affairs the <hi>Polanders</hi> were guided by their real Intereſts; which was to bring down and ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ine the <hi>Turks,</hi> their ſworn Enemy and near Neighbour, as alſo aſſure to themſelves the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity and Alliance of the Emperour, and the Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perial Protection for the Prince his Son, when the Throne ſhould become vacant.</p>
            <p>But if the King of <hi>France</hi> prov'd unſucceſsful in the main, he has had his ſatisfaction in Part.
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:39033:57"/> For it is viſible that his Intrigues in the Court of <hi>Poland</hi> have a long time hinder'd his Poliſh Majeſty from being Maſter of <hi>Caminieck:</hi> for what could elſe have hinder'd him but the French Louidores? more eſpecially ſeeing the <hi>Polanders,</hi> ever ſince this War have had only to deal with a beaten, baffl'd Enemy, whom their Prince had defeated, and forc'd to riſe from before the Walls of <hi>Vienna</hi> with Igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miny and a Prodigious Slaughter. Neverthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs theſe Great Advantages produc'd no great Effect; tho' the Pope ſtill continu'd his Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plies of Money to carry on the War. But the reaſon is plain: for the Pernicious Policy of the Court of <hi>France,</hi> who was reſolv'd to march to the Succour of the <hi>Turk,</hi> her dear Confederate, wrought ſo powerfully at the Court of <hi>Poland,</hi> by means of the Queen, and Great Preſents, that the Louidores which tar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh'd the Honour of <hi>Poland,</hi> ſurmounted the Pope's Piety and his charitable Aſſiſtance both together. Moreover, the King of <hi>Poland</hi> being naturally Thrifty, and rightly judging that the Prince his Son may one day have need of ready Money, to hoiſt him into the Throne, had ſo much power over himſelf, and ſo much preſence of Mind as to keep both the Aſſiſtance of <hi>Rome,</hi> and the French Penſion. His Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty of <hi>Poland</hi> who is a wiſe and an underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Prince, knows alſo that Money is a good
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:39033:57"/> Moveable at a time of Need, and by a Knack of Prudence, the Criticks may call it Pitiful, Mechanick, and below himſelf if they pleaſe, he provides an Apple againſt he comes to be adry. But if this be the King's Weakneſs, 'tis the Strength of the Prince his Son.</p>
            <p>The Policy of <hi>France</hi> has this particular Gift, that it carefully ſtudies the Inclination of Princes, the weak ſides, and where lies the ſtrength of thoſe Courts into which ſhe ſtrives to introduce her ſelf, and get to be Miſtreſs of Miſrule. Thither ſhe ſends ſuch Perſons as are proper for the Genius of the People, either as Publick Miniſters, or private Spies. For Example, to ſend to the Courts of <hi>Italy,</hi> where Gallantry and Courtſhip abounds, ſuch Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons whoſe Principal Vertue conſiſts in hard Drinking, would be an Idle Thing, and ſpoil all. No, the Court of <hi>France</hi> is more refin'dly cunning then ſo; ſhe reſerves her Lovers of <hi>Bac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chus</hi>'s Liquor for the Courts of <hi>Germany,</hi> where the Temper of the Climate induces the People to drink, on purpoſe to ſteel their Bodies againſt Cold Weather, and there it is that frequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly between the Pear and the Cheeſe, they ſtrike the Home-ſtrokes and do their Buſineſs, when the Wine has warm'd their Courage. As for the Court of <hi>Poland,</hi> 'tis a Place where neither Courtſhip nor the Pleaſures of the
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:39033:58"/> Table are predominant, but the Powder of Gold prevails with a witneſs; and indeed not only there, but in moſt part of the Courts of <hi>Europe.</hi> There are few Courtiers and fewer Women, ſo void of Ambition as to be proof againſt the Attacks of Money: I mean, that can refuſe to embrace his Intereſts, who courts 'em in Showers of Louidores. They are ſuch Irreſiſtible Temptations to thoſe that are ſhort of Money, as it uſually happens in the Court of <hi>Poland,</hi> where Money does not tumble about proportionable to the Expence, and where the Courtiers are not ſo thrifty as the King. The French Men and French Women, who generally affect a Port anſwerable to the Grandeur of their Prince, many times ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice their Fortunes and their Honour, to ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der themſelves uſeful to their Country; and ſuch are eaſily gain'd: A Director of Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence works Miracles upon the Minds of ſuch People: and therefore the Policy of <hi>France</hi> is very Careful to maintain French, both Men and Women, in the Court of <hi>Poland;</hi> and the Miniſters of <hi>France</hi> are ſo dextrous as to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commend French Men to ſerve him, with the Character of Publick Miniſters in Foreign Courts, without any Expence to his Poliſh Majeſty; while <hi>France</hi> takes care to provide 'em a Maintenance; and by that means, the Court of <hi>France</hi> is inform'd of all that paſſes,
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:39033:58"/> not only in reſpect of the Affairs of <hi>Poland,</hi> but alſo of all that comes to the knowledge of the Miniſters in thoſe Courts where they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide: thoſe Miniſters having ſold themſelves to <hi>France,</hi> and only acting and actuated by the Spirit and Counſel of <hi>France</hi> their Benefactreſs. As we have ſeen by Experience at the <hi>Hague,</hi> during the Reſidence of the Sieur <hi>Moreau;</hi> and of which the Proceedings againſt <hi>Grandval</hi> and <hi>Demont</hi> are authentick Proofs. We ought to be convinc'd, that <hi>France</hi> would never have pay'd thoſe Miniſters, but that ſhe receiv'd ſome Benefit by 'em; more particularly in a time of War, when ſhe cannot ſend Embaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſadours to Princes in Confederacy againſt Her. For tho' that <hi>France</hi> has not any publick Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter in the Courts of her Enemies, neverthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs we find ſhe is inform'd of every thing that paſſes there; ſhe neglects nothing, but makes a dextrous Uſe of the Weak ſide of Princes that are willing to liſten to her, and takes her Advantage of all Opportunities. 'Tis the chiefeſt, and indeed the Main Policy of <hi>France,</hi> to ſurprize her Friends, as well as her Enemies; and therefore they had need be always upon their Guard, and always diſtruſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful of whatever <hi>France</hi> propoſes to 'em.</p>
            <p>The Kingdom of <hi>Portugal</hi> ſince the loſs of the Battel in 1578. was poſſeſs'd by the <hi>Moors,</hi>
               <pb n="114" facs="tcp:39033:59"/> and after that by the <hi>Spaniards</hi> till the Year 1641. at what time <hi>John</hi> of <hi>Braganſa,</hi> aſſiſted by <hi>France,</hi> and being the next Heir to the Crown, was declar'd King of <hi>Portugal;</hi> after a general Revolt of the Kingdom, which not being able any longer to endure the Oppreſſion of the <hi>Spaniards,</hi> ſhook off their Yoke under the Reign of <hi>Philip</hi> IV. The Kings of <hi>Spain</hi> always thought they had an Ample Right to <hi>Portugal,</hi> by vertue of a Donation from the Cardinal of <hi>Portugal</hi> the lawful Heir of the Crown after the Death of King <hi>Sebaſtian,</hi> his Brother, who dy'd without Iſſue. That Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinal being unwilling to quit the Prieſthood, was puſh'd forward by the Sollicitations of the Jeſuits, who beſieg'd him in ſuch a man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, that they never let him reſt, till he had made a Donation of the Kingdom of <hi>Portugal</hi> to <hi>Philip</hi> II. King of <hi>Spain;</hi> which could not be done to the Prejudice of the Lawful Heirs, whom the <hi>Spaniards,</hi> contrary to their Politicks, ſuffer'd to live and grow up in <hi>Portugal.</hi> Nor did they lie aſleep, but lay'd hold of the firſt Opportunity, as has been already ſaid. And certain it is, that <hi>France,</hi> ſpurr'd on by her own Intereſt, contributed toward it with all her Power: for indeed the Policy of <hi>France</hi> requiring the pulling down and ruine of <hi>Spain,</hi> ſhe could not take a better Courſe, then to diſmember and rend a whole Kingdom from
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:39033:59"/> the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Puiſſance; in regard that <hi>Spain</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſing in Dominions and Revenues, muſt needs decreaſe in Strength.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>France,</hi> during the Reign of <hi>Lewis</hi> XIII. and the Minority of <hi>Lewis</hi> XIV. had great cauſe to fear the Strength of <hi>Spain,</hi> but very little, to be afraid of the Strength of <hi>Portugal,</hi> tho' ſeparated from <hi>Spain.</hi> Quite the contrary, <hi>Portugal</hi> might well make uſe of <hi>France</hi> to moleſt <hi>Spain,</hi> which viſibly decreas'd, and perhaps will never be in a Condition again to pull that Thorn out of her Foot; and to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce <hi>Portugal</hi> under her Obedience. For af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter that Revolution which follow'd that of the Low-Countries, <hi>Spain</hi> languiſh'd away by degrees, and <hi>Portugal</hi> encreas'd both in Strength and Riches, and is become ſo Potent, that a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone by her ſelf ſhe can make head againſt <hi>Spain,</hi> which at this day reſembles a ſtrong Man con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſum'd and waſted by Inward Sickneſs and Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtempers, and eaſily overturn'd by the puny ſtrength of a Child.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Portuguezes</hi> therefore, who are good Politicians, underſtanding their own Intereſt, leagu'd themſelves with the Greateſt Enemies of the <hi>Spaniards,</hi> that is to ſay, the <hi>Engliſh</hi> and <hi>French,</hi> who in a time of neceſſity might openly declare for 'em, if <hi>Spain</hi> ſhould hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:39033:60"/> to be in a Condition to attack 'em. But now <hi>Portugal</hi> has no need of Aſſiſtance againſt <hi>Spain;</hi> much rather ſhe ought to fortifie her ſelf againſt <hi>France,</hi> which in this Reign has look'd with a Covetous Eye upon the Wealth that arrives at <hi>Lisbon</hi> from the <hi>Eaſt</hi> and and <hi>Weſt Indies;</hi> and I am perſwaded, that the Court of <hi>Portugal</hi> is truly convinc'd of it. Which was the reaſon that enduc'd 'em, to the no ſmall Vexation of <hi>France,</hi> to ſeek the Friendſhip and Alliance of the Houſe of <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtria,</hi> by the Marriage of <hi>Don Pedro</hi> to the Princeſs of <hi>Nieuburg.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>However the Policy of <hi>France,</hi> that under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtands without all doubt the Deſign of the <hi>Portuguezes,</hi> is careful at preſent to embrace the Friendſhip of the King of <hi>Portugal,</hi> to the end that during the War ſhe may have the free uſe of his Ports, to fetch Proviſions and Neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaries which ſhe can have no where elſe. And we have ſeen, not long ſince, that the French Men of War wanting Seamen, and fearing to be attack'd by the Engliſh and Hollanders, ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply'd themſelves from the Coaſts of <hi>Portugal.</hi> So that conſidering the Need which the French have of the <hi>Portuguezes,</hi> would <hi>Don Pedro</hi> and his Council make the beſt of ſo favourable an Opportunity, there is no doubt but the Houſe of <hi>Auſtria,</hi> would grant him very Advanta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geous
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:39033:60"/> Conditions, in caſe the Portuguezes would joyn with the Confederates, and declare War againſt <hi>France.</hi> And her Intereſt ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſes her to it; for that if the <hi>Dauphin,</hi> after the death of the Catholick King, ſhould get the upper hand in <hi>Spain,</hi> there's no queſtion to be made but he would revive the Pretenſions of <hi>Al<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>honſo</hi> King of <hi>Arragon,</hi> and <hi>Philip</hi> II. King of <hi>Spain:</hi> for by the ſame reaſon that for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly the Policy of <hi>France</hi> requir'd her to ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port <hi>Portugal,</hi> it would be then her Intereſt to ruine &amp; make her ſelf Maſter of it. 'Twere well that all the other Courts of <hi>Europe</hi> would do as <hi>France</hi> does, who foreſees things at a Great Diſtance, and continually builds Deſigns up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on a Baſis of Probable Futurity: and for fear of being deceiv'd, uſually forms three or four Contrivances which way to bring about one and the ſame Thing; ſo that if one fail, ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther may hold. This is a Piece of Human Prudence that not only prevents Surprize, but ſhews the way to undertake ſeveral En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terprizes, which elſe a Man would never have thought of. 'Tis a Maxim to be obſerv'd by all Sovereigns, to miſtruſt even their neareſt Allies, and ſo to act, as if they were juſt ready to come to a Rupture; more eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally they that border upon <hi>France,</hi> that never obſerves Peace or Treaty any longer then ſhe finds it for her Convenience.</p>
            <pb n="118" facs="tcp:39033:61"/>
            <p>The City of <hi>Paris</hi> abounds in Perſons full of Curioſity and Invention. Among the reſt, there are a Great Number of old Practitioners, who employ their Wits, to get Money, in ſearching for Claims and Rights in Old Parch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, a good part of which has ſerv'd to feed the Rats and Mice, and to invent and ſet up Titles: ſo that if they are but largely pay'd, they will prove their Benefactors Deſcent from the Royal Race, tho' before that, he could hardly reckon a Groom among all his Prede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſors. Theſe Antiquaries tell yee, that <hi>Por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tugal</hi> is deriv'd from <hi>Po<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tus Gallo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>um.</hi> Thus you you ſee a Foundation lay'd for the French to pretend, that <hi>Portugal</hi> belongs to <hi>France.</hi> Moreover there are ſtill to be ſeen among the Archives certain Ancient Regiſters (or if they are not there, they can find 'em elſewhere) containing the Expences that <hi>France</hi> was at ſome Ages ſince, in aſſiſting the Portuguezes againſt the Moors of <hi>Caſtile</hi> and <hi>Andaluſia,</hi> in the Reign of King <hi>Henry,</hi> who was of the Houſe of <hi>Lorrain,</hi> and marry'd the Natural Daughter of <hi>Alphonſo</hi> King of <hi>Arragon,</hi> who gave him an Army to conquer <hi>Portugal,</hi> or <hi>Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitania,</hi> from the Moors. Now there would not need ſo much, were this Affair once brought before the Tribunal of <hi>Metz,</hi> which is the Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raign and Irrevocable Court of Judicature to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termine
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:39033:61"/> the Right of the Dependences and Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendences of <hi>France.</hi> However the Germans would have the firſt Right; in regard it was to the aſſiſtance of that War-like Nation that <hi>Henry</hi> was beholding for the Conqueſt of <hi>L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſitania,</hi> as alſo of <hi>Algarva,</hi> which is the reaſon that the Germans enjoy ſuch Privileges all over <hi>Portugal.</hi> But here's the Miſchief of it, that if the Caſe ſhould come to be argu'd before the Deſpotick Tribunal of <hi>Me<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>z</hi> between the <hi>Germans</hi> and <hi>France,</hi> that Court would never do the <hi>Germans</hi> Juſtice.</p>
            <p>As for the <hi>Switzers,</hi> they are compos'd of Thirteen Cantons, which are as it were ſo many Separate Provinces, free and indepen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent one from another. Theſe Cantons ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving withdrawn themſelves from their Subje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction to the Emperour<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> by reaſon of the hard uſage which they ſuffer'd under the German Governours, bethought themſelves of a Demo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cratick Government, which they have upheld till this preſent time after they had ſuſtain'd ſeveral tedious Wars, and fought a great number of Battels, always Victorious, protected by Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, and by that means becoming ſo powerful as to be ſought to by the Emperour and the Neighbouring Princes. Th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y very rarely ſent Embaſſadours to the Potentates, their Confederates, unleſs it were to renew an Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liance,
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:39033:62"/> or upon ſome Extraordinary Occaſion However the ſame Princes have generally their Miniſters reſiding among them, but more-eſpecially <hi>France,</hi> whoſe Embaſſadour keeps his Station at <hi>Soleurre,</hi> tho' it be one of the meaneſt Cantons, and that <hi>Berne</hi> be one of the moſt powerful and the largeſt: for which we ſhall give the Reaſon in due Place.</p>
            <p>Any Prince who deſires the Aſſembling of a Dyet in <hi>Switzerland,</hi> muſt requeſt it by his Embaſſadour or Miniſter there reſiding; but he muſt pay for it: and therefore they never refuſe it to thoſe that deſire the Meeting, which would not elſe be ſummon'd, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently there would be no notice taken of the Buſineſs there intended to be propos'd. This ſame Coldneſs, natural to the <hi>Switzers,</hi> makes me believe, that that Nation cares not ſo much for the Friendſhip of their Confede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rates, as for their Money. However it be, this muſt be agreed in their behalf, that they are not only faithful to what they promiſe, but ſtout upon all occaſions, as we may ſee by fourteen Battels which they fought with the Emperour <hi>Ferderick,</hi> and three others which they won from <hi>Charles the Bold,</hi> the laſt Duke of <hi>Burgundy,</hi> and all the Brave Atchievements which they perform'd in <hi>Italy,</hi> as well for, as againſt <hi>France,</hi> under the Reign of <hi>Charles</hi> the VIII. <hi>Lewis</hi> XII.
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:39033:62"/> and <hi>Francis</hi> I. And for that reaſon it is, that ſince that time the Greateſt Potentates of <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rope</hi> have always ſought their Friendſhip and their Alliance; and that the French have ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſs'd 'em with a great deal of Artifice and Money; not ſo much out of any Kindneſs which the French have for the Switzers, or for the need which they have of their Men in time of Peace, but for fear leaſt the Cantons ſhould enter into a Solemn Engagement with the Houſe of <hi>Auſtria.</hi> For which reaſon <hi>France</hi> is careful to ſtipulate in all the Treaties which ſhe renews with the Cantons, that they ſhall not ſend above ſuch a number of Men to any other Foreign Princes, and thoſe only for the Guards of their Bodies.</p>
            <p>The Embaſſadour of <hi>France</hi> has made choice of <hi>Soleurre</hi> for the Place of his Abode, becauſe the Inhabitants of that Canton are all zealous Roman Catholicks; who pin their Faith with great Submiſſion upon the Sinceri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of their Curate: and the Embaſſadour re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides here, to ſhew the Particular Honour which his Maſter has for the Roman Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Cantons, above the Evangelick, and that the Monks and Prieſts may have free Acceſs to him, who bear a great Sway among the Catholicks. Moreover, the little Summs of Money which the Embaſſadour ſcatters a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:39033:63"/> the Chief of 'em, procure him Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, that ſtill will be inclin'd to the Intereſts of <hi>France,</hi> and readily ſtoop to the Lure. And by this means it was, that the French got leave to build the Fortreſs of <hi>Huninghen,</hi> which as long as it ſtands, will be a Hook in the Noſes of the Inhabitants of <hi>Bale,</hi> to lead 'em which way the Policy of <hi>France</hi> ſhall judge moſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venient for her purpoſes. Nor is it long ſince the Governour of that Fortreſs made an Eſſay whether the Cannon of that Place would reach as far as the City, that he might take his Meaſures accordingly. For whatſoever Proteſtations of Friendſhip <hi>France</hi> at preſent makes to the Cantons, <hi>Lewis</hi> the XIV. had rather be their Soveraign, then their Confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derate; that Monarch has a long time caſt a Covetous Eye upon <hi>Bale</hi> and <hi>Geneva,</hi> and had e're this, been Maſter of 'em, had not other Conſiderations kept him within Bounds; and were he once Maſter of thoſe Barricado's of <hi>Switzerland,</hi> the reſt would ſoon be expos'd to the Misfortune of lying fit for his Conve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nience. He is a Fox; but he has Lyon's Claws; and he makes uſe of his Head to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive the Catholick Cantons, under the Speci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Pretence of Propagating Catholicity; but he reſerves his Paws for the Proteſtant Cantons.</p>
            <pb n="123" facs="tcp:39033:63"/>
            <p>There is no queſtion, but that among the Switzers, among whom there are ſome who have travell'd and ſeen the World, there are to be found ſeveral Perſons ſufficiently quick-ſighted &amp; Politick, and ſuch as underſtand how Things are carry'd. 'Tis not long ſince a Dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference happen'd in the Canton of <hi>Glaris,</hi> which <hi>France</hi> firſt kindl'd, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>mented to the ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt of her Power; bu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Innocent</hi> the XI. quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſtifl'd it, by his Wiſdom and Piety.</p>
            <p>I am convinc'd that thoſe Perſons are deep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſenſible of the Affronts which <hi>France</hi> puts upon 'em from time to time, and with what Scorn ſhe treats their Embaſſadours, the laſt of which, were forc'd to return without being able to procure Audience of the King, after ſedulous Applications to <hi>Colbert Croiſy,</hi> Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretary of State for the Foreign Affairs. But the more prudent ſort of Switzers, you'll ſay, would fain have the Lyon chain'd, and his Claws par'd before they fall upon him. To which I Anſwer, That the Switzers may con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tribute very much toward the Chaining of the Lyon, as furious as he ſeems to be, and yet not openly declare themſelves neither; by de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manding the diſmantling of <hi>Huninghen,</hi> and for want of ſo doing, by recalling their Men out of <hi>France,</hi> which compoſe the greateſt part of the French Infantry, and are the only
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:39033:64"/> Combatants well ſeconded by the Cavalry, upon which the French depend for all their Succeſs. The King of <hi>France</hi> is now Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinc'd of the Value of the Switzers, and ſo has been, ever ſince <hi>Louvois</hi>'s Miniſtry. Formerly they were not well belov'd at Court, nay, they were contemn'd; but ſince the Altera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Face of Affairs, they are at preſent conſider'd, for the Benefit which <hi>France</hi> receives from 'em, like Twins that are ty'd together, and muſt dye together. I muſt confeſs that the Eſtabliſhment of the Swiſs Regiments is worth ſome Money to that Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and diſcharges the Country of abundance of idle lazy People: but I'll maintain it, that the French Service is the Plague and Deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of vaſt numbers of Young Men of Good Proteſtant Families that ruine themſelves by the Debaucheries of Wine and Women, which always terminates in a Revolt againſt their Religion and their Country. Which would never happen, if they ſerv'd the Proteſtant Princes. The Court of <hi>France</hi> knows well that ſhe cannot faſten an Officer of Quality to her Intereſts with a ſtronger Tye, ſo as to make him abſolutely forget his own Country, then by the Change of his Religion. And therefore ſhe Labours underhand by means of the Women and Monks; and thoſe Snares take Effect with the greateſt part that are at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tack'd
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:39033:64"/> by thoſe Vermin, as was ſeen by the Example of the Two <hi>Stoupa's.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Not to reckon the more Inferiour Sort, all the Swiſs Officers and Soldiers, as well thoſe that ſerve in <hi>France,</hi> as thoſe that are ſent to the Mines in <hi>Sweden,</hi> I look upon 'em equally loſt both to their Families and their Country; for they never return again, unleſs they make their Eſcapes by ſome ſort of Stratagem: but it may be ſaid, that the Pleaſure and Voluptu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs of <hi>France</hi> is ſo great, that they are pleas'd with their Misfortune. There they are bred, and there they dye, to make room for other New Commers, who are Tempted thither like Young Pigeons with the ſmell of Roaſted Dogs.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>France</hi> has had no place from whence to ſupply her ſelf during this War, but the Swiſs Cantons: Some Seamen ſhe may get indeed from the North: but for Land-Soldiers, of neceſſity it behoves her to careſs and embrace the Hel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vetian Body, without whoſe Aſſiſtance the French would never be able to bring ſuch Nu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merous Armies into the Field: And the Swit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zers are the Only Perſons upon which the King of <hi>France</hi> may depend, ſo long as he keeps his Word with 'em, and that he pays 'em what he contracts for, and what he promiſes. Nor
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:39033:65"/> will they ſtand to the Loſſes of his enhauncing and re-inhauncing his Money. They muſt have their Money pay'd according to the old value ſet down and agreed upon in ther Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracts; that is to ſay, the Louidores at Eleven Livres; and the White Crowns at Sixty Sols. For the Switzers are thrifty Husbands, and ſend a good part of their Pay to their Parents in <hi>Switzerland,</hi> where there is no Variation of the Coin admitted.</p>
            <p>Now it being ſo certain, as I have already ſaid, that <hi>France</hi> ſtands in need of the Switzers in this Conjuncture, this is the reaſon that the French Embaſſadour reſiding in <hi>Switzerland,</hi> has Orders not to diſguſt 'em, nor give 'em the leaſt Subject of Complaint, but in every Canton to careſs all thoſe in particular who have the beſt Intereſt, and carry the greateſt Sway<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> on purpoſe to prevent 'em from entring into a more ſtrict Alliance with the Houſe of <hi>Auſtria,</hi> the King of <hi>Great Britain,</hi> and the States of the United Provinces. For which reaſon it was that the French Miniſter us'd all his Power and Intereſt to ſtop the Levies which M. <hi>Cox,</hi> the King of <hi>Great Britain</hi>'s Envoy would have rais'd not long ago. But if the Bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſs did not then ſucceed, <hi>France</hi> is beholding for it to the want of Management in thoſe that underſtood not the right knack of dealing
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:39033:65"/> with the <hi>Switzers,</hi> ſeeing afterwards others found the way to diſcover the forward Incli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations of that Nation toward the Confede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rates, by the Levies that were made under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hand, which is a terrible Blow to <hi>France,</hi> in regard that thoſe new Regiments draw away a Great Number of their fellow Country-men out of the French Service, eſpecially the <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants.</hi> However, we do not find that <hi>France</hi> dares to make any great noiſe about it, moderating and reſtraining her Paſſion, till a more propitious Opportunity: but in regard the Cantons on the other ſide may be aſſur'd that ſhe Barrels it up, and that if at preſent they eſcape Scot-free, yet whenever it lies in her Power, <hi>France</hi> will never forget ſuch heinous Provocations; therefore 'tis now the Swit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zers Intereſts to labour with the reſt, the hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling <hi>France,</hi> now the Confederates are fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing her ſo cloſe at the Heels. For the Lower <hi>France</hi> is brought, the more the French will careſs the Switzers, and ſeek their Aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance; whereas in their Proſperity they ſlight and domineer over 'em, and would utterly ſubdue 'em, were it in the Power of the Court of <hi>France,</hi> that reſembles Fire or the Sea, which never will acknowledge they have e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough. But at preſent, the Policy of the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters prompts em, as the wiſeſt Courſe, to tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porize, and to oppoſe whatever is tranſacted to
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:39033:66"/> the Prejudice of <hi>France,</hi> rather by Remonſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces and Preſents, then by Force and Menaces.</p>
            <p>As for the <hi>Turks,</hi> they have been all along Enemies of Chriſt and the <hi>Chriſtians;</hi> becauſe the Goſpel deſtroys their <hi>Alcaron.</hi> The <hi>Sultan</hi> takes upon him the Title of <hi>Muſulman,</hi> or <hi>Moſt Faithful,</hi> as the King of <hi>France</hi> aſſumes the Title of <hi>Moſt Chriſtian.</hi> Yet we know, that the Turkiſh Emperours have eſtabliſh'd their Dominion by Cruelty only, and that their Throne is ſoder'd together with the Blood of a Great Number of Martyrs, and an Infinite number of all ſorts of People and Nations; yet notwithſtanding all this, the <hi>Turk</hi> is at preſent the ſole Refuge of <hi>France,</hi> and ſhe embraces him as her only Patron: She is enter'd into a ſtrict Alliance with the Ottoman Port; fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhes him with Money, Cannon, and other Warlike Ammunition; ſupplies him with Able and Expert Officers and Engineers, to the great damage of the <hi>Chriſtians.</hi> And which was more pernicious, the Policy of the Court of <hi>France</hi> exerted it ſelf to that degree, as to perſuade the <hi>Turk</hi> to break the Truce with the <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> two Years before it came to be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pir'd, meerly to ſupport the Rebellion of the <hi>Hungarians,</hi> who according to the Opinion of the Miniſters of <hi>France,</hi> were to contribute toward the Ruine of the Empire and Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour of the <hi>Chriſtians.</hi> Had the Biſhop of <hi>Perefixe</hi> been living at this time, he muſt have
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:39033:66"/> been forc'd to have recanted what he aſſerted in his Hiſtory of <hi>Henry</hi> IV. where he ſays, <hi>That the Valour of the French was made choice of by God, to ſupport the Chriſtian Religion.</hi> See<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that the Court of <hi>France</hi> labours nothing more earneſtly then to deſtroy the ſame Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion. She never minds whether or no the <hi>Turks</hi> change the Churches into Moſquees, or ſet up the Standard of <hi>Mahomet</hi> above the Croſs of Chriſt, provided her Monarch ſatisfie his Ambition and become Maſter of the Empire.</p>
            <p>Tho' the <hi>Turks</hi> are People both Barbarous and altogether Infidels, nevertheleſs they ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve this Maxim, never to abandon thoſe that put themſelves under their Protection, and to keep their Words and Promiſes; and this is one of the Points of their Law. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it is, that they acknowledge that all the Misfortunes and Loſſes which they have ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtain'd during this War, have proceeded from their Breach of Faith and Truce. And this it was which ſpurr'd 'em on about two Years ago to ſend their Envoys to <hi>Vienna,</hi> with Offers of Peace to the Emperour. Which hotly ala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum'd the Court of <hi>France;</hi> but ſhe, being Subtle and Crafty, took an Occaſion to inſinu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate into the <hi>Turks,</hi> That they might continue the War without any Scruple of Conſcience, ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing they had offer'd Peace to the Emperour, that he had refus'd it, and continu'd his Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtilities againſt them; That now the <hi>Turks</hi> who
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:39033:67"/> were to look upon the War as purely defenſive on their ſide; and the French Embaſſadour at the Port, underſtood ſo well by Conſiderable Preſents to gain the Grand <hi>Mufti</hi> to his ſide, who is the Oracle of the Ottoman Court and conſulted in all Caſes of Conſcience, that the Infidel Pontiff embrac'd the French Divinity, and made it out to the <hi>Sultan</hi> and the People, after the Return of the Envoys, that they might continue the War without any ſcruple, and that their Submiſſion to the <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> was a ſufficient Expiation for the Crime they had committed. Nor is it a difficult thing to perſuade the <hi>Turks</hi> to theſe Things, who naturally hate the <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> and are eaſily induc'd to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take their Deſtruction, and ſo Self-intereſted, as readily to yield to the Temptations of Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſents. Moreover their Extraordinary Inclinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and their Intereſt to recover <hi>Hungary</hi> which they have loſt, perſuades 'em without any Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luctancy to embrace the Propoſals of the Court of <hi>France,</hi> and to renew the League between 'em from time to time, upon the Aſſurances, Promiſes, and Oaths of the French Embaſſadour, that his Maſter will make no Peace with the Emperour, wherein the <hi>Turk</hi> ſhall not be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehended. And yet all the World knows how earneſtly the Miniſters of <hi>France</hi> ſollicit the Confederates to make a Peace without mentioning the <hi>Turk</hi> in the leaſt: and it was an Argument of the French at <hi>Rome</hi> to ſpur up
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:39033:67"/> the Pope, that a Peace would give the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour great Advantages, and ſtrengthen him to carry on his Conqueſts to the very Walls of <hi>Conſtantinople</hi> (for which <hi>France</hi> would not be a little Sorry.) But when theſe Projects of <hi>France</hi> were made known at the Ottoman Court, and that the Grand Viſier upbraided the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſour with 'em, he appeas'd the Prime Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter by telling him, That what the Court of <hi>France</hi> had done in reſpect to that Affair, was only to deceive his Enemies, and to amuſe 'em with Frivolous Offers, on purpoſe to put a ſtop to their Preparations againſt the next Cam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paign, and to make the People the more un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>willing to contribute toward the War. It may be, ſome Perſons well affected to <hi>France,</hi> take this to be a Calumny, and will not believe that the Moſt Chriſtian King perſuaded the <hi>Turk</hi> to break with the <hi>Chriſtians.</hi> But to convince 'em, I ſhall here inſert what paſt at the <hi>Pyre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nean</hi> Treaty, where <hi>Lewis</hi> XIV. eſpous'd the Infanta of <hi>Spain,</hi> renounc'd all the Pretenſions which that Princeſs might have to <hi>Spain</hi> or the Low-Countries, and conſented with an Oath, <hi>That if ever he Pretended to what he had renoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced, that his Pretenſion ſhould be accounted Null and Void, and that if he proceeded to force of Arms, he beſought all Princes and Free States</hi> (obſerve the Expreſſions) <hi>to repute it unlawful, unjuſt, and wickedly attempted, a Piece of Tyran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nical <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſurpation againſt Reaſon and Conſcience.</hi>
               <pb n="132" facs="tcp:39033:68"/> This Proteſtation is to be met with in the Sixth Article of the Renunciation of the King of <hi>France</hi> belonging to the <hi>Pyrenaean</hi> Treaty in the Year 1660. Nevertheleſs, we have ſeen how <hi>Lewis</hi> XIV. brake this Peace ſo ſolemnly ſworn in a few Years afterwards, immediately upon the death of <hi>Philip</hi> IV. King of <hi>Spain,</hi> on purpoſe to renew the renounc'd Pretenſions of his Queen, which have ſince coſt ſo much Chriſtian Blood, and ſtill are like to coſt more before the Concluſion of the War.</p>
            <p>Theſe Things being conſider'd, all Men muſt be convinc'd, that <hi>France</hi> fomented the War in <hi>Hungary,</hi> that ſhe encourag'd the Turks to beſiege <hi>Vienna,</hi> that ſhe deſign'd the Dethro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of the Emperour, and to have ſet up her Monarch <hi>Lewis the Great,</hi> in his Place. But ſhe met with many Diſappointments. The Great Victories of the <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> the Conqueſt of Upper and Lower <hi>Hungary,</hi> but above all, the Taking of <hi>Belgrade,</hi> together with the fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent Revolutions in the Ottoman Court, ran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers'd all the Affairs of that Empire: and then it was that all the Perſuaſions, nor all the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes nor Preſents of the French could make any Impreſſion upon the Turks; all the Policy of the Court of <hi>France</hi> was reduc'd to this laſt Shift, which was to perſuade the Ottoman Port to continue the War but one Campaign more, and then if the Face of Affairs did not alter, but that their Misfortunes continu'd, ſhe
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:39033:68"/> would conſent to a Truce ſuch as the Turks ſhould think fit to make. This Expedient wrought well for the French: For in the Year 1690. the Infidels re-took <hi>Belgrade</hi> by Aſſault, which puff'd 'em up to a high degree. Nor was it then a difficult thing to perſuade 'em that their Misfortunes were at an end, that Heaven was now going to puniſh the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour for refuſing the Peace which they had offer'd him; and that to ſecond this happy beginning, the King his Maſter or the Dau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phin (who was call'd the <hi>Young Sultan</hi> at the Port) would come in Perſon with a numerous Army; and make a Conſiderable Diverſion up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the <hi>Rhine.</hi> But in regard the Turks have never yet ſeen any Effects of theſe Mighty Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes, the French Embaſſadour is forc'd from time to time, to bear the Brunt of moſt bloody Reproaches from the Lips of the Grand Viſier, and to endure many a rugged Storm without going to Sea. And the leaſt affront put upon him is that of <hi>Dog; That his Maſter is a man of no Faith, and worſe then a</hi> Chriſtian; <hi>and that if he does not keep his Word for the future, the Port will make a Truce with the Emperour, and leave him to himſelf.</hi> But theſe are Reprimands which the French never boaſt of; and the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſadour has Flegm enough to ſtay till the Tempeſt be over, and never to return to the Charge with his Flamms and Excuſes, till the firſt firing be over, and that the Grand Viſier's
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:39033:69"/> Fury be abated; and then with new Preſents he makes freſh Promiſes, and like the Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, promiſes to do better next time. A ſad Conjuncture for a Monarch, who believes him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf to be the firſt and greateſt in the World, and ranks himſelf like <hi>Philip</hi> of <hi>Macedon</hi> and <hi>Alexander the Great,</hi> in the Number of the Gods, to be forc'd to ſuch mean Submiſſions, and to ſuffer continual Affronts and Reproa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches from an Infidel, to preſerve the Friendſhip and Aſſiſtance of the Turks. But this is now the Depth of the Policy of <hi>France,</hi> rather to Cringe and Creep, and become a kind of Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>butary to the Ottoman Port, then to make Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution of what he has uſurp'd from the <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stians:</hi> rather to allow Liberty of Conſcience to the <hi>Turks</hi> then to the <hi>Huguenots.</hi> And this I have been aſſur'd, that <hi>Chasteauneuf,</hi> the French Embaſſadour, not knowing one day which way to appeaſe the Grand Viſier, offer'd him that Liberty in his Maſters Name, and that he ſhould give leave to the <hi>Turks</hi> to erect Moſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quees at <hi>Tholoun</hi> and <hi>Marſeilles.</hi> The ſame Offers have alſo been made to the Governour of <hi>Algiers</hi> in any place of <hi>Bretaigne</hi> that he ſhould make choice of, provided he would ſend his Men of War into St. <hi>George</hi>'s Channel to rob the Engliſh and Hollanders. And if theſe Offers did not take Effect, 'twas becauſe the Grand Signior ſtood in need of the <hi>Algerines</hi> to ſerve againſt the <hi>Venetians,</hi> and re-inforce
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:39033:69"/> his Fleet in the <hi>Levant.</hi> Nevertheleſs, theſe Offers fail'd not to work with the Grand Mufti, who like the Romiſh Eccleſiaſticks, loves the Propagation of his Faith and the Free Exerciſe of his Religion; and who being ſwee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten'd up withall, by ſome Conſiderable Preſent openly declar'd for the French <hi>Sultan.</hi> But as ſubmiſſive as <hi>France</hi> is yet a while to her Ally, that ſhe may preſerve his Friendſhip, you ſhall ſee that he will leave him in the Lurch, and deliver him up a Prey to the Emperour, ſo ſoon as he can find a way to make Peace with the Confederates. And then that Sepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration would infallibly beget a War between the two Sultans, were the <hi>Turk</hi> in a condition to revenge himſelf. However his want of Strength to commence a War will not hinder him from loading the French Merchants that reſide in his Dominions with Terrible Oppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions; and ſo the poor Merchants muſt pay for the Infidelity of their Monarch. But the Court of <hi>France</hi> never troubles her Head about That, provided ſhe can but compaſs her own Ends. And for the Obtaining of thoſe, ſhe will never Spare for the Blood or Eſtates of her own Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects, nor did ſhe ever value the Lives and Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berties of ſo many poor <hi>Chriſtians</hi> as have been ſacrific'd during this War with the <hi>Turk,</hi> to the Ambition of <hi>Lewis the Great.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But we are now aſcending if we can, to the Pinacle of French Policy, ſo high that few or
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:39033:70"/> none can reach it; that is to ſay, the Depopu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation of <hi>France,</hi> and conſequently the Ruine of the Kingdom for Religion's ſake. For it is well known that the <hi>Proteſtants</hi> of <hi>France</hi> have always made a Conſiderable Body of that Realm, and tho' they have been Perſecuted and Maſſacred under divers Reigns, more-eſpecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in the Reigns of <hi>Charles</hi> IX. and <hi>Henry</hi> III. nevertheleſs they have ſtill reviv'd again and conſiderably encreas'd their Number; yet al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways faithfully devoted to the Service of their Soveraign: and that Fidelity obtain'd all thoſe Edicts of Pacification and Liberty of Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ennce, which were granted 'em by <hi>Henry</hi> IV. and <hi>Lewis</hi> XIII. For as the Hiſtorians them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves confeſs, the <hi>Huguenots</hi> were the Men that fix'd the Crowns upon the Heads of <hi>Henry</hi> IV. and his Offſpring <hi>Lewis</hi> XIII. and <hi>Lewis</hi> XIV. now Reigning, whoſe Crown, when he was Young and in his Minority, the Firſt Prince of the Blood would have wreſted from him, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending that the Succeſſion belong'd to him by Right of Birth after the Death of <hi>Lewis</hi> the XIII. openly aſſerting his Claim as well by word of Mouth as publick Manifeſto's, at the Time of the <hi>Pariſian Bar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>cado's.</hi> Nor could the King himſelf forbear to give Truth her due, in ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Declarations and Edicts, and by Letters written to the <hi>Proteſtant</hi> Princes. And indeed ſo Signal a Piece of Service, and a Devotion ſo faithful to the Perſon of this Monarch gave the
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:39033:70"/> 
               <hi>Proteſtants</hi> all the Encouragement in the World to hope for an Irrevocable Protection, and an Enlarg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of their Liberties &amp; Aſſurance of Safety both for themſelves and their Poſterity, not only during the Reign of this King, but alſo of his Succeſſours. Nevertheleſs, notwithſtanding all theſe Signal Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vices, they only obtain'd the Title of <hi>Faithful Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects,</hi> which the King affected to beſtow upon 'em in all his Edicts and Declarations. Nay their Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>delity was ſo diſſerviceable to 'em as to create no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but Fears and Jealouſies in the Prime Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters and Courtiers; and augmented the Natural Hatred of the Jeſuits, who all together from that time forward meditated nothing more then to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſe and ruine the Proteſtant Party, and inſpir'd into the Young Prince diſtruſtful Sentiments of thoſe to whom he was beholding for his Crown; perſwading him, that if the <hi>Huguenots</hi> were ſo powerful as to ſettle him in his Throne, they would be able at another time to throw him down again whenever he refus'd 'em any Privilege which they demanded. Theſe Diſturbers of the Repoſe of <hi>France</hi> having thus found the Monarch diſpos'd and inclin'd to follow their pernicious Counſels, the Jeſuits, Directors of the Prince's Conſcience, fail'd not to improve thoſe Sentiments ſo Oppoſite to his Real Intereſts and his Promis'd Faith; and for the Expiation of ſome Great Sin, impos'd upon him, by way of doing Pennance, the cancelling ſome Privileges granted to the <hi>Proteſtants</hi> by the King his Predeceſſours, and with an Oath confirm'd by
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:39033:71"/> the Reigning Prince. And as it is uſual for Scorn to degenerate into Hatred, the King having lay'd a Deſign to ruin the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nited Provinces,</hi> thought it then high time to begin with the Deſtruction of the <hi>Proteſtants</hi> of his Kingdom. And then it was that every Body ſtudy'd who ſhould be moſt for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward to ſecond the Bloody Deſign of their Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raign, and to invent new Torments for the more quick diſpatch of the <hi>Great Work,</hi> as the Court of <hi>France</hi> call'd it: and the King himſelf could not refrain himſelf from ſaying, That he would have the ſatisfaction, in his Life-time, of having the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour to deſtroy Hereſie, and that he had rather leave the Dauphin a Beggarly, then Heretical King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom; and thus enflam'd, Men, Women, Children, Monks and Miniſters of State, all cry'd out, <hi>To the Sack, to the Sack with the Churches of the</hi> Hugue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nots; and every one according to his Power lent a willing hand to the Diabolical Work. Madam <hi>de Maintenon,</hi> an Old Female Sinner, was the Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuits faithful and ſedulous ſhe-Intelligencer, who for that purpoſe held their Cabals both day and night: the Marquis of <hi>Louvois</hi> ſent away the Dra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>goons into the Provinces, and St. <hi>Ruth</hi> put in Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecution with great delight the Cruel Orders that were diſpatch'd from Court, and recommended to his Executioners and Hangmen the Care of tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menting the poor Creatures with all ſorts of Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bariſm and Cruelty. And while this Tragedy was acting in the ſeveral Provinces, the Chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellor <hi>Tellier,</hi> ſent forth Declaration upon Declara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:39033:71"/> againſt the <hi>Proteſtants,</hi> and iſſu'd out the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocation of all their Edicts, Privileges and Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, with ſo much Satisfaction, that as he was ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling the Revocation of the Edict of <hi>Nants,</hi> he could not forbear declaring, <hi>That it was the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt Bleſſing that ever overjoy'd him in his Life, and that he could be content, after he had ſeen that happy Day, to dye;</hi> and he was ſo impious as upon that Bloody occaſion to repeat the Song of <hi>Simeon:</hi> and indeed God took him at his word: for within a few days after he deliver'd <hi>France</hi> from that ſame Monſter of Men. However the Perſecuti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on did not ceaſe with the Life of that Miniſter, who left very good Diſciples behind him: for that Father <hi>La Chaiſe,</hi> finding one day the King in a Good Humour, obtain'd an Order from him for a General Maſſacre of the <hi>Huguenots</hi> all over <hi>France,</hi> grounding his Perſuaſions upon the Conſtancy of ſome of 'em, with whom the Priſons and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vents were cramm'd; and upon the Hypocriſie of the New Converts, who when Opportunity ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, would be as ſo many Enemies within the Kingdom, and that therefore there wanted a little Blood-letting to cure the Miſchief. And if this Order were not put in Execution, the <hi>Proteſtants</hi> were beholding to the Two Firſt Princes of the Blood, <hi>Condé</hi> and <hi>Contí,</hi> who took it out of Father <hi>La Chaiſe</hi>'s Hands, and return'd it to the King. This Perſecution, which produc'd nothing but Hypocrites and forc'd Catholicks, conſtrain'd a vaſt number of People to quit <hi>France,</hi> and retire
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:39033:72"/> with their Effects into Foreign Countries, contrary to the Expectation of the Court, and the Policy of the King and his Miniſters, who never intended to diſpeople the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, as the Spaniards did their Country, by expelling the Moors: and for fear of falling into the ſame Blunder again, they committed another as bad: ſetting forth Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gorous Prohibitions, forbidding all People to ſtir out of the Kingdom, guarding the Paſſes and ordering all to be brought back Priſoners that ſhould be taken upon the Frontiers, and filling the Priſons, Convents and Galleys with their Captives, which was very near the ſame thing as expelling 'em the Kingdom.</p>
            <p>All this ſo barbarous and unheard-of Uſage was pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meditated, however, notwithſtanding the outward ſhew of Piety, to be ſerviceable to the King's Deſign, as having been for ſome Years contriving the Utter Ruin of the <hi>Proteſtants:</hi> and therefore rightly judging that the Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentates their Confederates would never conſent to their Deſtruction, in regard their Downfall would only ſerve to aggrandize <hi>France,</hi> and augment her Strength in order to the carrying the whole Univerſe before Her; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Policy of the Court of <hi>France</hi> very ſillily believ'd that the Perſecution of the <hi>Huguenots</hi> would draw all the <hi>Catholicks</hi> into her Snares which ſhe had thus baited with her Pretended Zeal. But the ſame <hi>Catholicks</hi> being more diſcreet and wary, and well acquainted with the Tricks and Fineſſes of <hi>France</hi> compar'd the French Zeal to Crocodiles Tears, that weep to drill Paſſengers with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in their reach, and then darting themſelves upon their Prey, ſeize and devour it. Nay, the Pope himſelf ſmelt out the Cheat, and did all that lay in his Power to oppoſe it; as was apparently ſeen by the Buſineſs of <hi>Furſtenberg.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But tho' the Event has ſhew'd us that <hi>France</hi> was miſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken in her Calculation, yet ſhe ſtill goes on with her Proſecutions of the <hi>Proteſtants,</hi> tho' leſs at one time then another, in regard that 'tis the beſt way for Princes to
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:39033:72"/> go through with Follies begun, and for that the King's meaning was to make all <hi>Europe</hi> believe, that he had no other End then to make Proſelytes, and to propagate the Catholick Religion, which is a thing that moſt prudent and moderate Perſons of the ſame Religion could never perceive by what is paſt, nor diſcover in any Proſpect of Futurity. Nor has the King of <hi>France</hi> procur'd the leaſt Advantage to the Roman Church by his Oppreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons within his Kingdom, or by his perſuading and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veigling the Duke of <hi>Savoy</hi> to perſecute the <hi>Vaudois</hi> with the ſame Severity; quite contrary to the Sentiments of <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent</hi> XI. who openly diſapprov'd Violence in Matters of Religion, and who could not forbear ſaying, That at the ſame time that the French Embaſſadour made Bon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fires at <hi>Rome,</hi> and rejoyc'd for the Deſtruction of the French <hi>Huguenots,</hi> That his Heart bled Tears of Blood: foreſeeing that all thoſe Forc'd Converſions would one day prove extreamly Prejudicial to the Church: and that the King of <hi>France</hi> did but diſpoil himſelf of the Lovely Robe of Primitive Charity, to put on the Old Rags of Paganiſm, dy'd with the Blood of ſo many Martyrs.</p>
            <p>Moreover theſe abominable Proceedings of <hi>France</hi> have only ſerv'd to render the <hi>Catholicks</hi> ſuſpected to the <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants,</hi> and to beget a Scorn and Hatred of 'em in Pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces where before they liv'd together in Brotherly Love and good Correſpondence.</p>
            <p>But what is more Conſiderable, and for which <hi>Rome</hi> and all the <hi>Catholicks</hi> will have juſt Reaſon eternally to reproach <hi>France,</hi> and complain of her Monarch <hi>Lewis</hi> XIV. is this, That he preferr'd the Advance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of <hi>Mahometiſm</hi> before the Support and Preſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the <hi>Catholick</hi> Religion in <hi>England,</hi> quite ruin'd by the Dethroning of King <hi>James,</hi> whom he forſook in his Greateſt Neceſſity; more-eſpecially ſeeing that unfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunate Prince had never fallen into ſuch <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n Abyſs of Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſery, had he not follow'd the Pernicious Counſels of
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:39033:73"/> his Confederate who incens'd him to perſecute his Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects in <hi>England,</hi> as he had done his own in <hi>France;</hi> and to alter the Religion and Laws of his Realm, to ſerve the Intereſts and Deſigns of <hi>France.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But the Engliſh, more Prudent and Circumſpect then the French, foreſeeing the Tempeſt that began to gather already over their Heads; and of which the Conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quences could not but produce a Shipwrack, like to that which had ſwallow'd up the <hi>Proteſtants</hi> of <hi>France,</hi> ſeeing that the Dragoons began already to croſs over out of <hi>France</hi> into <hi>England,</hi> where there was a Father <hi>Peters</hi> ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mated with the ſame prepoſterous Zeal as Father <hi>La Chaiſe;</hi> and a Chancellor <hi>Jefferies</hi> no leſs wicked and bloody then <hi>Tellier</hi> or <hi>Louvois;</hi> the Engliſh, I ſay, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holding the Scaffolds erected, and the Fires juſt ready to be kindl'd, withdrew themſelves in time from the Yoke that <hi>France</hi> was preparing for their Necks; and by that Reſolution for ever daſh'd the vain-glorious Hopes of all the Engliſh Catholicks.</p>
            <p>In ſhort, the King of <hi>France</hi> has great Reaſon to repent of Two Things; his Perſecution of the <hi>Protestants</hi> of his Kingdom, and his laſt Siege of <hi>Philipsburgh.</hi> For that thoſe two Things were the Original Cauſe of the War, and the Baſis of all the Calamities with which <hi>France</hi> is at preſent overwhelm'd; and which daily augment beyond any Help or Remedy, which all the Policy of that Court, all the Wiles, the Artifices and Knavery of her Miniſters, and all the Bigotry of her Male and Female Hypocrites can apply to ſtop their ſpreading, or prevent the ſame Deſtiny from befalling the Reign of <hi>Lewis</hi> the Great as befell <hi>Antiochus,</hi> ſirnam'd <hi>Epiphanes</hi> or, <hi>The Illuſtrious:</hi> there being ſo great a Uniformity in their Manner of Acting, the Beginning and Progreſs of their Atchievements, that we have great Reaſon to hope, that their <hi>Exits</hi> will be the ſame.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:39033:73"/>
         </div>
         <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
